<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../books.xsd">
<editions ul="The Treasury of Knowledge" checked="true">
<edition id="1" lang="tib-wylie" title="shes bya kun khyab las bstan pa dam pa'i chos kyi rim pa" author="karma ngag dbang yon tan rgya mtsho"/>
<edition id="2" lang="en" title="The Treasury of Knowledge. Book Three. What the Buddha Taught" author="Jamgön Kongtrul Lodrö Tayé" translator="Kalu Rinpoché translation group"/>
</editions>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="gnas gsum pa">
[dam pa'i chos kyi rnam par gzhag pa rim par phye ba ste gnas gsum pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Book Three">
The Treasury of Knowledge
Book Three
What the Buddha Taught
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
@#/ /de ltar 'dul byed 'jig rten gyi sgron me ji ltar snang ba'i tshul legs par bshad nas/ ston pa de'i bstan pa dam pa'i chos kyi rnam par gzhag pa rim par phye ba ste gnas gsum pa la skabs bzhi/ dam pa'i chos ngos bzung ba/ lung gi chos 'khor bye brag tu dbye ba/ bka'i bsdu ba 'byung tshul/ zhar byung bstan pa'i gnas tshad bcas pa/ snga 'gyur rnying ma'i babs lugs bye brag tu bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
I have thoroughly presented above the advent of the light of the world who appeared here to guide beings.
Book Three, which systematically describes the outline of that teacher’s doctrine, the sacred teachings, has four chapters: (1) identification of the sacred teachings; (2) a detailed classification of cycles of scriptural transmission; (3) how the Buddha’s teachings were compiled, accompanied by supplementary explanations of the doctrine’s duration; and (4) a detailed explanation of the transmission of the early translations’ Ancient tradition.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="skabs dang po">
[1. dam pa'i chos ngos bzung ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Chapter 1">
1. What Are the Sacred Teachings?
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la gnyis/ bshad bya ngos bzung bas mtshams sbyar/ de'i don rgyas par bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This chapter has two parts: (1) an introduction to identify the subject, the sacred teachings, and (2) a full explanation of that subject.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
dang po [I. bshad bya ngos bzung bas mtshams sbyar] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
An Introduction to Identify the Subject, the Sacred Teachings [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
lha mi'i bla mas gdul bya 'dul ba yi/ /cho 'phrul gtso bo chos kyi 'khor lo ste/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The foremost miracle performed by the spiritual master of gods and humans to guide his disciples
Is that of turning the wheel of Dharma:
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sangs rgyas bcom ldan 'das lha dang mi la sogs pa 'gro ba thams cad kyi bla mar gyur pa des 'dul bya 'dul thabs kyi cho 'phrul bsam gyis mi khyab pa bstan pa thams cad 'dul ba rnam pa bzhi'i khongs su 'du zhing*/ /de thams cad kyi nang nas mchog gam gtso bor gyur pa ni dam pa'i chos kyi 'khor lo bskor ba nyid yin pas rgyas par bshad par bya ste zhes lhag bcas kyi sgras mtshams sbyar ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Buddha, Transcendent Conqueror, spiritual master of all beings, including gods and humans, displayed inconceivable miracles as ways to guide his disciples. All these miracles are included in the four techniques of guiding beings to enlightenment [i.e., through the body’s tremendous merit; the mind’s clairvoyance; inconceivable miraculous displays; and apt speech]. Among these, the most sublime, or foremost one, is his turning the wheel of Dharma. Therefore, it is this I will explain in detail.
The colon in the root text [te in Tibetan], a grammatical particle that indicates something left over, connects that passage to the next.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="II">
[II. de'i don rgyas par bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="II">
A Full Explanation of the Sacred Teachings [II]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la gsum/ ngo bo/ nges tshig_/dbye ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: (1) the essence of Dharma, (2) the etymology of the word Dharma, and (3) the classification of Dharma.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
dang po [A. ngo bo] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
The Essence of Dharma [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
ngo bo sgrib pa'i gnyen po rnam dkar phyogs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The essence [of Dharma] is a wholly positive quality, the antidote to obscurations.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dam pa'i chos kyi ngo bo ni ji skad du/ sdug bsngal dag ni thams cad dang*/ /sgrib kun sel byed dam pa'i chos/ /zhes pa ltar/ gang la tshul bzhin dmigs na lus can rnams kyi sgrib pa zad pa'i gnyen po rnam dkar phyogs su gyur pa'i yon tan zhig ste/ mtshan gzhi ni/ 'gog lam gyis bsdus pa'i zag med kyi chos rnams dang tshad ldan gyi bka' bstan bcos rnams yin zhing*/ de'ang snga ma ni brjod bya dang*/ phyi ma ni rjod byed kyi tshul gyis so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The holy Dharma’s essence is as follows. As it is said:
The holy Dharma
Dispels all sufferings and all obscurations.
When the holy Dharma is correctly focused upon, it is a wholly positive quality, the antidote that exhausts embodied beings’ obscurations. The Dharma is illustrated by the uncontaminated attributes gathered in [the truths of] cessation and the spiritual path, as well as the authoritative canon and treatises. The former [the truths] constitutes the subject; the latter [the words and texts] expresses it.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
gnyis pa [B. nges tshig] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
Etymology of the Word Dharma [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
nges tshig d+harma'i sgra las don bcu 'dzin/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The etymology of dharma: in Sanskrit, dharma has ten meanings.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
chos zhes bya ba'i nges tshig ni legs sbyar gyi skad du/ Dud+hr-inya? 'dzin pa'i byings las bsgrubs pa'i ng+harma zhes bya ba'i sgra las don bcu 'dzin pa'am/ de dag la 'jug ste/ 'dod 'jo las/ thams cad 'dzin pas na ng+harma ste chos so/ /zhes bshad do/ /don bcu ni rnam bshad rigs pa las/ chos ni shes bya lam dang ni/ /mya ngan 'das dang yid kyi yul/ /bsod nams tshe dang gsung rab dang*/ /'byung 'gyur nges dang chos lugs la'o/ /zhes 'byung ba ltar chos kyi sgra shes bya la 'jug pa ni dper na mdo las/ chos gang la la 'dus byas sam/ 'dus ma byas sam/ zhes dang*/ chos rnams thams cad de 'drar shes par gyis/ /zhes pa la sogs pa lta bu'o/ /lam la 'jug pa ni/ dge slong dag log pa'i lta ba ni chos ma yin la yang dag pa'i lta ba ni chos yin no/ /zhes pa lta bu dang*/ myang 'das la 'jug pa chos la skyabs su song ba/ zhes pa lta bu/ yid kyi yul la 'jug pa chos kyi skye mched/ ces pa lta bu/ bsod nams la 'jug pa/ btsun mo'i 'khor dang zhon nu ma rnams dang lhan cig tu chos spyod/ ces pa lta bu/ tshe la 'jug pa/ byis pa ni mthong ba'i chos gces par 'dzin pa yin/ ces pa lta bu/ gsung rab la 'jug pa/ dge slong chos zhes pa ni/ 'di lta ste/ mdo'i sde dang*/ dbyangs kyis bsnyad pa'i sde dang*/ zhes pa lta bu/ 'byung 'gyur la 'jug pa/ 'du byed kyi rdzas rnams ni de'i chos so/ /zhes dang*/ nga yang 'chi ba'i chos dang 'chi ba'i chos nyid las ma 'das so/ /zhes pa lta bu/ nges pa la 'jug pa/ dge slong gi chos bzhi zhes dang*/ dge slong dag srog gcod pa ni chos ma yin la/ srog gcod pa spang ba ni chos yin no/ /zhes sogs 'byung ba lta bu/ lugs la 'jug pa/ yul chos dang rig chos lta bu rnams so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Etymologically, [the Tibetan word] chos [pronounced “chö”] is the equivalent of the Sanskrit word dharma, derived from dudhrn, which means “to hold.” Dharma has ten meanings or denotes ten things. The Wish-Fulfilling Discourse states:
It holds everything; therefore it is dharma.
A Rational System of Exposition lists the ten meanings:
Dharma denotes phenomena, the spiritual path,
Transcendence of sorrow, the mental function’s domain,
Merit, life, scriptures,
Nature, specified conduct, and tradition.
As stated, (1) the word dharma denotes that which is knowable. To take examples from discourses,
Some things [dharma] are composite, some non-composite.
Further,
Know all phenomena [dharma] to be like that.
(2) Dharma denotes the spiritual path, as in the following:
O monks, an erroneous view is not the spiritual path [dharma]; A correct view is the path.
(3) Dharma denotes transcendence of sorrow: Having taken refuge in the Dharma...
(4) Dharma denotes the mental function’s domain: The sense bases’ domains [dharma]...
(5) Dharma denotes merit:
[The Buddha] enjoyed [the fruits of] merit [dharma] together with his circle of queens and youthful maidens...
(6) Dharma denotes life: Immature persons cherish the life [dharma] they see.
(7) Dharma denotes scriptures:
O monks, that which is called scripture [dharma] is the discourses, the melodious expressions, [and]...
(8) Dharma denotes nature: Composite substances have this nature [dharma]. Further,
Not even I have transcended the nature [dharma] of death, and the reality of death.
(9) Dharma denotes specified conduct:
The four regulations [dharmas] for a mendicant...
Moreover,
O monks, killing is not specified conduct [dharma]; renunciation of killing is specified conduct.
(10) Dharma denotes tradition, as in a country’s traditions [dharma] or a caste’s customs.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag 'dzin pa'i sgra don dang ji ltar 'brel snyam na/ shes bya rnams kyis ni rang dang spyi'i mtshan nyid 'dzin pa ste/ dper na sa ni sra ba'o/ /chu ni gsher ba'o/ /me ni tsha ba'o/ /rlung ni yang zhing g.yo ba'o/ /zhes pa lta bu rang mtshan dang*/ 'dus byas thams cad ni mi rtag pa'o/ /zag bcas thams cad ni sdug bsngal ba'o/ /chos thams cad ni bdag med pa'o/ /mya ngan las 'das pa ni zhi ba'o/ /zhes pa lta bu spyi mtshan 'dzin pa dang*/ lam dang myang 'das kyis ni 'khor bar ltung ba las 'dzin pa dang*/ yid yul gyis ni yid 'dzin pa dang*/ bsod nams kyis ngan 'gror ltung ba las 'dzin pa dang*/ tshe'am srog gis ni lus sam ris mthun 'dzin pa dang*/ gsung rab kyis ni don phyin ci ma log par 'dzin pa dang*/ 'byung 'gyur gyis 'byung rgyu'i chos de 'dzin pa dang*/ nges pas nges par bya ba'i gzhi 'dzin pa dang*/ lugs kyis ni rang dang mtshungs pa'i spyod pa 'dzin pa dang*/ rig pas ni 'khrul pa'i phyogs las 'dzin pa lta bur rigs pas dpag par bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
What is the connection between these and the meaning of the [Tibetan] word ’dzin [pronounced “dzin”], “to hold”? One can infer the logic [of the connection in the following illustrations]:
(1) Phenomena hold specific and general characteristics. Holding specific characteristics is illustrated in the following:
For example, earth is firm; water, wet; fire, hot; and wind, light
and mobile.
The general characteristics they hold [are expressed in this verse]:
All that is compounded is impermanent;
All that is contaminated is suffering;
All phenomena are without a self;
Transcendence of sorrow is peace.
(2 and 3) The path and transcendent states hold one from falling into the wheel of life. (4) The mental function’s domain holds the mind. (5) Merit holds one from falling into miserable existences. (6) Vitality, or life-force, holds the body or its genus. (7) Scriptures hold incontrovertible meaning. (8) Nature holds the seeds of future phenomena. (9) Specifications hold the basis for regulations. (10) Traditions preserve conduct that conforms to its own [customs]. Similarly, awareness holds one apart from delusion.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="C">
[C. dbye ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="C">
The Classification of Dharma [C]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gsum pa la gnyis/ dbye gzhi dang*/ dbye ba dngos so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the meaning of dharma which is the basis of this classification and (2) the actual classification of Dharma.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
dang po [1. dbye gzhi] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
The Meaning of Dharma Which Is the Basis of This Classification [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
de las 'gog lam gyis bsdus dam pa'i chos/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Among those meanings is the holy Dharma, comprising [the truths] of cessation and of the path.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bshad ma thag pa de dag rnams las skabs 'dir bstan par bya ba ni/ 'gog pa dang lam gyi bden pas bsdus pa'i dam pa'i chos nyid yin la/ mtshan de ldan gyi rgyu mtshan kyang*/ chos thams cad kyi mchog yin pas sam/ dam pa zhes bya ba rdzogs pa'i sangs rgyas/ chos ni des bstan pa yin pas sam/ yang na skyes bu dam pa rnams kyis spyad par bya ba'i chos yin pa'i phyir de skad ces bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Among those meanings just presented, what I will explain at this point is the holy Dharma, comprising the truths of cessation and of the path. The reason the “holy Dharma” has this appellation is that it is supreme among all phenomena. Alternatively, “holy” can refer to the perfect Buddha and “Dharma” to what he taught. Also, we say “Dharma” because it is the spiritual path (dharma) holy individuals engage in.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
[2. dbye ba dngos]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
The Actual Classification of Dharma [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la gnyis/ mdor bstan/ rgyas bshad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) a concise presentation of the classification of Dharma and (2) a full explanation of the classification of Dharma.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="a">
dang po [a. mdor bstan] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="a">
A Concise Presentation of the Classification of Dharma [a]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
dbye na brjod bya rtogs pa rjod byed lung*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In the classification of Dharma, there is realization, the subject; and the scriptural transmissions that express it.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
zhes pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="b">
[b. rgyas bshad]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="b">
A Full Explanation of the Classification of Dharma [b]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la gnyis/ brjod bya rtogs pa dang*/ rjod byed lung ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the subject, the Dharma of realization; and
(2) the scriptural transmissions that express realization.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="i">
dang po [i. brjod bya rtogs pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="i">
The Subject, the Dharma of Realization [i]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rtogs pa'i dam chos 'gog lam bden pa ste/ /'phags bzhi'i thugs rgyud gang zhig bral ba dang*/ /
gang gis bral byed gnyen po'i rang bzhin nyid/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The holy Dharma of realization comprises the truths of cessation and of the spiritual path:
These are the four kinds of exalted beings’ wisdom mind streams, which are free from any [attachment];
And the agent of that separation, which itself has the nature of antidotes.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de la rtogs pa dam pa'i chos la'ang rnam pa gnyis te 'gog pa dang lam gyi bden pa'o/ /
dang po ni/ rnam par rtog pas ma brtag cing brjod pa'i yul las 'das pas 'phags pa kho nas mkhyen pa'i phyir bsam du med pa dang*/ rang bzhin gyis zhi ba'i phyir gnyis su med pa dang*/ gzung 'dzin gyis spros pas dben pas rtog pa med pa ste mtshan nyid gsum ldan 'phags bzhi'i thugs rgyud kyi gnyen pos spang bya spangs pa gang zhig chags pa bral ba don dam pa'i bden pa'i ngo bo rtogs pa'i stobs kyis thob pa yin la/
gnyis pa ni/ nyi ma'i dkyil 'khor rang bzhin gyis dag cing 'od gsal la mun pa'i gnyen por gyur pa bzhin du nyes pa'i dri ma dag cing yon tan gyi 'od gsal la sgrib pa dang nyon mongs pa'i gnyen por gyur pa ste mtshan nyid sum ldan zag med kyi ye shes 'khor dang bcas pa gang gis chags pa dang bral bar byed pa kun rdzob gnyen po'i rang bzhin nyid de/ rgyud bla ma las/ bsam med gnyis med rtog med pa/ /dag gsal gnyen po'i phyogs nyid kyis/ /gang zhig gang gis chags bral ba/ /bden gnyis mtshan nyid can de chos/ /chags bral nyid ni 'gog pa dang*/ /lam gyi bden pa dag gis bsdus/ /go rim ji bzhin de dag kyang*/ /yon tan gsum gsum gyis rig bya/ /brtag min phyir dang brjod min phyir/ /'phags pas mkhyen phyir bsam med nyid/ /zhi nyid gnyis med rtog med de/ /dag sogs gsum ni nyi bzhin no/ /zhes pa ltar ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The holy Dharma of realization has two aspects: the truth of cessation and the truth of the spiritual path.
First, only exalted beings know [the truth of cessation]: concepts cannot analyze it and it surpasses the domain of expression. Therefore, it is inconceivable. It is naturally peaceful, therefore nondual. Dissociated from dualistic formulations, it is nonconceptual. Having these three characteristics, [the truth of cessation is the result of] antidotes applied in the four kinds of exalted beings’ wisdom mind streams; they have relinquished that which must be renounced. They attain cessation through the strength of realization of the essence of ultimate truth free from any attachment.
Second, the circle of the sun is naturally pure luminosity that acts as the antidote to darkness; likewise, [the truth of the spiritual path] is purified of faults’ defilements, and the qualities of its luminosity act as the antidote to obscurations and afflictive emotions. The path is that which is imbued with the three characteristics [mentioned in the last paragraph], accompanied by uncontaminated wisdom and its associated qualities, and it separates one from attachment. The spiritual path is relative [truth], the nature of antidotes. The Highest Continuity states:
Inconceivable, nondual, and nonconceptual,
Pure, clear, and belonging to antidotes—
The Dharma, which has the characteristic of the two truths,
Is free from attachment and is that which frees from attachment.
Freedom from attachment comprises
The truths of cessation and the path.
Know them in that order
With three qualities each:
[The first] is inconceivable, since it is inscrutable,
Inexpressible, and known by exalted beings—
Nondual, peace itself, and nonconceptual.
[The second] has three [qualities]: purity, etc., like the sun.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="ii">
[ii. rjod byed lung]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="ii">
The Scriptural Transmissions That Express Realization [ii]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa rjod byed lung bshad pa la gnyis/ mdor bsdus te bstan pa dang*/ de nyid rgyas par bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) a concise presentation and (2) a full explanation of scriptural transmissions.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="aa">
dang po [aa. mdor bsdus te bstan pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="aa">
A Concise Presentation of Scriptural Transmissions [aa]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
lung ni ngo bo'i sgo nas rnam pa bcus/ /legs gsungs bka' dang dgongs 'grel bstan bcos gnyis/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The essence of scriptural transmissions is twofold:
[The Buddha’s] words well spoken in ten ways and the treatises that elucidate [the Buddha’s] intent.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de la lung gi dam pa'i chos kyang ngo bo'i sgo nas dbye na rnam pa bcus legs par gsungs pa'i bka' dang*/ bka'i dgongs pa 'grel ba'i bstan bcos gnyis te/ lha'i bus zhus pa'i mdo las/ chos rnams thams cad bka' dang bstan bcos gnyis su 'dus/ /legs par gsungs dang de yi dgongs 'grel ba/ /zhes gsungs so/ /rnam pa bcu ni rnam bshad rigs par/ ji ltar na legs par gsungs pa yin zhe na/ rnam pa bcu dag gis te/ yang dag par bslang ba nyid kyis dang*/ dbang du mdzad pa nyid kyis dang*/ 'jug pa nyid kyis dang*/ rab tu bstan pa nyid kyis dang*/ rab tu dbye ba nyid kyis dang*/ rten nyid kyis dang*/ go bar mdzad pa nyid kyis dang*/ gdags pa nyid kyis dang*/ dus nyid kyis dang*/ yon tan yongs su 'dzin pa nyid kyis so/ /zhes bstan pa ste/ de'ang rim pa bzhin yang dag par mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas nas gsungs pa'i phyir dang*/ sems can thams cad kyi dbang du mdzad pa'i phyir dang*/ res 'ga' ba ma yin par rgyun du gsungs pa'i phyir dang*/ slob dpon gyi dpe mkhyud mi mnga' ba'i phyir dang*/ sems can gyi bsam pa ji lta ba bzhin du gsungs pa'i phyir dang*/ dbyangs kyi yan lag lnga dang ldan par gsungs pa'i phyir dang*/ dbyangs gcig gis 'jig rten mtha' yas khyab par mdzad pa'i phyir ram/ 'khor gyi dkyil 'khor ji snyed pas go bar mdzad de gsungs pa'i phyir dang*/ mtha' gnyis spangs pa'i lam gsungs pa'i phyir dang*/ gdul bya yongs su smin pa rnams la gsungs pa'i phyir dang*/ yon tan drug cu dang ldan par gsungs pa'i phyir ro/ /de la dbyangs kyi yan lag lnga ni/ 'brug sgra ltar zab pa dang*/ snyan cing 'jebs la rnar snyan pa dang*/ yid du 'ong zhing dga' bar byed pa dang*/ rnam par gsal zhing rnam par rig par byed pa dang*/ mnyan par 'os shing mi mthun pa med pa rnams so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
When the scriptural transmissions’ sacred teachings are classified in relation to their essence, they are twofold: [the Buddha’s] words well spoken in ten ways, and the treatises that elucidate his canon’s intent. The Discourse Requested by the Young God states:
Teachings are gathered into two collections: the Buddha’s words and the treatises. [The first are] well spoken; [the second] elucidate their intent.
A Rational System of Exposition lists the ten ways the Buddha’s words were well spoken:
In what ways were they well spoken? In ten ways: the nature of their (1) drawing from an authentic [source]; being (2) attuned, (3) engaged, (4) fully taught, and (5) diversified; (6) support; (7) creation of comprehension; (8) designations; (9) timing; and (10) being replete with qualities.
[To explain these ten, the Buddha’ words (1) are drawn from an authentic source] in that they were spoken following his manifest, perfect enlightenment; (2) they were attuned to all sentient beings’ capacities; (3) they were spoken continually, rather than on sporadic occasions; (4) the master did not conceal some topics; (5) the Buddha’s words were spoken according to beings’ exact interests; (6) they were endowed with five euphonic components; (7) each euphonic component pervaded infinite world-systems, or they were spoken to be comprehended by the entire range of the circle of the Buddha’s followers; (8) they delineate a spiritual path upon which the two extremes are relinquished; (9) they were spoken to spiritually mature disciples; (10) their delivery was imbued with the sixty qualities [of the Buddha’s speech].
The five euphonic components mentioned here are as follows: [the Buddha’s speech was] (1) deep like the sound of thunder, (2) melodious and pleasing to the ear, (3) appealing and delightful, (4) clear and intelligible in all respects, and (5) significant and not inconsistent.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag la rgya che ba la sogs pa'i yon tan lnga yod pas/ mnyan pa la sogs pa'i bya ba lnga byed de/ ji skad du/ slob dpon dbyig gnyen gyis/ yon tan lnga ni rgya chen dang*/ /snyan dang rig don ldan nyid dang*/ /gzung sla sna tshogs ci 'dod nyid/ /'di dag lnga yi yan lag ste/ /mnyan dang rnam par mi g.yeng dang*/ /rnam grol khong du chud pa dang*/ /smin par byed pa yin te des/ /thub chen gsung ni yan lag lnga/ /zhes legs par bshad do/ /gsung gi yon tan drug cu ni/ de bzhin gshegs pa'i gsang ba'i mdo las drug cu rtsa gnyis su 'byung ba thub pa dgongs rgyan du so sor rgyas par bshad pa'i sdom ni/ mnyan[1] 'jam[2] yid 'ong[3] yid[4] 'thad dag[5]/ /dri med[6] gsal[7] 'jebs[8] mnyan par 'os[9]/ /mi tshugs[10] snyan[11] 'dul[12] mi rtsub[13] dang*/ /mi brlang[14] rab dul[15] rna bar snyan[16]/ /lus[17] sems tshim[18] dang snying dga'[19] byed/ /bde[20] skyed yongs su gdung ba[21] med/ /shes bya[22] rig bya[23] rnam par gsal[24]/ /dga' bya[25] dga' 'os kun shes gzhug[26]/ /rnam[27] rig[28] rigs[29] 'brel[30] zlos[31] skyon med/ /seng[32] ge glang[33] 'brug[34] klu dbang[35] sgra/ /dri za[36] ka la[37] ping+ka'i dbyangs/ /tshangs[38] dang shang shang[39] te'u'i sgra/ /sgra[40] dang dbyangs[41] dang grags[42] pa bzung*/ /lha[43] dbang rnga[44] sgra ma[45] khengs pa/ /mi dma'[46] sgra kun[47] rjes su zhugs/ /zur[48] ma chag cing ma[49] tshang med/ /ma zhum[50] ma zhan[51] khyab[52] dang chub[53]/ /rgyun[54] chags 'brel[55] zhing sgra kun[56] rdzogs/ /dbang[57] po tshims byed ma smad[58] dang*/ /mi 'gyur[59] ma brtabs[60] khor yug[61] grags/ rnam pa thams cad mchog dang ldan/ /ces so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The words of the Buddha, having five qualities such as being wide ranging, etc., perform five functions, such as being audible, and so forth. These are well expressed by Master Vasubandhu:
These are the five qualities:
Wide ranging, pleasant sounding, imbued with the meaning of awareness,
Easy to retain, and varied according to the listener’s wishes.
These have five branches:
They are audible, they prevent distraction, they liberate,
They are conducive to understanding, and they bring the listener to spiritual maturity:
With these, the great sage’s speech has five branches.
On the subject of the sixty qualities of speech,
The Discourse Showing the Transcendent Buddhas’ Inconceivable Mysteries presents them as sixty-two;
The Ornament of the Sage’s Wisdom Mind explains each extensively. In summary, [the Buddha’s speech is said to be]
(1) Supple, (2) gentle, (3) compelling, (4) reasonable, (5) pure, (6) Flawless, (7) clear, (8) pleasant sounding, (9) worthwhile, (10) Unassailable, (11) pleasing, (12) calming, (13) not harsh, (14) Not inflexible, (15) perfectly restrained, (16) pleasing to the ear, (17) Satisfying to the body, (18) satisfying to the mind, (19) gladdening the heart, (20) Delightful, (21) never troubling, (22) Worth knowing, (23) worth understanding, (24) lucid, (25) Heartening, (26) exhilarating, (27) comprehensive, (28) Informative, (29) logical, (30) relevant, (31) without the fault of being repetitive, (32) Sounding like a lion, (33) sounding like an elephant, (34) sounding like a dragon, (35) sounding like the king of nagas, (36) Melodious like the celestial musicians, (37) melodious like a divine bird, (38) Sounding like Brahma, (39) sounding like a chakora bird, (40) Articulate, (41) melodious, (42) resonant, (43) [Resounding] like Indra’s [voice], (44) like a drum, (45) not vain, (46) Not degraded, (47) consistent with all forms of grammar, (48) Not deficient, (49) not incomplete, (50) Not timid, (51) not weak, (52) encompassing, (53) perfected, (54) Fluent, (55) coherent, (56) grammatically complete, (57) Satisfying to all senses, (58) irreproachable, (59) Reliable, (60) not rushed, (61) sounding all around, and (62) Sublime in every circumstance.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="bb">
[bb. de nyid rgyas par bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="bb">
The Full Explanation of Scriptural Transmissions [bb]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa rgyas par bshad pa la gnyis/ bka' dang*/ bstan bcos so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the canon and (2) the treatises.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1'">
[1'. bka']
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1'">
The Canon [1']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la gnyis/ ngo bo dang*/ dbye ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the essence of the canon and (2) classifications of the canon.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="a'">
dang po [a'. ngo bo] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="a'">
The Essence of the Canon [a']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bslab pa gsum brjod ngag tshig dri ma med/ /tshad ma gsum ldan thog mtha' bar dge ba/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The canon presents the three trainings, is expressed in flawless language,
Has three kinds of logic [as proof], and is virtuous in the beginning, middle, and end.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
zhes pa ste/ de la bka'i ngo bo ni/ brjod bya bslab pa gsum ston/ rjod byed ngag tshig dri med/ sgrub byed tshad ma gsum ldan/ 'bras bu thog mtha' bar du dge ba can yin te/ mgon po byams pas/ bslab pa gsum brjod ngag tshig dri ma med/ /tshad ma gsum ldan thog mtha' bar dge ba/ /de ni chen por gsungs ba rgyal ba'i bka'/ /bzlog pa gzhan gyi gzhung du shes par bya/ /zhes dang*/ 'dul ba 'od ldan las/ /bslab pa gsum ni rab ston zhing*/ phyag rgya gsum dang yang dag ldan/ /thog ma bar dang mthar dge ba/ /sangs rgyas gsung du mkhas pas rtogs/ /zhes gsungs pa ltar ro/ /'dir tshad ma gsum ni/ /mngon sum rjes dpag lung tshad ma'o/ /yang na rgyud bla ma las/ /gang zhig don ldan chos dang nyer 'brel zhing*/ /khams gsum kun nas nyon mongs spong byed gsung*/ /zhi ba'i phan yon ston par mdzad pa gang*/ /de ni drang srong gsung yin bzlog pa gzhan/ /zhes pa ltar/ /brjod bya don ldan gyi chos dang nye bar 'brel zhing*/ /byed las khams gsum gyi nyon mongs spong ba'i thabs su gyur ba/ /'bras bu mya ngan las 'das pa zhi ba'i phyogs su gzhol zhing 'bab pa'i ngag_/bdag rkyen gtso bor rdzogs pa'i sangs rgyas la brten nas byung ba'o/ /de'ang nges tshig gi dbang du byas na/ su b+hA Shi ta/ zhes legs par gsungs pa ste/ rnam bshad rigs par de la phyin ci ma log par yang dag par gsungs pa'i phyir legs par gsungs pa'o/ /zhes so/ /de'i don yang mdo las dam pa'i chos ni thog mar dge ba/ bar du dge ba/ tha mar dge ba/ don bzang po/ tshig 'bru bzang po/ ma 'dres pa/ yongs su rdzogs pa/ yongs su dag pa/ yongs su byang ba/ zhes gsungs pa'i tshul gyis te/
</d>
<d e="2">
The canon’s essence is described as follows: its subject presents the three trainings [in ethical conduct, meditative states, and sublime insight]; it is expressed in flawless language; its has three kinds of logic as proof; and its result is virtuous in the beginning, middle, and end. Lord Maitreya states:
The Victor’s canon presents the three trainings; its speech and
terms are flawless;
It has the three kinds of logic; and it is virtuous in the beginning,
middle, and end:
He spoke these teachings in the great way.
Anything opposite to this should be known as others’ texts.
Radiant Discipline states:
The wise know that the Buddha’s speech
Fully presents the three trainings,
Bears the authentic three seals,
And is virtuous in the beginning, middle, and end.
The three kinds of logic referred to here are [proofs based in] direct perception, inference, and scriptural authority. Further, The Highest Continuity states:
Speech fully connected to what is meaningful,
That causes the pervasive afflictive emotions of the three realms
to be relinquished,
And which reveals the benefits of peace
Is the Seer’s speech; the opposite belongs to other systems.
As stated, the subject of the Buddha’s speech is fully connected to what is meaningful. Its function is to serve as a means to relinquish the afflictive emotions of the three realms. Its result is speech that flows toward and descends into peace, the transcendence of sorrow. Its dominant causal condition is that it arose based upon the perfect Buddha.
The etymology of subhashita [Sanskrit for “well spoken”] is explained in A Rational System of Exposition:
Because it was spoken correctly and incontrovertibly, it was well spoken.
Its meaning is said in the discourses to relate to the mode of speaking:
The holy Dharma is virtuous in the beginning, virtuous in the
middle, and virtuous in the end; it contains excellent meanings and excellent words; it is unadulterated, fully complete, fully pure, and fully refined.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang slob dpon thogs med kyis/ thog mar dge ba ni nyan pa rnams rab tu dga' ba skyed pa'o/ /bar du dge ba ni rab tu sbyor ba rnams tshegs chung ngus mtha' gnyis rnam par spangs pa dbu ma'i lam la yang dag par brten pa'o/ /tha mar dge ba ni shin tu dri ma med pa dang*/ shin tu mthar phyin pa'i phyir dang*/ thams cad la 'dod chags dang bral ba dang*/ shin tu 'dod chags bral ba'i mthar gyur ba'i phyir ro/ /don bzang po ni phan pa dang bde ba dang ldan pa'i phyir ro/ /tshig 'bru bzang po ni ming gi tshogs la sogs par legs par sbyar ba dang*/ tshig tu 'don pa zur phyin pa dang ldan pa'o/ /ma 'dres pa ni 'di las phyi rol pa rnams dang thun mong ma yin pa'o/ /yongs su rdzogs pa ni tshad med pa'i phyir thams cad kyi mchog tu byung ba'o/ /yongs su dag pa ni rang bzhin rnam par grol ba'o/ /yongs su byang ba ni rgyud rnam par grol ba'o/ /zhes so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Moreover, Master Asanga states:
[The holy Dharma] is virtuous in the beginning: those who listen to it develop abundant joy. It is virtuous in the middle: those who thoroughly apply it relinquish the two extremes with little difficulty and rely purely on the middle way. It is virtuous in the end: it is totally flawless and totally perfected. It free from attachment to anything, since it is the culmination of freedom from attachment. It has excellent meanings: it is imbued with benefit and happiness. It has excellent words: it is well composed in its collection of terms, etc.; its verbal oration is complete. It is unadulterated: it is extraordinary when compared with non-Buddhist [teachings]. It is fully complete: since it is immeasurable, it is sublime among all. It is fully pure: its nature is liberation. It is fully refined: its coherent continuity is that of liberation.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="b'">
[b'. dbye ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="b'">
Classifications of the Canon [b']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la bzhi/ bdag rkyen gyi sgo nas dbye ba/ brjod bya'i sgo nas dbye ba/ rjod byed kyi sgo nas dbye ba/ dbang po'i rim pas dbye ba'o/
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has four parts: (1) classification of the canon according to its dominant cause, (2) classification of the canon according to its subjects, (3) classification of the canon according to its modes of expression, and (4) classification of the canon according to the disciples’ degrees of acumen.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="i'">
/de la dang po [i'. bdag rkyen gyi sgo nas dbye ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="i'">
Classification of the Canon according to Its Dominant Cause [i']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bdag rkyen sangs rgyas zhal nas gsungs pa dang*/ /sku gsung thugs byin brlabs dang rjes gnang ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In terms of its dominant cause, [the canon] was spoken by the Buddha;
Blessed by his wisdom body, speech, or mind; or authorized by him.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de bzhin gshegs pa'i gsung rab la dbye sgo mang yang gsung ba po bdag po'i rkyen gyi sgo nas dbye na gsum/ zhal nas gsungs pa'i bka' dang*/ byin gyis brlabs pa'i bka' dang*/ rjes su gnang ba'i bka'o/ /
dang po ni/ mdo sdud pa lta bu bcom ldan 'das nyid kyis dpal gyi mgur nas gsungs pa'i tshul bstan pa dang*/
gnyis pa ni/ sku gsung thugs kyi byin gyis brlabs pa gsum du slob dpon seng ge bzang pos bshad de/ de'ang skus byin gyis brlabs pa'i bka' rdo rje snying po'i spyi bor phyag bzhag nas byin gyis brlabs pas/ mdo sde sa bcu pa 'chad pa'i spobs pa skyes nas/ rnam par grol ba'i zla bas dris pa lta bu'o/ /gsung gis byin gyis brlabs pa'i bka' ni 'jam dpal la ma skyes dgra'i 'gyod pa sol cig ces bka' stsal pas/ 'jam dpal gyis ma skyes dgra'i 'gyod pa bsal ba'i mdo byung ba lta bu'o/ /thugs kyis byin gyis brlabs pa'i bka' ni bcom ldan 'das zab mo snang ba'i ting nge 'dzin la bzhugs nas/ shA ri'i bu dang spyan ras gzigs la byin gyis brlabs pas/ shes rab snying po gsungs pa lta bu'o/ /gzhan yang yon tan dang phrin las lhun gyis grub pa'i byin rlabs 'od zer bkye ba las de bzhin gshegs pa'i sku snang nas chos ston pa 'bum gyi gleng gzhi las bshad pa lta bu dang*/ ri dang*/ shing dang*/ bya dang*/ pad+ma dang*/ rnga bo che la sogs pa las chos kyi sgra dbyangs 'byung ba lta bu dang*/ nyan thos gang dag byin gyis brlabs pa'i mthu las chos smra ba dang*/ skyes pa dang*/ bud med dang*/ khye'u dang*/ bu mo la sogs pa phrin las chen po'i mthus chos smra ba dag kyang bkar bsdu ba ni/
</d>
<d e="2">
Among the many approaches to the classification of the Transcendent Buddha’s excellent speech, a classification based upon the perspective of the speaker—the dominant cause—yields three [categories]: the canon the Buddha spoke, the canon the Buddha blessed, and the canon the Buddha authorized.
The first refers to words the Transcendent Conqueror himself spoke from his glorious throat; for instance, The Concise Discourse on the Perfection of Sublime Insight.
Second, Master Haribhadra taught that [the canon the Buddha blessed] comprises words blessed by his wisdom body, speech, or mind. As an example of the canon his wisdom body blessed, [the Buddha] placed his hand in blessing on the crown of the head of [Bodhisattva] Vajra Heart. Thus, the confidence to expound The Discourse of Awakening’s Ten Stages was born in that bodhisattva, and Liberated Moon asked questions [to begin the teaching]. As an example of the canon his wisdom speech blessed, [the Buddha] ordered Manjushri to assuage Ajatashatru’s despair. This resulted in The Discourse to Assuage Ajatashatru’s Despair. As an example of the canon his wisdom mind blessed, the Transcendent Conqueror entered the meditative state of profound illumination and blessed Shariputra and All-Seeing One, who then spoke The Discourse of the Heart of the Perfection of Sublime Insight.
Further, [the Buddha’s] spontaneously present qualities’ and activities’ blessings shone lights that illuminated transcendent buddhas’ bodies, who taught the Dharma, as presented in the introduction to The Discourse on the Perfection of Sublime Insight in One Hundred Thousand Verses. [Likewise,] the teaching’s melodious sounds that emerged from mountains, trees, birds, lotuses, great drums, and so on; the teachings expressed by any pious attendant through the power of the Buddha’s blessing; and the teachings expressed by men, women, boys, girls, and others through the power of the Buddha’s supreme activity have been compiled in the canon.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sdud pa las/ rgyal ba'i nyan thos pa dag ji snyed chos ston dang*/ /'chad dang rigs pa dag dang ldan par brjod pa dang*/ /mchog 'phags bde ba byed dang de yi 'bras thob pa/ /de dag kun kyang de bzhin gshegs pa'i skyes bu'i mthu/ /ci phyir zhe na rgyal bas chos tshul gang bstan pa/ /de la mi mchog slob mar bcas pas sngon bslabs shing*/ mngon sum byas nas bslab pa ji bzhin ston byed pa/ /sangs rgyas mthus byed rang gi stobs kyi mthus ma yin/ /ces so/ /des na snga 'gyur gter ma'i phyogs su gter ston sprul pa'i skyes mchog rnams kyis shog ser gyi brda dang*/ dag snang dang*/ dgongs pa'i rtsal las byung ba rnams kyang lung dang rigs pa 'dis tshad mar grub pa yin no/ /
gsum pa ni/ bka'i sdud pa po rnams kyis/ mgor gleng gzhi/ bar du mtshams sbyor/ mthar mthun 'gyur la sogs pa bkod pa rnams te/ snying rje chen po pad dkar las/ kun dga' bo/ de na dge slong de dag gis khyod la de skad dris pa dang 'di skad lung ston cig_/'di skad bdag gis thos pa dus gcig na bcom ldan 'das dang po mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas nas yul ma ga d+hA na byang chub kyi snying po la bzhugs/ zhes sogs nas/ don dang tshig dang yi ge gang dang gang dag gis rnam grangs gang dang gang gsungs pa de la khyod kyis gleng gzhi dang bcas pa dang*/ rgyu dang bcas pa dang*/ rkyen dang bcas pa dang*/ don bzang po dang*/ tshig 'bru bzang po rgyas par ston cig_/mdo sde'i mjug tu'ang bcom ldan 'das kyis de skad ces bka' stsal nas thams cad dang ldan pa'i 'khor yi rangs te/ bcom ldan 'das kyis gsungs pa la mngon par bstod do/ /zhes bris shig_/kun dga' bo chos kyi tshul 'di de ltar yang dag par bsdu bar bya'o/ /zhes dang*/ lung las kyang*/ gnas ma dran na grong khyer drug po gang rung smros shig_/ces sogs rjes su gnang bar mdzad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Concise Discourse on the Perfection of Sublime Insight states:
However much the Victor’s pious attendants teach the Dharma,
Explain it, and expound it imbued with pure logic,
And thereby edify sublime exalted beings, and attain the results
[of their states],
All is [accomplished through] the power of the person of the
Transcendent Buddha.
Why is this so? In whichever modes the Victor taught the Dharma,
Those sublime humans first trained as his disciples,
[Gained] manifest [attainment], and taught according to that training. This is done by the Buddha’s power, not by the speaker’s own might.
This scripture and its reasoning validate the teachings which emerge from symbols written on yellow parchment, pure visions, or wisdom mind’s manifest expression produced by treasure revealers—the sublime emanated individuals belonging to the early translation school.
Third, [words the Buddha authorized refers to] the compliers of the canon’s compositions, such as those indicated in the introductions at the beginning [of texts], connections [between topics] in the middle, and affirmations at the end. The White Lotus of Great Compassion Discourse states:
Ananda, when those monks question you in that way, present scriptures in these words: “At one time, I heard these words: the Transcendent Conqueror first attained manifest, perfect enlightenment, then remained at the Heart of Awakening, in the region of Magadha...” and so on.
Then take any teaching I spoke using any meanings, terms, and words, and present it in detail with excellent meanings and excellent words, accompanied by an introduction, accompanied by an account of the teaching’s primary causes, and accompanied by an account of contributory conditions.
Then, at the end of discourses, add: “After the Transcendent Conqueror had spoken these words, the fully constituted circle of his disciples rejoiced: they manifestly praised the speech of the Transcendent Conqueror.”
Ananda, follow these conventions to compile the Dharma purely.
Moreover, the scriptures on monastic discipline state:
If you don’t remember the location of the teaching, declare it to be any of the six great cities.
In these and other ways, [the Buddha] granted his authorization.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="ii'">
gnyis pa [ii'. brjod bya'i sgo nas dbye ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="ii'">
Classification of the Canon according to Its Subjects [ii']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
brjod bya'i dbang byas rjod byed sde snod gsum/ /de yang tshul khrims 'dul ba ting 'dzin mdo/ /
shes rab bslabs pa mngon pas gtso bor ston/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
From the perspective of the canon’s subjects, its content comprises three collections.
The collection on discipline mainly teaches training in ethical conduct; the collection of discourses, training in meditative states;
And the collection on observed phenomena, training in sublime insight.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bka' thams cad brjod bya bslab pa gsum gtso bor ston pa'i dbang du byas nas rjod byed sde snod gsum du dbye na/ 'dul ba/ mdo sde/ mngon pa gsum mo/ /de yang*/ lhag pa tshul khrims kyi bslab pa brjod bya'i gtso bor ston pa'i rigs su gnas pa'i gsung rab ni 'dul ba'i sde snod/ lhag pa sems kyi bslab pa brjod bya'i gtso bor ston pa'i rigs su gnas pa'i gsung rab ni mdo sde'i sde snod/ lhag pa shes rab kyi bslab pa brjod bya'i gtso bor ston pa'i rigs su gnas pa'i gsung rab ni mngon pa'i sde snod kyi mtshan nyid do/ /de dag gi mtshan gzhi ni rim pa bzhin/ lung sde bzhi sogs dang*/ sher phyin 'bum pa sogs dang*/ mngon pa sde bdun sogs so/ /de dag gi ming don yang spyir sde snod ces bya ba legs sbyar skad du piT ka ste/ de gong bu dang bre'o che la 'jug phyir/ don mang po 'dus pas bre'o che lta bu ste/ bre'o che la bre'u chung mang po 'dus pa bzhin no/ /de ltar yang*/ slob dpon thogs med kyis/ ci'i phyir sde snod ces bya zhe na/ smras pa/ bsdus pa'i phyir te zhes bya ba ni don thams cad bsdus pa'i phyir ro/ /zhes sogs gsungs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The entire canon’s subject matter mainly presents the three trainings. From this perspective, the content is classified into three collections; these are the discipline, the discourses, and observed phenomena. Moreover, the excellent speech that mainly presents the subject of training in higher ethical conduct constitutes the collection on discipline. The excellent speech that mainly presents the subject of training in higher meditative states constitutes the collection of discourses. The excellent speech that mainly presents the subject of training in higher sublime insight constitutes the collection on observed phenomena. [This classification describes] the characteristics [of these three]. Works that embody these characteristics include, respectively, the four texts of the scriptural transmission [of discipline], The Discourse on the Perfection of Sublime Insight in One Hundred Thousand Verses, and the seven texts on observed phenomena.
On the subject of the term for these collections and its meaning, the general term [in Tibetan] for their name is sde snod [pronounced “dénö”] (collection), [the equivalent of the] Sanskrit pitaka, because this term denotes an agglomerate or a large measure. Since many meanings are included in each, [each collection] is like a large measure, just as a large measure contains many small measures. On this subject, master Asanga states:
Why are they called “collections”? The answer is that they are
inclusive, in that they include all meanings.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
nang gses 'dul ba'i mdo sogs dgur dbye bas/ /don gyi dbang du bslabs pa'ang dgu ru 'gyur/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Nine categories are found within [the three collections], such as discourses on discipline;
Thus in fact, the training is ninefold.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sde snod gsum po de la nang gses 'dul ba'i 'dul ba/ 'dul ba'i mdo sde la sogs pa dgur dbye ba gsungs pas/ don thob kyi dbang du bslabs pa gsum la'ang nang gses kyi dbye bas dgu ru 'gyur bar bzhed pa yin no/ /de'ang 'dul ba'i sde snod tshul khrims kyi bslab pa gtso bor ston pa las brtsams te/ 'dul ba'i 'dul ba bcas pa dang rang bzhin gyis rnam par gzhag pa che long rnams dang*/ 'dul ba'i mdo sde ting nge 'dzin dang tshangs par spyod pa rnal 'byor du bya ba'i rim pa dang*/ 'dul ba'i mngon pa de dag gi rab tu dbye ba rgya cher bshad pa la sogs pa rnams so/ /mdo sde'i sde snod gtso bor sems kyi bslab pa ston pa las/ mdo sde'i 'dul ba byang chub sems dpa'i sdom pa'i tshogs rnam par gzhag pa dang*/ mdo sde'i mdo sde ting nge 'dzin zab cing rgya che ba dang*/ mdo sde'i mngon pa sa dang lam dang gzungs dang ting nge 'dzin gyi rab tu dbye ba ji snyed pa rnams so/ /mngon pa'i sde snod shes rab kyi bslab pa gtso bor ston pa las/ mngon pa'i 'dul ba tshegs chung zhing sla ba'i thabs kyis nyon mongs pa 'dul ba rnams dang*/ mngon pa'i mdo sde de kho na nyid la 'jug pa'i tshul rgya mtsho dang*/ mngon pa'i mngon pa phung khams skye mched dbang po rnam shes sogs dang*/ de bzhin gshegs pa'i snying po'i khams rang bzhin gyis rnam par dag pa'i rab tu dbye ba cha dang bcas pa rnams so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The three collections are said to be divided into nine categories: the discipline’s internal structure includes the discipline’s discipline, discourses on discipline, etc. Therefore, it is thought that in fact the classification of the three trainings’ internal structure is ninefold.
On this subject, the discipline collection mainly teaches training in ethical conduct. With that as its point of departure, the discipline’s discipline gives rough overviews of the framework [of discipline] by presenting proscribed and natural [rules of conduct]. The discipline’s discourses present the stages of the contemplative practice of meditative states and pure conduct. Discipline’s [section on] observed phenomena comprises an extensive presentation of those topics.
The collection of discourses mainly teaches the training of the mind. Within it, the discourses’ discipline presents the framework for the many vows of a bodhisattva. The discourses’ discourses present profound and vast meditative states. The discourses’ section on observed phenomena presents the entire range of the topics of awakening’s stages and paths, retention mantras, and meditative states.
The collection on observed phenomena mainly teaches the training in sublime insight. Within it, the collection on observed phenomena’s section on discipline presents instruction in easy techniques for subduing the afflictive emotions without much difficulty. The collection on observed phenomena’s discourses present an ocean of ways to enter suchness. The collection on observed phenomena’s section on observed phenomena presents topics that include the aggregates, sense constituents, sense bases, sense faculties, and consciousness; and constituent buddha nature, which is naturally pure.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
gzhan yang so byang sngags la sde snod dgu/ /ming rkyang dang ni lhag dang zab sgras brgyan/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Otherwise, there are nine collections in the individual liberation, bodhisattva, and secret mantra [systems].
[The three collections bear their] simple names, or can be adorned with the terms “higher,” or “profound.”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bshad ma thag pa der ma zad sde snod gsum po la dbye tshul gzhan yang yod de/ theg dman so thar gyi dbang du byas pa gsum/ theg chen byang sems kyi dbang du byas pa gsum/ gsang sngags rdo rje theg pa'i dbang du byas pa gsum ste bsdams pas sde snod dgu ru 'gyur zhing*/ de dag kyang rim par 'dul mdo mngon pa'i sde snod ming rkyang tsam phyi'i sde snod dang*/ lhag pa'i bslab pa gsum ston pa'i cha nas ston byed sde snod la'ang lhag pa'i sgra don gyis thob pa dang*/ zab mo nang gi don ston pas zab mo'i 'dul ba sogs kyi sgras brgyan pa nang gi sde snod de/ 'dul dang mdo sde phyir shes pas/ /nyan rang 'bras bu thob byed de/ /zab mo'i mdo 'dul mngon pa rnams/ /spyod byed byang chub sems dpar 'gyur/ /zhes sogs 'byung bas rgyal ba gnyis pa rang byung zhabs kyi don gyi bzhed pa yang dag pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In addition to what was just presented, other ways to classify the three collections exist: from the perspective of the lesser way’s individual liberation system, there are three collections; from the perspective of the great way’s bodhisattva system, there are three collections; and from the perspective of the secret mantra vajra way’s system, there are three collections, a total of nine collections.
Further, the mere simple names of, in order, the collections on discipline, of discourses, and on observed phenomena refer to the outer collections. Since the collections teach the three higher trainings, this is indicated by adding the term “higher” (as in “higher discipline,” etc.) to the collections. Since they teach the deep inner meaning, the word [profound] can adorn them (as in “profound discipline,” etc.). [The latter two] are [referred to as] the inner collections. As is said,
Knowledge of outer disciplines and discourses
Effects the results of the pious attendants and solitary sages.
The profound discourses, discipline, and observed phenomena
[Effect the result] of an actively engaged bodhisattva.
This reflects the authoritative ultimate viewpoint of the second Victor, Venerable Rangjung Dorjé.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
mdo 'dul mngon pa rgyu mtshan bzhi bzhis brjod/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
They are called “discourses,” “discipline,” and “observed phenomena” for four reasons each.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
mdo 'dul mngon pa zhes bya ba'ang nges tshig gi dbang du byas na rgyu mtshan bzhi bzhi ldan pas der brjod pa ste/ de la mdo sde zhes bya ba sU tra ste don gyi sdom smos pa yin la de'ang rnam pa bzhi ste/ mdo sde rgyan las/ gnas rnams dang ni mtshan nyid dang*/ /chos don smos phyir mdo yin no/ /zhes 'byung ba ltar yul gang du gang zag gang gi phyir gsungs pa smos pas gnas dang*/ kun rdzob dang don dam pa'i bden pa'i mtshan nyid smos pas mtshan nyid dang*/ phung khams skye mched la sogs pa smos pas chos dang*/ dgongs pa'i don zab mo dag ston pas don no/ /'dul ba zhes bya ba ni bi na ya ste/ mdo rgyan las/ ltung dang 'byung dang ldang ba dang*/ /nges par 'byung dang gang zag dang*/ /bcas pa dang ni rab dbye dang*/ /rnam par nges phyir 'dul ba nyid/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
From the perspective of etymology, “discourse,” “discipline,” and “observed phenomena” are called by their respective names for four reasons. [The Tibetan word for discourse,]  mdo sde [“dodé”], is sutra [in Sanskrit], which means a verbal expression of a synthesis of meanings. This has four aspects. The Ornament of the Discourses states:
Because it verbally expresses circumstances, characteristics,
Phenomena, and meaning, it is [called] a discourse.
As stated, a discourse relates [that teaching’s] location where and the person for whom it was spoken—the circumstances. It states the characteristics of relative truth and ultimate truth—the characteristics. It describes the aggregates, sense constituents, sense bases, etc.—phenomena. It reveals the profound meaning of [the Buddha’s] wisdom mind—meaning.
[The Tibetan word for discipline,] ’dul ba [“dul-wa”], is vinaya [in Sanskrit]. The Ornament of the Discourses states:
[Because it elucidates] downfalls, [their] sources, recovery [from downfalls],
And definitive restoration, [as well as]
The individual, proscriptions, classification [of vows],
And specification [of vows], it is [called] the collection on discipline.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
zhes bzhi tshan gnyis kyis bshad pa las/ ltung ba ni ltung ba sde lnga dang*/ ltung ba de dag gang las 'byung ba ni/ mi shes pa/ bag med pa/ nyon mongs pa mang ba/ ma gus pa rnams dang*/ ltung ba de dag las ldang ba ni spang ba'i sems pa sor chud pa dang*/ ltung ba las nges par 'byung ba ni chad pa'i las khas len pa dang*/ rjes nas gnang ba dang*/ bag yangs su bya ba dang*/ rten du gyur pa dang*/ yang dag pa so sor rtog pa dang*/ chos nyid thob pa rnams so/ /de ltar gnas bzhi po de ston pas 'dul ba'i phyir ram/ gang la brten nas bslab pa bca' ba gang zag_/bslab pa bcas pa dngos/ de rab tu dbye ba/ ltung ba dang ltung med rnam par nges pa ste rnam pa bzhi smos pa'i phyir ro/ /mngon pa zhes bya ba ni/ a b+hi ste/ mdo rgyan las/ mngon du'i phyir dang yang dang yang*/ /zil gnon rtogs phyir mngon pa'i chos/ /zhes pa ltar rgyu mtshan bzhis de ltar brjod de mya ngan las 'das pa la mngon du phyogs pa'i bden pa la sogs pa ston pa'i phyir dang*/ chos re re la'ang gzugs can dang gzugs can ma yin pa sogs zhib mor phye nas yang nas yang du ston pa'i phyir dang*/ phas rgol zil gyis gnon pa'i phyir dang*/ 'dis mdo sde'i don rtogs par 'gyur ba'i phyir ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This presents the discipline in two groups of four aspects. “Downfall” [refers to] the five downfalls [that contravene the vows of ethical conduct]. From what have these downfalls arisen? Ignorance, carelessness, excessive afflictive emotions, or disrespect. Recovery from these downfalls is effected through renewal [of the vows] in a spirit of relinquishing [the act that caused the downfall]. Definitive restoration from a downfall [is achieved through] acceptance of penalties, subsequent dispensation, acting with great care, [relying upon] supports [for the vows], correct discernment, and [realization of] the nature of reality. Thus, it is [referred to as] the collection on discipline because it teaches those four aspects as described, or because it expresses the following four: the individual for whom the regulation [was initially] instituted, the actual proscriptions of the training, the classification [of vows], and the specification of what does or does not constitute a downfall.
[The Tibetan word for observed phenomena,] mngon pa [“ngön pa”], is abhi [in Sanskrit]. The Ornament of the Discourses states:
It is called the teaching on observed phenomena
Because it is manifest, repetitive,
Overpowering, and [conducive to] realization.
As stated, there are four reasons why [the collection on observed phenomena] is so named. It teaches such subjects as the truth manifestly belonging to transcendent states. It repeatedly presents subtle distinctions for each phenomenon, such as having form or not having form, etc. It overpowers challenges, and it fosters realization of the discourses’ meaning.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
the tshom spyod dang lta ba phyin log spong*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The collections eliminate doubt, detrimental behavior, and erroneous views.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de ltar sde snod gsum po de nyid du rnam par gzhag pa'i rgyu mtshan ci zhe na/ thar pa sgrub pa rnams kyi spang bya'i gtso bo/ lam gong ma la the tshom za ba dang*/ rang lam la spyod pa phyin ci log pa dang*/ lta ba phyin ci log pa ste gsum yin pa'i phyir/ de dag gi gnyen por mdo 'dul mngon pa'i sde snod gsum gsungs pa ste/
sde snod dang po ni/ gang zhig don gang la the tshom pa de la nges par bya ba'i phyir bshad pa gang zhig_/
gnyis pa ni/ kha na ma tho ba dang bcas pa'i yongs su spyad pa 'dod sred kyi dbang gis gsog 'jog byed pa sogs bkag pa'i sgo nas 'dod pa bsod snyoms la rjes su sbyor ba'i mtha' spong ba dang*/ kha na ma tho ba med pa'i yongs su spyad pa tshul khrims dag cing ma zhen par lhag par rnyed na/ brgya stong ri ba'i gos la sogs pa'ang rjes su gnang ba'i sgo nas bdag nyid dub pa la sbyor ba'i mtha' spong ba ste mtha' gnyis spong ba'i spyod pa ston pa'i phyir dang*/
gsum pa ni/ chos rnams kyi rang dang spyi'i mtshan nyid phyin ci ma log par ston pa'i phyir bshad pa yin pas so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
What is the reason for placing the three collections in this framework?
Those who strive for freedom must abandon three principal things: entertaining doubt toward higher spiritual paths, conduct detrimental to their own path, and detrimental views. [The Buddha] spoke the three collections—of discourses, on discipline, and on observed phenomena— as antidotes to these.
The first collection [of discourses] comprises any teaching that instills certainty where doubt existed in relation to any subject. The second collection [on discipline] teaches conduct that rejects the two extremes. Those teachings eliminate the extreme of engaging in begging for what is desired by prohibiting engagement in inadmissible conduct, such as hoarding motivated by craving. Through dispensations, the teachings reject the extreme of exhausting oneself; for instance, they permit an ordained person to possess expensive clothing when he or she has acquired it while fully engaged in pure ethical conduct without inadmissible acts, and he or she has gained definite freedom from attachment. The third collection [on observed phenomena] was presented to teach incontrovertibly the specific and general characteristics of phenomena.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
yang na chos don bshad sgrub 'bel gtam phyir/ /sde snod gsum bzhag gdul bya'i dbang byas nas/ /
theg pa che chung sde snod gnyis su 'du/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The collections’ framework is threefold
Because one collection presents the Dharma and its meaning, one collection presents its practice, and one [defines] terminology.
In relation to disciples’ [degree of scope], they are gathered into two: the lesser and great way’s collections.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sde snod gsum du nges pa'i rgyu mtshan yang na chos don bshad pa dang*/ chos don sgrub pa dang*/ chos don 'bel ba'i gtam gtan la dbab pa rnams kyi ched du rim pa bzhin du gsungs pa'i phyir sde snod gsum du rnam par gzhag ste/ de la chos dang don ni/ mdo sde rgyan gyi 'grel bshad las/ ming dang tshig dang yi ge rnams la ni chos zhes bya'o/ /des brjod par bya ba phung po dang khams dang*/ skye mched rnams la ni don zhes bya'o/ /yang na phung po dang khams dang skye mched la sogs pa la ni chos zhes bya'o/ /dgongs pa bzhi dang ldem dgongs bzhi la ni don zhes bya'o/ /yang na mtho ris thob par byed pa'i rgyu dge ba bcu la ni chos zhes bya'o/ /mya ngan las 'das pa thob par byed pa'i rgyu byang chub kyi phyogs kyi chos sum cu rtsa bdun la sogs pa la ni don zhes sogs bshad do/ /'di dag la dgongs nas mdo rgyan du/ sde snod dag ni gsum mam gnyis kyang rung*/ /bsdus pa'i phyir te rgyu ni dgur 'dod do/ /zhes 'byung ngo*/ /yang gdul bya'i gang zag gi dbang du byas na/ theg chen la zhugs pa'i gang zag dang theg pa chung ngur zhugs pa'i gang zag gnyis su nges pas byang chub sems dpa'i sde snod dang nyan thos kyi sde snod gnyis su'ang 'du ba yin la/ de'ang bshad ma thag pa'i sde snod gsum so so la gnyis gnyis su dbye ba ste/ dman pa la mos pa rnams kyi ngor gsungs pa dang*/ rgya chen po la mos pa rnams kyi ngor gsungs pa'i khyad par gyis so/ /de la thogs med zhabs kyis/ gsum po de nyid theg pa dman pa dang*/ theg pa mchog gi bye brag gis gnyis su 'gyur te/ nyan thos kyi sde snod dang*/ byang chub sems dpa'i sde snod do/ /zhes gsungs pa ltar ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The conclusive reason for the collections as threefold is that they were spoken in stages to teach the Dharma and its meaning; to teach the practice of Dharma and its meaning; and to define the Dharma’s terminology and its meaning. On what is meant by “Dharma and its meaning,” A Commentary on “The Ornament of the Discourses” states:
“Dharma” [in this case] refers to names, words, and letters. “Meaning” refers to the subjects they express: the psychophysical aggregates, sense constituents, and sense bases. Or, “Dharma” can refer to the aggregates, sense constituents, and sense bases, etc.; “meaning,” to the four intentions and covert intentions in the Buddha’s speech. Or, “Dharma” can refer to the ten virtuous acts, causes that lead to the attainment of the higher realms; “meaning,” to such subjects as thirty-seven aspects of awakening, causes that lead to the attainment of transcendent states.
Considering these [reasons], The Ornament of the Discourses states:
The collections can also be considered as threefold or twofold because they are compilations. Their primary causes are believed to be ninefold.
Alternatively, disciples are definitely of two kinds: individuals who have entered the great way and those who have entered the lesser way. Therefore, [the collections] are also grouped into two: the bodhisattva collection and the pious attendant collection. In other words, the three collections just presented are each divided into two, differentiated according to what was spoken to those drawn to a lesser scope and what was spoken before those drawn to a wide-ranging scope. It is as Venerable Asanga states:
These three become two based upon the difference between the lesser and sublime ways—the pious attendant collection and the bodhisattva collection.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="iii'">
gsum pa [iii'. rjod byed kyi sgo nas dbye ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="iii'">
Classification of the Canon according to Modes of Expression [iii']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rjod byed tsam gyi sgo nas rgyal ba'i bka'/ /mdo sde dbyangs bsnyad lung bstan tshigs su bcad/ /
ched brjod gleng gzhi rtogs brjod de ltar byung*/ /skyes rabs rgyas dang rmad byung gtan la dbab/ /
gsung rab yan lag bcu gnyis rnams su dbye/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In terms of content alone, the Victor’s canon
Is divided into twelve branches of the Buddha’s excellent speech:
Discourses, aphorisms in verse, prophetic declarations, verses,
Purposeful declarations, accounts to provide a framework, narrative stories, legends,
Accounts of former lives, extensive teachings, marvelous events, and definitions.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rjod byed dam rjod tshul tsam gyi sgo nas dbye na rgyal ba'i bka' rnams gsung rab yan lag bcu gnyis su dbye bar rigs te/ /
de la dang po mdo'i sde ni 'dus byas 'dus ma byas rnam nges su/ de la tshig rkyang lhug gis mdo mdor brjod pa de ni mdo'o/ /zhes bshad pa bzhin du smos pa'i tshul gyis tshig lhug pas don mdor bstan pa'i gsung rab yin zhing*/ smos pa'i tshul gyis gsungs pa la phan yon bcu yod pa kun btus las gsungs te/ sdom ni/ bzhag dang bshad dang bzung bar sla/ /gus pas tshogs rdzogs chos nyid rtogs/ /dkon mchog gsum la dad pa thob/ /mthong chos bder gnas 'bel gtam nus/ /zhes so/ /dbyangs kyis bsnyad pa'i sde ni/ mdo'i sde de nyid kyi bar mtha' rnams su tshigs su bcad pa'i dbyangs kyis bsnyad pa dag dang*/ brtag par bya ba gzhan yod pa'i phyir drang ba'i don gyi mdo sde gang yin pa rnams so/ /lung du bstan pa'i sde ni/ nyan thos la sogs pa 'das pa dang skye ba lung ston pa rnams dang*/ bye brag tu dgongs pa gsal bar bstan pa'i phyir nges don gyi mdo sde rnams so/ /tshigs su bcad pa'i sde ni/ tshigs bcad rkang pa gnyis pa nas drug pa'i bar gyis gsungs pa rnams so/ /ched du brjod pa'i sde ni/ gzhan gyis ma bskul bar thugs dgyes pa'i tshul gyis ched du gsungs par snang ba rnams so/ /gleng gzhi'i sde ni/ gang zag gi ched du gsungs pa dang*/ byung ba dang bcas pa'i bslab pa gsungs pa rnams so/ /rtogs pa brjod pa'i sde ni/ dpe dang bcas nas gsungs pa rnams te/ bam gnyis las/ chos nyan pa rnams kyis go zhing rtogs par bya ba'i phyir sngon btags par byung ba gzhan las drangs te dpe rgyas par bstan pas na rtogs pa brjod pa'i sde zhes bya zhes so/ /de lta bu byung ba'i sde ni sngon gyi gtam rgyud sogs gsungs pa rnams so/ /skyes rabs kyi sde ni/ byang chub sems dpa'i spyod pa ston pa rnams te thams cad sgrol ba'i skyes rabs lta bu'o/ /shin tu rgyas pa'i sde ni/ byang chub sems dpa'i sde snod theg chen 'ba' zhig ston pa rnams te/ de la rnam par 'thag pa'i sde dang mtshungs pa dang bral ba'i sde zhes kyang bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In terms of content or mode of expression alone, it is reasonable to divide the Victor’s canon into twelve branches of the Buddha’s excellent speech.
(1) The first of these is the class of the discourses. Certainty about the Conditioned and the Unconditioned states:
Discourses are concise syntheses of subjects, expressed in prose.
As stated, [discourses are] excellent speech that presents a subject concisely, in the mode of a dialogue in prose. The mode of dialogue has ten advantages, as stated in A Compendium of Training. In summary,
[A dialogue facilitates] (1) an outline, (2) a presentation, and
(3) easy retention; [It induces] respect; (4) the accumulations become complete;
(5) realization of the nature of reality [is rapid]; [The listener] gains faith in the three jewels (6, 7, 8); [It leads to] (9) abiding in happiness during this lifetime; and it
(10) can be discussed informally.
(2) Aphorisms in verse refers to what is related in the melody of poetry at the middle and at the end of discourses. These are discourses of provisional meaning because they must be examined in ways other than [an analysis of their literal meaning].
(3) Prophetic declarations predict the transcendence [of sorrow] and future births of pious attendants and others. Specifically, these are discourses of definitive meaning since they reveal the Buddha’s intent.
(4) Verses are what the Buddha spoke in verse, from two to six stanzas.
(5) Purposeful declarations are what the Buddha appeared to speak out of his wisdom mind’s own initiative, rather than from others’ encouragement.
(6) Accounts to provide a framework are what the Buddha spoke for the sake of an individual, or to relate a background story along with a proscribed point of training.
(7) Narrative stories are what the Buddha spoke accompanied by illustrative examples. The Second Volume states:
They are called “narrative stories” since they present extensive illustrative examples drawn from accounts of the past, so that those listening to the Dharma may come to understanding and realization.
(8) Legends are stories of the past and other similar accounts.
(9) Tales of the Buddha’s past lives are stories that present [the Buddha’s] conduct as a bodhisattva, such as the life of the One Who Liberates Everyone.
(10) Extensive teachings are the bodhisattva collection, teachings that are exclusively of the great way. This is also called “the category that conquers,” or “the unparalleled category.”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang kun btus las/ sems can thams cad la phan pa dang bde ba'i gnas yin pa dang*/ rgyas pa dang*/ rgya che ba dang*/ zab pa'i rnam par chos ston pa'i phyir ro/ /ci'i phyir rnam par 'thag pa zhes bya zhe na/ sgrib pa thams cad rnam par 'thag pa'i phyir ro/ /ci'i phyir mtshungs bral zhes bya zhe na/ mtshungs pa med pa'i phyir ro/ /zhes so/ /rmad du byung ba'i sde ni/ nyan thos dang byang chub sems dpa' dang sangs rgyas rnams kyi mkhyen pa dang rdzu 'phrul dang byin rlabs sogs ngo mtshar rmad du byung ba'i chos bstan pa rnams so/ /gtan la dbab pa'i sde ni/ gang du chos rnams kyi mtshan nyid ci lta bar gtan la phab nas mdo sde la sogs pa'i don gsal bar gsungs pa rnams so/ /de ltar gsung rab yan lag bcu gnyis po rnams sngar bshad pa'i sde snod rnams su so sor bsdu na 'di ltar shes dgos te/ mdo'i sde nas ched du brjod pa'i sde'i bar lnga ni nyan thos kyi mdo sde'i sde snod do/ /de nas gleng bzhi'i sde la sogs pa bzhi ni 'dul ba'i sde snod de/
de la dang po ni ltung ba bslab bya dang bcas pa ston pa'i phyir gtso bo yin la/ phyi ma rnams ni de'i 'khor ro/ /de nas shin tu rgyas pa'i sde sogs gnyis ni byang chub sems dpa'i mdo sde'i sde snod yin te bsam gyis mi khyab cing rgya che ba'i khyad par dang ldan pa'i phyir ro/ /de nas gtan la dbab pa'i sde gcig pu ni gnyis ka'i mngon pa'i sde snod du shes par bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
[These names are explained in] A Compendium of Training:
... because it is the location of happiness and benefit for all sentient beings and because it presents the Dharma as extensive, vast, and profound. Why is it called conquering? Because it completely conquers all obscurations. Why is it said to be unparalleled? Because it is without equal.
(11) Marvelous events are teachings that present marvelous and wonderful qualities, such as the omniscience, miracles, and blessings of pious attendants, bodhisattvas, and buddhas.
(12) Definitions are what the Buddha spoke to define phenomena’s characteristics as they are in order to then elucidate the meanings of discourses and other works.
If you wished to gather these twelve branches of scripture as described within each of the collections previously presented, you must know the following. The [first] five—from the discourses to the purposeful declarations—belong to the collection of the pious attendant discourses. The following four, starting with accounts to provide a framework, belong to the collection on discipline. The first is the principal one because it teaches the [story of] downfalls and their corresponding points of training; the subsequent [three] complement it. The next two, the extensive teachings [and the marvelous events] belong to the collection of bodhisattva discourses since they are especially inconceivable and vast. The class of definitions alone belongs to the collection on observed phenomena of both [pious attendants and bodhisattvas].
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="iv'">
bzhi pa [iv'. dbang po'i rim pas dbye ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="iv'">
Classification of the Canon according to the Disciples’ Degrees of Acumen [iv']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
dbang po'i rim las chos 'khor rnam gsum mam/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Classification based on degrees of acumen yields the three wheels of Dharma.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
yang na bka' thams cad gdul bya'i dbang po'i rim pa dang sbyar na chos kyi 'khor lo rnam pa gsum du dbye ba rigs te mdo sde dgongs pa nges 'grel gyi lung don kun mkhyen dri med 'od zer gyi zhal nas/ de la las dang po pa'i tshe gzung 'dzin rang rgyud pas bcings pa'i nyon mongs pa las sems bsrung ba'i phyir spang gnyen blang dor byed pa'i rim pa gtso bor ston pas bden pa bzhi'i chos kyi rnam grangs dang*/ bar pa gnyen po la mngon par zhen pa dgag pa'i phyir mtshan nyid med pa dang*/ tha ma gshis ji ltar gnas pa bstan pa don dam rnam par nges pa'i chos kyi rnam grangs gsum du byung ba yin no/ /dbang po'i sgo nas dbye na nyan thos dang*/ rang sangs rgyas dang*/ bla na med pa'i theg pa ste gsum nyid mtshan brjod las/ theg pa gsum gyis nges 'byung la/ /theg pa gcig gi 'bras bur gnas/ /zhes so/ /zhes sogs gsungs pas so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
An alternative approach is to correlate the entire canon with disciples’ degrees of acumen. In that case, it is reasonable to divide the canon into
three wheels of Dharma. In The Meaning of the Scripture “The Discourse of the Definite Elucidation of the Wisdom Mind,” all-knowing Drimé Özer [i.e., Longchenpa] states:
At the beginner’s level, the Buddha mainly taught an enumeration of the four truths—including the stages of renunciation, antidotes, and the acceptance and rejection [of conduct]—to protect the mind from the binding afflictive emotions produced by a dualistic autonomous mind stream. At the intermediate level, he taught the absence of defining characteristics to prevent manifest attachment to antidotes. Finally, he taught the way the fundamental nature abides—the ultimate and definitive enumeration of the teaching. Thus three enumerations arose.
When the canon is divided based on [the disciples’] degrees of acumen, there are three ways—the pious attendants’ way, the solitary sages’ way, and the unsurpassable way. The Full Litany of the Names of Manjushri states:
You use three spiritual systems [to foster] disengagement And to have beings dwell in the result of the single way.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2'">
[2' bstan bcos]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2'">
The Treatises That Comment upon the Scriptural Transmissions’ Intent [2']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa dgongs 'grel bstan bcos bshad pa la lnga/ rtsom pa po/ bstan bcos kyi mtshan nyid/ nges tshig_/dbye ba/ zhar byung blang dor gyi gnas bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has five parts: (1) qualifications of authors of treatises, (2) characteristics of the treatises, (3) etymology of the word “treatise,” (4) classifications of treatises, and (5) a supplementary explanation to present which treatises to adopt and which to reject.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="a'">
dang po [a'. rtsom pa po] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="a'">
Qualifications of Authors of Treatises [a']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rab 'bring tha ma'i tshad ldan rtsom pa pos/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Authors must possess a degree of [qualification] — highest, medium, or minimum.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang bstan bcos rtsom pa po mtshan nyid rab 'bring tha ma gsum gang rung gi tshad dang ldan pa dgos te/ kun mkhyen chos rjes/ rab chos nyid kyi bden pa mthong ba ste klu sgrub dang*/ 'phags pa lha/ thogs med la sogs pa lta bu'o/ /'bring yi dam lha'i zhal gzigs te gnang ba thob pa/ thugs rje chen pos byin gyis brlabs pa tsan+d+ra pa dang*/ zhi ba lha la sogs pa lta bu'o/ /tha ma yang rig pa'i gnas lnga la mkhas shing bla ma brgyud pa'i bshad pa'i gdams ngag yod pa ste/ slob dpon dpal sbas dang*/ ye shes snying po dang*/ shAkya blo gros la sogs pa lta bu'o/ /zhes gsungs pa ltar te/ da lta'ang mtshan nyid gsum rjes mthun pa dang ldan pa'i gang zag ni rtsom pa po'i tshad du rung ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Authors of commentaries must possess a degree of all or any of three qualifications—highest, average, or minimum. The all-knowing Lord of Dharma [Longchenpa] states:
The highest degree of qualification is to have gained sight of the truth of the nature of reality, as in the case of Nagarjuna, Aryadeva, and Asanga. The medium degree of qualification is to have seen the wisdom deity’s face and to have received [that deity’s] authorization, as in the case of Chandragomi, blessed by Bodhisattva Great Compassion; and Shantideva. The minimum degree of qualification is to be learned in the five subjects of Buddhist culture and to possess the profound instructions taught by a lineage of spiritual masters, as in the case of Master Shrigupta, Jnanagarbha, and Shakyamati.
Even at the present time, a qualified author is one who is endowed with a level commensurate with [one of] these three degrees of qualification.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="b'">
gnyis pa [b'. bstan bcos kyi mtshan nyid] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="b'">
Characteristics of the Treatises [b']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rgyal bstan dbang byas/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
[Treatises] refer to the Victor’s doctrine
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">zhes pa ste/ rgyud bla ma las/ gang zhig rgyal ba'i bstan pa 'ba' zhig gi_/dbang byas rnam g.yeng med yid can gyis bshad/ /thar pa thob pa'i lam dang rjes mthun pa/ /de yang drang srong bka' bzhin spyi bos blang*/ /zhes bshad pa ltar/ dngos dang brgyud nas bde bar gshegs pa'i gsung rab kyi dgongs pa 'grel pa'i dbang du byas nas rtsom pa po lta ba ngan pa dang the tshom sogs rnam g.yeng med pa'i blo gros can gyis bshad pa'i ngag gang zhig_/thar pa thob pa'i lam dang rjes su mthun pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Highest Continuity states:
Place on the crown of your head, as you would the Seer’s canon, [The teachings of] whoever teaches referring exclusively to the
Victor’s doctrine With a mind free from distraction, And [whose teachings] concur with the path to the attainment
of freedom.
As stated, treatises are defined as any presentation that directly or indirectly comments upon the intent of the Joyful Buddha’s excellent speech, written by an author whose intellect is free from such disturbances as wrong views or doubt. Such works concur with the path to the attainment of freedom.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="c'">
gsum pa [c'. nges tshig] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="c'">
Etymology of the Word “Treatise” [c']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
'chos skyob yon tan can/ /bstan bcos de ni drug bral gsum du 'dod/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
And have the qualities of refining and protecting.
Three kinds of treatise are believed to be free from six faults.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
mtshan nyid de dang ldan pa'i bstan bcos kyi nges tshig ni legs sbyar gyi skad du shAs+t+ra zhes bya ste/ de'ang shA sa ni 'chos pa/ tra ya skyob pa'i phyir bstan bcos zhes bya ste/ rnam bshad rigs par/ nyon mongs dgra rnams ma lus 'chos pa dang*/ /ngan 'gro'i srid las skyob byed gang yin pa/ /'chos skyob yon tan phyir na bstan bcos te/ /gnyis po 'di dag gzhan gyi lugs la med/ /ces so/ /yang shAs+t+ra zhes pa nges par bstan pa dang*/ gzhung lugs la 'jug pa 'chi med mdzod du bshad pa ltar/ sa sde las/ don med don log don dang ldan/ /thos rtsod sgrub pa lhur len dang*/ /ngan g.yo brtse bral sdug bsngal spong*/ /bstan bcos drug bral gsum du 'dod/ /ces so/ /de'ang rig byed bzhi la sogs pa yang dag pa'i don med pa'i bstan bcos dang*/ rtag chad du lta ba la sogs pas grol ba 'grub par smra ba sogs don log pa'i bstan bcos dang*/ snyan ngag la sogs pa thos pa lhur len pa'i bstan bcos dang*/ rtog ge la sogs pa'i rtsod pa lhur len dang*/ g.yul las rnam par rgyal ba la sogs pa'i ngan g.yo dang*/ ba glang la sogs pa'i mchod sbyin chos su smra ba'i rang gzhan la 'tshe ba can brtse ba dang bral ba'i bstan bcos ngan pa drug dang bral zhing*/ gnas skabs bde zhing mthar thug grol ba 'grub pa'i don chen po dang ldan pa dang*/ byang chub sgrub pa dang*/ 'khor ba'i sdug bsngal mtha' dag spong ba'i bstan bcos gsum ni/ sangs rgyas pa dag gis dang du blang byar 'dod pa yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The etymology of treatises that have the characteristics mentioned above is as follows. Bstan bcos [“ten-chö”]  in Tibetan is the equivalent of the Sanskrit shastra. Shasana means to refine; traya, to protect. Therefore, treatises are called [from the Tibetan “ten-chö”] “refinement of the doctrine.” A Rational System of Exposition states:
Texts that refine every afflictive emotion—our enemies—
And protect us from the miserable existences are treatises,
Since they have these qualities of refinement and protection.
These two qualities cannot be found in other systems.
Alternatively, The Treasury of Immortality presents the term shastra as meaning “definitive teaching” or “textual tradition.” [One of Asanga’s] five treatises on awakening’s stages states:
Three [kinds of] treatise are believed to be free from these six
[faults]:
Meaningless, [or] irrational, [versus] meaningful;
Stressing study, [or] debate, [versus] emphasizing practice;
Misleading, [or] cruel, [versus effective in] relieving suffering.
The six types of deficient treatises [referred to here] are treatises that lack authentic meaning, such as the four Vedas; irrational treatises, such as those that assert that liberation can be accomplished based on such views as eternalism or nihilism; treatises stressing subjects of study, such as poetic composition; treatises stressing debate, such as polemical texts; misleading treatises, such as those concerned with victory in battle; and treatises devoid of loving-kindness that are harmful to the reader and others, such as those that assert that the sacrifice of cows or other animals constitutes a religious practice of offering or generosity.
Buddhists believe that three kinds of treatise, different from these six deficient types of treatise, should be accepted: treatises imbued with great meaning—the achievement of temporal happiness and ultimate freedom; treatises that [emphasize] the accomplishment of awakening; and treatises that promote renunciation of every suffering of the wheel of life.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="d'">
[d'. dbye ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="d'">
Classifications of Treatises [d']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bzhi pa la gsum/ byed las kyi sgo nas dbye ba/ bshad bya'i sgo nas dbye ba/ brjod bya'i sgo nas dbye ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: (1) classification of treatises according to function, (2) classification of treatises according to topics, and (3) classification of treatises according to subject.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="i'">
dang po [i'. byed las kyi sgo nas dbye ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="i'">
Classification of Treatises according to Function [i']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
de yang byed las sgo nas rgya chen sdud/ /zab mo rnam 'byed 'khrugs pa sdeb dang gsum/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In terms of function, there are three kinds of treatise:
Treatises that encompass the vast, reveal the profound, or rectify order.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang bstan bcos de la byed las kyi sgo nas dbye na/ rgya chen po sdud pa'i bstan bcos dang*/ zab mo rnam par 'byed pa'i bstan bcos dang*/ 'khrugs pa go rim du sdeb pa'i bstan bcos dang gsum du bshad pa las/
dang po ni/ mngon pa mdzod lta bu/
gnyis pa mngon rtogs rgyan lta bu/
gsum pa mdo sde rgyan lta bu'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In terms of function, treatises are divided into three kinds: treatises that encompass a vast [wealth of information], treatises that reveal the subject of the profound, and treatises that rectify order.
The Treasury of Observed Phenomena is an example of the first; The Ornament of Manifest Realization, of the second; and The Ornament of the Discourses, of the third.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="ii'">
gnyis pa [ii'. bshad bya'i sgo nas dbye ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="ii'">
Classification of Treatises according to Topics [ii']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bshad bya spyi dang bye brag dgongs 'grel la/ /'khor lo gsum gyi lta spyod tha dad dang*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Among commentaries on the intent [of the canon’s] general or specific topics, The three wheels’ commentaries on the view and conduct are distinct.
In terms of the canon’s topics, there are two kinds of treatises: commentaries on the canon in general, and commentaries on the intent of specific [passages].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bshad bya bka'i sgo nas bstan bcos kyi dbye ba gnyis su 'gyur te/ bka' spyi'i dgongs 'grel dang*/ bye brag gi dgongs 'grel lo/ /
dang po katsAn la sogs brda sprod pa dang*/ sde bdun sogs tshad ma rig pa'i bstan bcos rnams so/ /
gnyis pa la'ang 'khor lo gsum gyi lta spyod 'grel pa'i dbye ba tha dad pa mang du 'gyur te/
'khor lo dang po'i lta ba'i cha 'grel pa la/ nyan thos kyi mngon pa sde bdun/ bye brag bshad mdzod chen mo/ de dag gi don bsdus mngon pa mdzod la sogs pa'o/ /spyod pa'i cha 'grel pa la/ 'dul ba mdo rtsa dang me tog phreng rgyud la sogs pa'o/ /'khor lo bar pa'i lta ba'i cha 'grel pa la/ dngos bstan stong nyid kyi rim pa gsal bar byed pa dbu ma rigs tshogs drug sogs dang*/ sbas don mngon rtogs kyi rim pa gsal bar byed pa mngon rtogs rgyan sogs so/ /spyod pa'i cha 'grel pa bslab pa kun las btus sogs dang*/ lta spyod gnyis char 'grel pa byang chub sems dpa'i spyod pa la 'jug pa sogs so/ /'khor lo tha ma'i lta ba'i cha 'grel pa mdo sde rgyan dang rnam 'byed gnyis/ rgyud bla sogs dang*/ spyod pa'i cha 'grel pa sdom pa nyi shu pa sogs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The first [category] includes treatises on grammar, such as The Kalapa Grammar and Chandra’s Grammar, and those on the study of logic, such as the seven treatises on logic.
The second is divided into commentaries on the view and conduct of the three turnings of the wheel; thus, it has many distinct [categories]:
Commentaries on the view aspect of the first wheel include the seven texts on observed phenomena of pious attendants and The Great Treasury of Detailed Exposition; and The Treasury of Observed Phenomena, which summarizes their meaning. Commentaries on the conduct aspect of the first wheel include The Basic Discourse on Monastic Discipline and The Continual Flower Garland.
Commentaries on the view aspect of the middle wheel comprise explicit teachings elucidating the stages [of understanding] of emptiness, such as the six collections on middle way logic; and the concealed meaning that elucidates the stages of manifest realization, such as The Ornament of Manifest Realization. Commentaries on the conduct aspect of the middle wheel include A Compendium of Training. Commentaries on both the view and conduct aspects of the middle wheel include Entering the Conduct of Enlightenment.
Commentaries on the view aspect of the last wheel include The Ornament of the Discourses, Discerning Between Phenomena and Their Nature, Discerning Between the Center and the Extremes, and The Highest Continuity. Commentaries on the conduct aspect of the last wheel include Twenty Verses on Bodhisattvas’ Vows.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="iii'">
gsum pa [iii'. brjod bya'i sgo nas dbye ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="iii'">
Classification of Treatises according to Subject [iii']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
brjod bya ji snyed pa dang ji lta ba/ /thar dang rnam mkhyen gtso bor ston rnams te/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In terms of subject, treatises mainly present
“All that there is,” “things as they are,” or freedom and omniscience.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bstan bcos rnams brjod bya'i sgo nas dbye ba gsum ste/ ji snyed pa ston pa dang*/ ji lta ba ston pa dang*/ thar pa dang thams cad mkhyen pa ston pa'o/ /ji snyed pa ston pa'ang phal pa dang mchog gnyis las snga ma ni lugs kyi bstan bcos sogs dang*/ phyi ma ni rig pa'i gnas lnga'i bstan bcos rnams te/ de las nang rig pa ston pa ni phung po lnga'i rab byed sogs so/ /ji lta ba ston pa bden gnyis rnam nges dang*/ sum cu pa dang*/ dbu ma rgyan sogs dang*/ thar pa dang thams cad mkhyen pa ston pa byang sa dang dgongs rgyan la sogs pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Classified in terms of subject, there are three kinds of treatises: treatises that teach “all that there is,” treatises that teach “things as they are,” and treatises that teach freedom and omniscience.
Treatises presenting “all that there is” are of two kinds, those that present common knowledge and those that present sublime knowledge. The former refers to treatises on social customs; the latter, treatises on the five [main] subjects of Buddhist culture. Among the latter, those concerned with Buddhist studies include A Dissertation on the Five Aggregates. Treatises presenting “things as they are” include Ascertaining the Two Truths, The Thirty Letters, and The Ornament of the Middle Way. Examples of treatises that teach freedom and omniscience are The Stages of Awakening and The Ornament of the Sage’s Wisdom Mind.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="e'">
bzhi pa [e'] zhar byung blang dor gyi gnas bshad pa ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="e'">
A Supplementary Explanation of Which Treatises to Adopt and Which to Reject [e']
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
sa bcu'i dbang phyug rgyan drug la sogs pa'i/ /gzhung rnams rgyal ba'i bka' bzhin spyi bor blang*/ /
bod gzhung rnying pa rnams kyang khyad 'phags so/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The works by the sovereign bodhisattvas of awakening’s tenth stage, the six ornaments, and others
Should be venerated like the Victor’s canon.
Older Tibetan treatises as well are especially exalted.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bstan pa nub ka ma'i skabs 'dir mi rnams bsod nams dang blo gros chung ba'i dbang gis rgyal ba'i bka' las bstan bcos/ de'ang rgya gzhung las bod gzhung*/ de'ang sngar byung rnams las phyis byung rnams rim gyis rtsis su byed do/ /de la 'jig rten gyi khams 'di na tshig gi nang nas mchog gam phul du gyur pa ni rgyal ba'i gsung rab rin po che yin pas don ma go yang tshig klog pa kho na tsam la byin rlabs dang dgos pa bsam gyis mi khyab pa dang ldan pas srog ltar du gces par bya ba yin la/ de'i 'og tu byams chos sde lnga/ sems 'grel skor gsum sogs sa bcu'i dbang phyug gi gsung rnams dang*/ sangs rgyas gnyis pa pad+mA ka ra'i rdo rje'i gsung yin nges pa rnams dang*/ dzam gling mdzes par byed pa'i rgyan drug_/sogs khongs nas chen po bzhi/ rmad du byung ba'i slob dpon gnyis/ mkhas pa sgo drug_/jo bo rje dang a b+ha yA ka ra sogs grub pa'i slob dpon chen po rnams kyis mdzad par nges pa'i gzhung rnams kyang rgyal ba'i bka' bzhin du spyi bor blang bar rigs shing*/ bod du snga 'gyur gyi lo tsA chen po rnams dang*/ phyi dar bshad sgrub kyi rtsa ba'i shing rta chen po rnams kyi bstan bcos phyogs su ma lhung ba rnams kyang khyad par du 'phags pa yin pas/ rgya gzhung rtsod med rnams dang rjes mthun par blta zhing dang du blang bar bya ba yin la/ paN+Di ta phal pas mdzad pa'i rgya gzhung dang*/ bod kyi bstan bcos phyogs re'i mig can dag gis sbyar ba rnams dang*/ khyad par phyi rabs kyi rtog ge ba rnams dang*/ blo gros rmongs kyang g.yar khral du lad mo zlo ba rnams dang*/ chos lugs so so'i kha 'dzin can rnams kyis ci thod du sbyar ba'i yig bris rnams ni dus dang blo gros gron pa'i rgyu dang*/ de lta bus mi dge ba'i bshes gnyen byed pa'i nyen yod pas yid brton bya ba'i yul ma yin te/ rje btsun thams cad mkhyen pa sgrol ba'i mgon pos/ phyi rabs kyi gtam la ma dges shig_/sngon gyi mkhas pa grub thob yin/ deng sang gi mkhas pa mkhas rdzu ru 'dug_/ces gsungs pa bzhin no/ /
bstan pa dam pa'i chos ngos bzung pa'i skabs dang po'i 'grel pa'o// //
</d>
<d e="2">
At this time of the disappearance of Buddha’s doctrine, human beings’ faint merit and intelligence result in treatises being more esteemed than the Victor’s canon; Tibetan works, more than Indian works; and modern works, more than earlier ones.
Among words expressed in this world, the most sublime and magnificent are those that comprise the Victor’s precious excellent speech. Thus, even though you do not understand the meaning of the Buddha’s words, to merely recite them aloud has inconceivable blessing and purpose. Thus, they are to be cherished as we do our own lives.
Next to these in importance are works spoken by sovereign bodhisattvas of awakening’s tenth stage, including the five works of Maitreya, the three cycles of commentaries by the bodhisattvas, works that definitely [record] the vajra speech of the second buddha Padmakara, and the major texts definitely composed by great adepts. These works include writings of the six ornaments who beautify this Land of Jambu, and others including the four great masters, the two outstanding masters, the six scholars, Lord Atisha, and Abhayakaragupta. It is fitting to venerate such works as though they were the Victor’s canon.
Impartial treatises composed by the great translators of the early translation school in Tibet, and by the great spiritual pioneers whose works became the sources for study and practice during the later proliferation [of Buddhism in Tibet] are especially exalted. As such, they should be regarded as similar to Indian works of incontestable validity, and accepted accordingly.
On the other hand, some works cause readers to squander their time and attention: Indian works composed by mediocre scholars, Tibetan treatises compiled by those with biased views, and especially the pedantry of later generations, mindless plagiarism, and writings carelessly organized by narrow-minded adherents to a single religious tradition. There is danger that such books might act as guides to nonvirtuous acts—they are not to be trusted. It is as all-knowing Drolwé Gönpo (Taranata) states:
Do not delight in the talk of later generations! Scholars of the past were accomplished masters. Modern scholars are frauds.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="skabs gnyis pa">
[2. lung gi chos 'khor bye brag tu dbye ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Chapter 2">
2. Cycles of Scriptural Transmission
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
!_skabs gnyis pa lung gi chos 'khor bye brag tu bshad pa la gnyis/ bzhed pa spyir bstan pa/ chos 'khor bye brag tu bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This chapter has two parts: (1) a general presentation of perspectives on the cycles of scriptural transmission and (2) a detailed explanation of the cycles of scriptural transmission.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
dang po [I. bzhed pa spyir bstan pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
Perspectives on the Cycles of Scriptural Transmission [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
ston pa mngon sangs rgyas te bdun phrag bdun/ /rdzogs mthar chos 'khor bskor nas myang 'das bar/ /
theg dman 'ba' zhig gsungs zhes nyan thos smra/ /theg chen pa rnams 'khor lo gsum du bzhed/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Pious attendants state that our teacher [began to] turn the wheel of Dharma
Seven weeks after he attained enlightenment.
Until he transcended sorrow, he taught only the lesser way.
Followers of the great way believe that there were three cycles [of scriptural transmission].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
ston pa bcom ldan 'das shAkya'i dbang po byang chub kyi snying por mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas nas zhag bdun phrag bdun du chos ma gsungs la/ zhag grangs zhe dgu rdzogs pa'i mthar tshangs pas gsol ba btab ste wa ra NA sir chos kyi 'khor lo thog mar bskor nas mya ngan las 'das kyi bar du theg dman nyan thos kyi sde snod bden pa bzhi'i tshul las brtsams pa 'ba' zhig gsungs so/ /zhes nyan thos sain+d+ha pa rnams de skad du smra zhing*/ 'khor lo phyi ma gnyis kyi rnam gzhag khas mi len no/ /theg chen pa rnams ni chos kyi 'khor lo rim pa gsum du bskor bar bzhed cing de'i tshul rgyas par 'chad par 'gyur ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Pious attendants of the sandha school assert that after our teacher, Transcendent Conqueror Lord of the Shakyas, attained manifest, perfect enlightenment at Heart of Awakening, he did not teach for seven weeks. After forty-nine days, Brahma asked him to teach. Thus, the Buddha first turned the wheel of Dharma at Varanasi. From that time until he transcended sorrow, he taught only the lesser way—the collection of teachings addressed to pious attendants, beginning with the subject of the four truths. [Adherents to that belief] do not accept a presentation [of the Buddha’s teaching that includes] two subsequent cycles.
Followers of the great way believe that the wheel of Dharma was turned in three stages. In this chapter, I will explain in detail how this was done.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="II">
[II. chos 'khor bye brag tu bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="II">
Cycles of Scriptural Transmission [II]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la gsum/ chos 'khor gyi ngo bo/ nges tshig_/rnam par dbye ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: (1) the essence of the wheel of Dharma, (2) the etymology of the term “wheel of Dharma,” and (3) categories of the wheel of Dharma.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
[A. chos 'khor gyi ngo bo]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
The Essence of the Wheel of Dharma [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la'ang gnyis/ spyir chos 'khor gyi ngo bo/ bye brag lung chos kyi mtshan nyid do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the general essence of the wheel of Dharma and (2) the specific characteristics of scriptural transmission.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
dang po [1. spyir chos 'khor gyi ngo bo] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
The General Essence of the Wheel of Dharma [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
chos 'khor ngo bo dam chos mi mthun gcod/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In essence, “the wheel of Dharma” refers to sacred teachings that cut through what is incompatible [with enlightenment].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
spyir chos kyi 'khor lo zhes bya ba ston pas gsungs pa'i dam pa'i chos gang zhig_/mi mthun phyogs 'joms shing gcod pa'i nus pa can no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In general, “the wheel of Dharma” refers to sacred teachings our teacher spoke that have the power to subdue and cut through what is incompatible [with enlightenment].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bye smras mthong lam mdo sdes mthong sgom dang*/ /mi slob lam ston chos kyi rnam grangs bcas/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The particularist school asserts that the path of seeing [is the wheel of Dharma];
The discourse school, the paths of seeing, meditation, and no further training, along with enumerations of the Dharma that explain [these paths].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang bye brag tu smra ba rnams kyis mthong lam kho na chos 'khor du 'dod de/ mdzod las/ chos kyi 'khor lo mthong ba'i lam/ /myur bar 'gro sogs/ zhes bshad pa ltar/ 'khor los sgyur ba'i 'khor lo rin po che ni 'dong bar 'dod pa'i sar myur du 'gro ba dang*/ yul gzhan 'dor zhing gzhan du 'jug pa dang*/ grong dang grong rdal sogs ma rgyal ba las rgyal ba dang*/ rgyal ba rnal du 'god pa dang*/ gnas la lar 'phar zhing la lar 'bab pa ltar/ skad cig bco lngas bden pa rtogs pa'i phyir myur du 'gro ba dang*/ bar chad med lam 'dor ba dang*/ rnam grol lam mngon du bya ba'i phyir 'jug pa'am/ bden pa'i dmigs pa gzhan 'dor zhing*/ gzhan du 'jug pa dang*/ bar chad med lam gyis 'jig lta sogs nyon mongs pa ma rgyal ba rnams las thob pa gcod pa'i sgo nas rgyal bar byed pa dang*/ rnam grol lam gyis nyon mongs bral ba'i thob pa dang*/ lhan cig skyes pa'i sgo nas rgyal ba rnal du dgod pa dang*/ gzugs dang gzugs med pa'i khams la dmigs nas 'phar ba dang*/ 'dod pa'i khams la dmigs nas 'bab pa la sogs pa rnams kyi phyir/ chos 'khor ni mthong lam kho na'o zhes so/ /mdo sde pa rnams kyis ni/ mthong sgom mi slob lam gsum ga de ston par byed pa'i chos kyi rnam grangs dang bcas pa chos 'khor du 'dod de/ slob dpon rgyal po'i sras kyis/ de lta bas na chos kyi rnam grangs de nyid chos kyi 'khor lo yang yin te/ chos kyi 'khor lo rab tu ston pa'i phyir ro/ /zhes dang*/ mthong ba dang sgom pa dang mi slob pa'i lam yang chos kyi 'khor lo yin te/ gdul bya'i skye bo'i rgyud la 'jug pas 'khor lo zhes bya ba'i phyir ro/ /zhes bshad pas so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Followers of the particularist school believe that the wheel of Dharma denotes the path of seeing alone. The Treasury of Observed Phenomena states:
The wheel of Dharma is the path of seeing.
It travels quickly, etc....
As stated, when a wheel-monarch’s precious wheel is set in motion, it travels swiftly to its intended destination, passing some places and entering others. It defeats unconquered regions, such as cities or villages, and naturally establishes its dominion over them. It ascends to some places and descends to others. Likewise, the wheel of Dharma moves swiftly since truth is realized in fifteen moments. It passes through the uninterrupted path and makes manifest the path of liberation, thereby entering it. Alternatively, the wheel of Dharma rejects focus on the reality [of things] and enters another [i.e., spiritual path]. Through [the power] of firm decisiveness, the uninterrupted path defeats unconquered afflictive emotions, such as the view of perishable collections [as a self]. The path of liberation is the attainment of separation from afflictive emotions. Dominion over those emotions is naturally established at the same time. Focusing on the form or formless realms, [the wheel of Dharma] ascends; focusing on the desire realm, it descends. Therefore, it is said, “The wheel of Dharma is the path of seeing alone.”
Followers of the discourse school believe that the wheel of Dharma includes three paths—seeing, meditation, and no further training— along with enumerations of the teachings that explain them. Master Jinaputra states:
. . . That being the case, the wheel of Dharma also includes enumerations of teaching, since they clearly explain the wheel of Dharma.
Further, he taught,
The paths of seeing, meditation, and no further training are also the wheel of Dharma. They enter the mind streams of beings to be guided; thus, they are called “wheel.”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
theg chen lam lnga gsung rab kun la 'jog_/
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The great way places the five paths and the scriptures within [the wheel of Dharma].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
theg chen pa ltar na tshogs lam nas mi slob lam gyi bar lam lnga po thams cad chos kyi 'khor lo yin te/ dbu ma pa chos bshes kyis/ chos kyi 'khor lo kha cig ni tshogs kyi lam mo/ /kha cig ni sbyor ba'i lam mo/ /kha cig ni bar chad med pa'i lam gyi bar ro/ /zhes bshad cing rnam grol gyi lam yang chos kyi 'khor lo thams cad kyi mchog tu gyur pa ste/ rgya cher rol pa'i mdor byams pa chos kyi 'khor lo de ni gting mi dmigs pa'i phyir zab pa'o/ /zhes pa la sogs pa rgya cher gsungs pas so/ /lam de dag brjod byed ston pa'i gsung rab kun kyang chos kyi 'khor lor 'jug pa ste/ slob dpon dbyig gnyen gyis/ kun rdzob kyi chos kyi ngo bo bstan pa'i rang bzhin gyi 'khor lo ni chos kyi 'khor lo yin no/ /zhes dang*/ sher phyin dang mngon pa sogs kyi ming yang gzhung lugs la 'jug pa mi 'gal ba bzhin du 'dir yang rigs pa'i phyir ro/ /yang na chos 'khor dngos rtogs pa'i chos dang tshogs sbyor gyi lam de'i yan lag yin zhing*/ gsung rab ni de dag gzhan rgyud la go bar byed pa'i phyir chos 'khor bskor ba zhes bya bar bshad kyang legs pa'i phyogs gcig yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
According to followers of the great way, five paths (from the path of accumulation to the path of no further training) comprise the wheel of Dharma. The middle way scholar Dharmamitra states:
Some wheels of Dharma are the path of accumulation. Some are the path of preparation. Some are [all paths] until the uninterrupted path.
The path of liberation is the most sublime among all wheels of Dharma. The Vast Enjoyment Discourse states this here and throughout its text:
Loving-Kindness, that wheel of Dharma [i.e., the path of liberation] is profound because its depth is unimaginable.
Further, all scriptures that present those paths are placed within the wheel of Dharma. Master Vasubandhu states:
The wheel whose nature is to present the essence of relative teachings is the wheel of Dharma.
Moreover, just as it is not contradictory to give names such as “the transcendent perfection of sublime insight” and “collection on observed phenomena” to textual traditions, the same logic applies here: [all teachings may be referred to as “wheel of Dharma”].
An acceptable alternative approach is to consider the real wheel of Dharma to be the Dharma of realization, and the paths of accumulation and preparation to be branches of it. The scriptures make these comprehensible to others’ mind streams; thus, the phrase, “turning the wheel of Dharma.”
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
gnyis pa [2. bye brag lung chos kyi mtshan nyid] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
The Characteristics of Scriptural Transmission [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
lung gi ngo bo ngag gi rnam rig ste/ /rgyal ba'i ye shes 'gro sems dag pa las/ /
gdul bya'i shes pa ming tshig yi ger snang*/ /bye mdos ming tshig phung po gnyis su smra/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The essence of scriptural transmission is knowledge manifest in speech.
Based upon the Victor’s wisdom and beings’ pure minds,
Disciples’ understanding manifests as terms, words, and letters.
The particularist and discourse schools assert that words and terms belong to two [different] aggregates.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de la bye brag lung gi chos 'khor gyi ngo bo ni/ ston pas gsungs pa'i dam chos gang zhig_/mya ngan las 'das pa'i rgyu 'bras ngo bo nyid gsum gang rung brjod bya'i gtso bor gyur pa ngag gi rnam par snang ba'i rnam rig go_/de'i mtshan gzhi'ang*/ bdag rkyen sangs rgyas kyi ye shes dang*/ rgyu rkyen gdul bya'i 'gro ba rnams kyi rgyud dag pa gnyis la brten nas/ gdul bya de'i shes pa ming tshig yi ge'i rnam par snang ba nyid yin gyi/ bcom ldan 'das la ngag kun nas slong ba'i bag chags mi mnga' ba'i phyir dang*/ nang gi shes pa phyi rol gyi sgrar zhen pa'i ma rig pa med pa'i phyir don dam par de bzhin gshegs pas bzhed pa'i dbang gis bstan pa ni ma yin no/ /de lta bas na theg chen gyi mdo sde 'ga' zhig las/ bde bar gshegs pas chos tshig 'bru gcig kyang ma bstan par bshad pa'ang don 'di la dgongs so/ /theg dman pa dag gis de ltar mi 'dod de/ mdzod las/ gang rnams thub pas gsungs de dag_/tshig gam ming yin de dag ni/ /gzugs dang 'du byed dag tu 'dus/ /zhes bshad pa ltar/ bye smras gsung rab kyi ngo bo ming tshig yi ge'i tshogs pa sgra spyi'i phreng bar 'dod pas ldan min 'du byed dang*/ mdo sde pas de sgra rang mtshan par 'dod pas gzugs phung ste dngos po'i mtha' gnyis su smra bar byed do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The essence of the wheel of Dharma of scriptural transmission is any sacred teachings spoken by our teacher. Its main subject is the transcendence of sorrow’s cause, result, and essence; it is knowledge manifest in the form of speech.
The basis for this definition is as follows: The dominant cause [for scriptural transmission] is the Buddha’s wisdom; its causal condition is the pure mind streams of beings who are his disciples. Based on the convergence of these two, those disciples’ understanding manifests in the form of terms, words, and letters.
Since the Transcendent Conqueror did not fall under the sway of habitual patterns that motivate speech, and since he had no lack of awareness, [including] inner cognition attached to external sound, ultimately, the Transcendent Buddha did not teach through the power of intentions. Thus, in consideration of this fact, some great way discourses relate that the Joyful Buddha did not teach even one word or syllable.
Followers of the lesser way do not share that belief. The Treasury of Observed Phenomena states:
Whatever the Sage spoke Are words or terms; They are gathered within form or formative factors.
The particularist school believes that the essence of the scriptures is a collection of words, terms, and letters that are connected according to general rules of grammar. Therefore, the teachings belong to [the aggregate of] non-associated formative factors. The discourse school believes that the scriptures’ grammar has its own identifiable attributes; therefore, the teachings belong to the form aggregate. [Both schools believe that scriptural transmission] falls within these two limits of substance.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
gnyis pa [B] nges tshig ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
Etymology of the Term “Wheel of Dharma” [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
nges tshig d+harma tsakra'i sgra phyi ma/ /rtogs pa 'pho dang lung gi chos phung tshogs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Concerning the etymology of the term “wheel of Dharma,” chakra, the latter part of the term Dharmachakra,
Denotes the movement of realization and the aggregate of scriptural transmission.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
legs sbyar gyi skad du d+harma tsakra zhes bya ba d+harma'i sgra bshad gong du song*/ tsakra'i sgra 'pho ba dang tshogs pa la'ang 'jug pas/ rtogs pa'i chos 'khor gdul bya'i rgyud la 'pho ba ltar snang ba'i phyir dang*/ lung gi chos 'khor chos kyi phung po mang po'i bdag nyid yin pa'i phyir de skad ces bya ste/ chos bshes kyis kyang*/ 'khor lo ni gdul bya'i rgyud la 'pho bar snang bas na'am/ tshogs kyi don gyi phyir 'khor lo ste sgra'i don ni de dag dang nye ba'i phyir ro/ /zhes so/ /yang ming gi rnam grangs tshangs pa'i 'khor lo zhes bya ba'ang*/ mdzod las/ de nyid tshangs tshul tshangs pa yi/ /'khor lo tshangs pas bskor phyir ro/ /zhes 'byung ba ltar ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In the Sanskrit term dharmachakra, the meaning of dharma has been explained above [in the previous chapter]. The term chakra denotes movement or a collection. The term chakra (wheel) is used because the wheel of the Dharma of realization seems to move to disciples’ mind streams, and because the cycle of scriptural transmission is the epitome of many aggregates of Dharma. Dharmamitra states:
The term “wheel” is used because [realization] appears to move into disciples’ mind streams or because it has the meaning of a collection, since the meaning of the word “wheel” is close to those [intended meanings].
Also, in other synonyms for it, reference is made to “Brahma’s wheel,” as The Treasury of Observed Phenomena states:
It [the wheel of Dharma] itself [is Brahma’s wheel], since in purity, Brahma’s [literally: the Pure’s] wheel is turned by Brahma.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="C">
[C. rnam par dbye ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="C">
Categories of the Wheel of Dharma [C]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gsum pa rnam par dbye ba la gnyis/ thun mong dang*/ thun mong ma yin pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the common wheel of Dharma and (2) the extraordinary wheel of Dharma according to the secret mantra way.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
[1. thun mong]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
The Common Wheel of Dharma [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la gnyis/ chos 'khor gsum du dbye ba/ de chos phung du rnam par gzhag pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the wheel of Dharma classified as three cycles of teaching and (2) the wheel of Dharma described in terms of aggregates.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="a">
[a. chos 'khor gsum du dbye ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="a">
The Wheel of Dharma Classified as Three Cycles of Teaching [a]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'i dang po la gnyis/ spyi dang so so'i rnam gzhag go_/
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the general classification of three cycles of teaching and (2) separate frameworks of the three cycles of teaching.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="i">
dang po [i. spyi] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="i">
The General Classification of Three Cycles of Teaching [i]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
dbye na dang po bden bzhi bar pa ni/ /mtshan nyid med dang tha ma legs par phye/ /
nges 'byung rnam thar phyir mi ldog pa'i gtam/ /zhir 'jug smin dang lung ston thob phyir gsungs/ /
bsod nams ma yin bdag dang lta kun zlog_/
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
When scriptural transmission is classified, the first doctrine comprises the four truths;
The intermediate doctrine, absence of characteristics; the final doctrine, accurate discernment.
[The Buddha] spoke of renunciation, freedom, and irreversibility
To have beings enter peace, reach spiritual maturity, and fulfill prophecies;
And to have them turn away from what is not meritorious, from the self, and from [the basis of] all views.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
lung gi chos de la dbye na chos kyi 'khor lo rnam pa gsum zhes theg chen pa rnams la grags shing grub pa ste/ de'ang bka' dang po bden pa bzhi'i chos 'khor/ bar pa mtshan nyid med pa'i chos 'khor/ tha ma legs par rnam par phye ba'i chos 'khor ro/ /de'ang gzungs kyi dbang phyug rgyal pos zhus pa'i mdo las/ de bzhin gshegs pas yongs su ma dag pa'i sems can gyi khams rig nas/ mi rtag pa dang*/ sdug bsngal ba dang*/ bdag med pa dang*/ mi sdug pa yid 'byung bar 'gyur ba'i gtam gyis 'khor ba la mngon par dga' ba'i sems can rnams yid 'byung bar byed/ 'phags pa'i chos 'dul ba la 'jug par byed do/ /de tsam gyis de bzhin gshegs pa brtson 'grus rgyun mi gcod cing*/ de'i 'og tu stong pa nyid dang*/ mtshan ma med pa dang*/ smon pa med pa'i gtam gyis de bzhin gshegs pa'i tshul khong du chud par byed do/ /de tsam gyis kyang de bzhin gshegs pa brtson 'grus rgyun mi gcod kyi/ de'i 'og tu phyir mi ldog pa'i 'khor lo'i gtam dang*/ 'khor gsum yongs su dag pa'i gtam gyis sems can de dag de bzhin gshegs pa'i yul la 'dzud do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
When scriptural transmissions are classified, the wheel of Dharma has three cycles; this is widely known and accepted among followers of the great way.
The first doctrine the Buddha taught is the scriptural transmission of the four truths; the middle one, the scriptural transmission concerning absence of characteristics; and the final one, the scriptural transmission of accurate discernment. The Discourse Requested by Powerful King of Dharanis states:
Aware of the dispositions of thoroughly impure sentient beings, the Transcendent Buddha’s speeches on impermanence, suffering, absence of self, and undesirability [of the wheel of life] provoked disillusionment in sentient beings enthralled with the wheel of life—those beings entered exalted beings’ spiritual discipline.
The Transcendent Buddha’s diligence did not end with merely that; his later accounts of emptiness, absence of inherent characteristics, and lack of aspiration allowed sentient beings to comprehend the nature of transcendent buddhas.
The Transcendent Buddha’s diligence did end with merely that; his later accounts of the irreversible wheel of Dharma and of complete threefold purity [of act, agent, and object] placed beings within the transcendent buddhas’ domain.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
zhes chos 'khor gsum la gtam gsum gyis bstan par mdzad de/
dang po 'khor ba las yid nges par 'byung ba'i gtam dang*/
gnyis pa rnam thar sgo gsum gyi gtam dang*/
gsum pa phyir mi ldog pa'i 'khor lo'i gtam mo/ /de ltar 'jog pa'i rgyu mtshan ni/ gdul bya byang chub mchog tu dkri ba'i rim pas bzhag pa ste/ rgyud bla ma las/ 'jig rten zhi ba'i lam la 'jug pa dang*/ /rab tu smin dang lung ston rgyu yi gzugs/ /zhes bshad pa ltar/ dang po gdul bya 'khor ba la chags pa rnams yid 'byung ba'i gtam gyis bskul nas zhi ba'i lam la 'jug pa dang*/ de nas stong nyid kyi gtam gyis theg pa chen por yongs su smin pa dang*/ de nas phyir mi ldog pa'i 'khor lo'i gtam gyis de bzhin gshegs pa'i yul la 'jug cing lung ston pa chen po 'thob par byed pa'i phyir gsungs so/ /gzhan yang 'phags pa lhas/ bsod nams ma yin dang por zlog_/bar du bdag ni zlog pa dang*/ /tha mar lta gzhi kun zlog pa/ /gang gis shes de mkhas pa yin/ /zhes bshad pa'ang chos 'khor gsum la sbyor bar bzhed de rgyas par phyi nas 'byung ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Thus, among the three wheels of Dharma, three styles of speech deliver the teachings. The first is speech [that inspired] renunciation toward the wheel of life; the second, speech that presented the three gateways to freedom; and the third, speech that described the irreversible wheel. The reason for this order is that these stages connect disciples to supreme awakening. The Highest Continuity states:
The form [bodies] constitute the cause which makes the worldly enter the path of peace, Brings them to spiritual maturity, and gives prophecies.
As stated, the Buddha’s initial talks of disillusionment given to those attached to the wheel of life compelled them to enter the path of peace. Then, talks on emptiness brought them to spiritual maturity in the great way. Then, talks on the irreversible wheel had them enter the transcendent buddhas’ domain and receive outstanding prophecies [of awakening]. Therefore, the Buddha spoke [in this order]. Furthermore, Aryadeva states:
First, turn away from what is not meritorious; Later, turn away from the self; Lastly, turn away from the basis of all views. Whoever understands this is wise.
Various perspectives related to the three wheels of Dharma will appear in detail in later chapters within The Treasury of Knowledge.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="ii">
[ii. so so'i rnam gzhag]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="ii">
Separate Frameworks of the Three Cycles of Teaching [ii]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa so so'i rnam gzhag la gsum/ 'khor lo dang po/ bar pa/ tha ma'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: (1) the first, (2) the middle, and (3) the final cycle of teaching.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="aa">
dang po [aa. 'khor lo dang po] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="aa">
The First Cycle of Teaching [aa]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bden bzhi lan gsum bzlas pa bcu gnyis te/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The four truths were repeated three times, making twelve [parts].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de la dang po bden bzhi'i chos 'khor gyi mtshan nyid ni/ ston pas gsungs pa'i dam chos gang zhig theg chen gyi lam stegs su dgongs nas/ gtso bor theg dman gyi rigs can rnams la bstan pa'o/ /de'i mtshan gzhi ni/ nyan thos rnams la grags pa'i 'dul mngon mdo sde'i gsung rab rnams te lung sde bzhi sogs so/ /de dag la ci'i phyir bden bzhi'i chos 'khor zhes bya zhe na gtso bor bden pa bzhi las brtsams te dman pa la mos pa rnams drang ba'i phyir lta spyod yang dag par ston pas na de skad ces bya'o/ /de'ang 'khor lo dang po'i dngos gzhi yul wa ra NA si drang srong lhung ba ri dwags kyi nags su 'khor lnga sde bzang po la bden bzhi lan gsum du bzlas pa rnam pa bcu gnyis kyi 'khor lo bskor ba'i tshul bstan pa de yin te/ de'i tshul yang bye brag smra bas/ bden bzhi'i ngo bo bstan pa/ bya ba bstan pa/ 'bras bu bstan pa'i tshul gyis bzlas pa gsum/ bzlas pa re re la'ang yid/ shes pa/ rig pa/ blo skyes so zhes bzhi bzhi dang bcas pa'i rnam pa bcu gnyis su bstan par bzhed/ mdo sde pas/ bden bzhi rang gi ngo bo la dmigs pa'i tshul gyis bzlas pa dang po/ bya ba'i ngo bo la dmigs pa'i tshul gyis bzlas pa gnyis pa/ mthar thug pa la dmigs pa'i tshul gyis gsum pa ste/ bzla bya ni bden bzhi'i chos kyi rnam grangs nyid yin zhing*/ bzlas pa gsum la bden pa bzhi so sor ngo bo bya ba 'bras bu rnams la dmigs pa'i rnam pa bzhi bzhir 'gyur ba'i phyir rnam pa bcu gnyis yin no zhes 'dod pa ni 'thad pa'i phyogs so/ /chos 'khor de'i dngos kyi dgos pa lnga sde bzang pos dgra bcom thob pa sogs dang*/ khyad par gyi dgos pa de nas brtsams 'bras bu'i bstan pa rdzogs kyi bar 'bras bu bzhi thob pa sa chen po'i rdul tsam byung ba de'i phyir ro/ /'di las gzhan pa bden bzhi'i chos 'khor du gtogs pa rnams ni 'dul lung grong khyer drug sogs su thor bur gsungs pas mtshon gnas dang dus ma nges pa sna tshogs pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The first wheel of Dharma, that of the four truths, can be characterized as sacred teachings the Buddha spoke with the intention to establish a foundation for the great way’s path. He mainly taught this cycle to disciples with an affinity for the lesser way. The scriptures known to pious attendants as [collections] on discipline, on observed phenomena, and of the discourses, such as the four classes of discourses, exemplify this cycle.
Why is it referred to as the doctrinal cycle of “the four truths”? This term is used because, to guide disciples inclined to the lesser way, [the Buddha] taught the correct view and conduct starting from the principal subject of this cycle, the four truths. The main teachings of the first wheel took place in the region of Varanasi, at Deer Park, Descent of the Seers. To a circle of disciples, the excellent group of five, [the Buddha] first enunciated the four truths three times. Thus, he taught this turning of the wheel in a twelve-part format.
On the subject of that format, the particularist school considers that presentations of the four truths’ essence, function, and result constitute the three enunciations. Moreover, each repetition had four aspects — words, knowledge, understanding, and realization. Thus, the teaching was carried out in twelve parts.
The discourse school maintains that the first repetition focused upon the essence of the four truths themselves; the second focused upon the essence of their functions; and the third focused upon their ultimate [result]. What was repeated was the system of the four truths; in the course of three repetitions, the focus was upon three features (essence, function, and result) of each of the four truths. Thus, this school states that the teaching had twelve parts. This belief seems reasonable to me.
This doctrinal cycle’s actual purpose included to bring the excellent group of five to the attainment of the state of arhat. Its special purpose is that, from that time until the end of the doctrine of fruition, those who attain the four results [of the lesser way’s path] will be as numerous as the earth’s dust motes.
Other teachings besides the ones mentioned here belong to the four truths’ doctrinal cycle. For example, the Buddha spoke fragments of the scriptural transmission on discipline in six cities and in other locations. [In the same way, this doctrinal cycle was enunciated] in various unspecified times and places.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="bb">
gnyis pa [bb. bar pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="bb">
The Middle Cycle of Teaching [bb]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
mtshan nyid med la dngos bstan rnam thar gsum/ /sbas don mngon rtogs brgyad po yan lag bcas/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
To teach the absence of characteristics, the explicit teaching presented the three gateways to freedom;
The hidden meaning explained the eight manifest realizations and related topics.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'khor lo bar pa'i mtshan nyid ni/ ston pas gsungs pa'i dam chos gang zhig_/theg pa chen po'i lam dngos la dgongs nas gtso bor theg chen pa'i rigs can rnams la bstan pa'o/ /de'i mtshan gzhi ni/ yum rgyas 'bring bsdus gsum sogs sher phyin gyi mdo sde gtso bor gyur pa rnams so/ /de dag la ci'i phyir mtshan nyid med pa'i chos kyi 'khor lo zhes bya zhe na/ gzugs nas rnam mkhyen gyi bar gyi chos thams cad rang rang gi mtshan nyid shin tu dben pa'i smra bsam brjod bral gyi de kho na nyid ston par snang ba'i phyir de skad ces bya'o/ /de'ang gnas rgyal po'i khab bya rgod phung po'i ri la 'khor rnam pa bzhi dang byang chub sems dpa'i tshogs dpag tu med pa rnams la/ dngos bstan rnam par thar pa'i sgo gsum las brtsams te zab mo stong pa nyid kyi tshul bstan pas sbas don mngon rtogs brgyad gdul bya'i rgyud la ji ltar skye ba'i rim pa yan lag gi don bdun cu dang bcas pa legs par rtogs pa'i thabs su sgo gsum rnam grangs bcu gcig gi sgo nas 'chad par mdzad do/ /de la rnam thar sgo gsum ni/ gzhi stong pa nyid/ lam mtshan ma med pa/ 'bras bu smon pa med pa'o/ /sbas don mngon rtogs brgyad ni/ mngon rgyan las/ shes rab pha rol phyin pa ni/ /dngos po brgyad kyis yang dag bshad/ /rnam kun mkhyen nyid lam shes nyid/ /de nas thams cad shes pa nyid/ /rnam kun mngon rdzogs rtogs pa dang*/ /rtse mor phyin dang mthar gyis pa/ /skad cig gcig mngon rdzogs byang chub/ /chos kyi sku dang de rnams brgyad/ /ces pa ltar dang*/
</d>
<d e="2">
The middle wheel of Dharma can be characterized as sacred teachings the Buddha spoke with the intention to establish the great way’s actual path. He mainly taught them to disciples with an affinity for the great way. The discourses on the perfection of sublime insight, including the text referred to as the mother [of all buddhas] in its extensive, medium, and brief versions, chiefly exemplify this cycle.
Why is this cycle referred to as the doctrinal cycle of “the absence of characteristics”? All phenomena, from form up to and including omniscience, dwell far removed from substantial characteristics. These teachings were apparently given to show this indescribable, inconceivable, and inexpressible ultimate nature; thus this term is used.
At the site of Vulture Peak at Rajgir, [the Buddha] taught a circle of disciples belonging to the four assemblies [of laywomen, laymen, nuns, and monks] and an infinite gathering of bodhisattvas. He began with an explicit teaching, the three gateways to freedom; then, by presenting the profound subject of emptiness, he explained the hidden meaning, the stages through which the eight manifest realizations arise in disciples’ mind streams, and he included seventy related topics. He employed three styles and eleven systems [listed here below] that serve as effective means to achieve realization.
The three gateways to freedom are as follows: the basis is emptiness; the path, absence of characteristics; and the result, aspirationlessness. The hidden meaning, the eight manifest realizations, [are listed] in The Ornament of Manifest Realization:
Eight points fully elucidate
The perfection of sublime insight:
Knowledge of all aspects of phenomena, knowledge of paths,
Knowledge of everything,
Manifest perfect realization of all aspects,
Reaching the peak, culmination,
Instantaneous manifest perfect awakening,
And the body of ultimate enlightenment. These are the eight points.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
don bdun bcu ni/ rnam mkhyen mtshon byed kyi chos bcu/ lam shes mtshon byed bcu gcig_/gzhi shes mtshon byed dgu/ rnam rdzogs sbyor ba mtshon byed bcu gcig_/rtse sbyor mtshon byed chos brgyad/ mthar gyis pa'i sbyor ba mtshon byed bcu gsum/ skad cig ma'i sbyor ba mtshon byed bzhi/ 'bras bu chos sku mtshon byed kyi chos bzhi rnams so/ /de dag ston byed sgo gsum ni/ 'go smos pas go ba rnams kyi ngor bsdus te bstan pa'i sgo/ spros pa tsam gyis go ba rnams kyi ngor 'bring du bstan pa'i sgo/ tshig la 'chel ba rnams kyi ngor rgyas par bshad pa'i sgo rnams so/ /rnam grangs bcu gcig ni/ shA ri'i bu/ rab 'byor/ brgya byin/ yang rab 'byor/ byams pa/ yang rab 'byor/ brgya byin/ rab 'byor/ byams pa/ rab 'byor/ kun dga' bo rnams go rim bzhin du dris lan sogs kyis bstan pa rnams so/ /'khor lo 'di'i dgos pa ni dngos su bskor ba'i tshul bstan yul gyi gdul bya nges par rgyur grol ba 'di la ltos dgos pa rnams de bzhin gshegs pa'i yul la 'jug pa dang*/ brgyud nas sems can thams cad kyi lta ba ngan pa'i sgrib g.yogs bsal nas chos thams cad kyi gnas lugs phyin ci ma log par mngon sum du rtogs nas mtha' gnyis la rab tu mi gnas pa'i mya ngan las 'das pa chen po 'thob pa'i phyir ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The seventy related subjects are as follows: ten teachings illustrate omniscience, eleven illustrate knowledge of the paths, nine illustrate knowledge of the ground, eleven illustrate training which is complete in all aspects, eight illustrate reaching the peak, thirteen illustrate culmination, four illustrate reaching instantaneous [awakening], and four illustrate the result, the body of ultimate enlightenment.
Three styles teach [these eight points and seventy related subjects]: a condensed teaching addressed to those who understand based on a statement of the main points; a moderate length teaching for those who understand based upon mere elaboration; and an extensive explanation for those fond of words.
The eleven systems were presented in such forms as answers to the questions of Shariputra, Subhuti, Shakra, Subhuti again, Maitreya, Subhuti again, Shakra, Subhuti, Maitreya, Subhuti, and Ananda, each in turn.
This doctrinal cycle’s purposes are as follows: directly, the Buddha demonstrated the way of turning the wheel; and the minds of its recipients, his disciples, were definitely liberated. Based on these purposes, they entered the transcendent buddhas’ domain. Indirectly, this cycle removes all sentient beings’ obscuring veils of wrong views, leading to the manifest and irreversible realization of all phenomena’s abiding nature, and the attainment of the supreme transcendence of sorrow which does not fall into the two extremes.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="cc">
gsum pa [cc. tha ma] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="cc">
The Final Cycle of Teaching [cc]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
tha mas mtshan nyid rnam gsum gtso bor ston/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The final cycle principally teaches the three characteristics [of knowable things].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'khor lo tha ma'i mtshan nyid ni/ ston pas gsungs pa'i dam chos gang zhig_/mthar thug pa'i don la dgongs nas gtso bor phyir mi ldog pa'i byang chub sems dpa' rnams la bstan pa'o/ /de'i mtshan gzhi ni/ phal po che dang lang kar gshegs pa sogs de bzhin gshegs pa'i snying po'i gtam gtso bor ston pa'i phyogs kyi gsung rab rnams yin no/ /de dag la ci'i phyir legs par rnam par phye ba'i chos 'khor zhes bya zhe na/ gzugs nas rnam mkhyen gyi bar gyi chos thams cad kun brtags gzhan dbang yongs grub ste mtshan nyid gsum du legs par phyes nas gtso bor gsungs pa'i phyir de skad ces bya'o/ /de la 'khor lo tha ma'i dngos gzhi ni/ don dam par tshad gzungs ci zhig kyang*/ rang re byis pa rnams kyi mthong thos kyi yul tsam du'ang ri ma la ya dang*/ byang chub kyi snying po dang*/ yangs pa can sogs su dus ma nges par gsungs pas 'di nyid kho na'o zhes mtha' gcig tu gzhag dka' mod kyi gong smos rnams dang dkon mchog brtsegs pa sogs tshig don gnyis ka rgyas pa'i phyogs rnams ni der bzhag par 'os shing*/ de'ang theg pa che chung gi mdo sde phal che ba zhig las dgongs pa can du gsungs pa mang po 'di dag tu gsal bar bstan pa shas che ste/ dper na 'dul ba'i mdor/ dge slong dag gis rung ba'i sha bza' bar gnang ba/ rnam gsum dag pa'i sha 'di ni/ /ma brtags pa dang ma bslangs dang*/ /ma bskul ba ni yong med pas/ /de phyir sha ni mi za'o/ /zhes sogs kyis dgongs pa can du bstan pa sogs mang ba'i phyir ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The final wheel of Dharma can be characterized as sacred teachings the Buddha spoke with the intention of teaching the ultimate meaning. He mainly taught bodhisattvas at levels of no regression. Scriptures that principally teach accounts of buddha-nature, such as The Flower Ornament Discourse and The Journey to Lanka Discourse, exemplify this cycle.
Why are they referred to as “the doctrinal cycle of accurate analysis”? This expression is used since the Buddha mainly began with an accurate analysis of all phenomena, from form up to and including omniscience, according to three characteristics [of knowable things]: imagined, dependent, and consummate.
The final doctrinal cycle’s main part is ultimately immeasurable, yet merely in the visual and aural domain of spiritually immature persons like ourselves, the Buddha spoke at indefinite times at Mount Malaya, Heart of Awakening, Vaishali, and other places. Therefore, a single delineation—“This, and this alone, constitutes the [final cycle of teaching]”— is difficult to make. Nevertheless, the above-mentioned texts and others, such as A Cluster of Jewels, that have extensive [elucidations] of both the words and meanings [of the subjects of this cycle] should be placed within this cycle. Many words spoken with an underlying intention in the majority of lesser and great way discourses are largely clarified in these [discourses of the final cycle of instruction]. For example, The Basic Discourse on Monastic Discipline states:
Monks are permitted to eat suitable meat. This meat that is pure in three ways—[the meat has] not been designated [for the monk], nor begged for, nor ordered—will not occur; thus do not eat meat.
In this and other examples, the Buddha gave many instructions with an underlying intention.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="b">
gnyis pa [b] de dag chos phung du rnam par gzhag pa ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="b">
The Wheel of Dharma Described in Terms of Aggregates [b]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
thams cad chos kyi phung po zhes bya ste/ /de yang brgyad khri dang ni bzhi stong ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
All scriptural transmissions are referred to as “aggregates of Dharma,”
Of which there are eighty-four thousand.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de ltar lung gi chos thams cad la spyir chos kyi phung po zhes bya ste/ brjod bya don dang rjod byed kyi tshig du ma spungs pa'i phung por snang ba'i phyir ro/ /de'ang mdzod las chos phung brgyad khrir bshad cing mdzod TIka tu sde pa kha cig brgyad khri bzhi stong du 'dod pa'ang bshad la theg chen pa rnams kyis phyi ma 'dod pa ni yongs su grags pa ltar ro/ /de ltar yang*/ kun mkhyen dri med 'od zer gyis/ gnyen po rnam grangs kyi sgo nas dbye na chos kyi phung po brgyad khri bzhi stong ste/ sgron gsal las/ thub pa chen pos chos phung po/ /brgyad khri bzhi stong gsungs pa las/ /zhes gsungs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
All scriptural transmissions are generally referred to as “aggregates of Dharma” because their various subjects’ meanings and their content’s words appear as a heaped mound. The Treasury of Observed Phenomena states that there are eighty thousand aggregates of Dharma; a commentary to The Treasury of Observed Phenomena states that some schools believe that there are eighty-four thousand. Followers of the great way have made this latter belief prevalent. Omniscient Drimé Özer [Longchenpa] states:
Classified according to the number of antidotes [to the afflictive emotions], there are eighty-four thousand aggregates of
Dharma. The Radiant Lamp states:
Among the eighty-four thousand aggregates of Dharma
The great Sage spoke,...
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
phung po'i tshad la nyan thos 'dod tshul gsum/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Pious attendants determine an aggregate in three ways.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
chos kyi phung po re re'i tshad la 'dod tshul mang yang*/ nyan thos kyi 'dod tshul gtso bo gsum ste/ sde pa kha cig gis ni bye smras bka' dang*/ mdo sde pas bstan bcos su 'dod pa'i mngon pa sde bdun gyi nang tshan/ chos kyi phung po shA ri'i bus/ zhes bshad pa de la gzhung tshad sho lo ka drug stong yod pas/ de chos phung gcig gi tshad yin zhing brgyad khri'i nang nas de tsam zhig lus kyi gzhan ni nub bo zhes zer ro/ /yang sde pa kha cig gis ni/ phung po khams dang skye mched dang*/ rten 'brel la sogs pa'i rnam grangs re re'i gtam rdzogs pa ni chos phung re re'i tshad du 'gyur zhing dbye ba'ang de ltar byas par 'dod do/ /yang kha cig nyon mongs pa 'dod chags/ zhe sdang*/ gti mug_/nga rgyal/ log lta/ the tshom rnams nang gses su dbye ba dang*/ phan tshun sbyor ba sogs kyis brgyad khrir 'gyur la/ de dag re re'i gnyen por chos phung re re bstan cing*/ rang rang gi gnyen po'i bya ba yongs su rdzogs par ston pa'i gtam ni de'i tshad du 'dod do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
There are many beliefs concerning the ways of measuring a single aggregate of Dharma. The pious attendants have three main beliefs: Some [pious attendant] schools claim that since the main text of Aggregates of Dharma by Shariputra (one of the seven texts on observed phenomena, which the particularist school believes to belong in the canon; the discourse school, among the treatises) is six thousand verses long, that represents the measure of one aggregate of Dharma. They say that among the eighty thousand [aggregates], just this remains; the rest has disappeared.
Some schools believe that a complete discussion of the topic of each enumeration (such as the psycho-physical aggregates, sense constituents, sense bases, or interdependency) is a measure of an aggregate of Dharma, and they classify them accordingly.
Moreover, some schools believe that various sub-classifications and combinations of the afflictive emotions (desire, anger, stupidity, pride, wrong view, and doubt) total eighty thousand. As an antidote to each of them, an aggregate of Dharma was taught. They believe that the measure [of an aggregate of Dharma] is the words that completely present the application of each antidote.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
gzhan dag glang po rab brtan rgyab tshad bzhed/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Others consider that the measure is equal to [a load] on the back of the elephant Steadfast.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de las gzhan dag theg pa chen po dag gi dbang du byas te/ nA ga bod+hi la sogs pa ni/ chos gang zhig gi ming tshig lha'i gos ltar srab pa'i gro ga'am tA lar/ skra'i rtse mo'i cha shas kyis mtha' rgyags med par bris pa/ glang po che dar ma'i rgyab non pa'i tshad la phung po gcig tu bzhed cing*/ tshig gsal las theg pa bla na med pa'i dbang du byas te/ dbang po'i glang po che rab brtan gyis bkur bar 'os pa'i snag tshas ni chos kyi phung po gcig 'dri bar nus so zhes gsungs te/ de ltar byas na mdo gang dag las 'phags pa lhas byin gyis glang po che lnga stong gis bkur bar bya ba'i glegs bam rnams kha ton du brjod par byed do zhes gsungs pa 'di yang rigs par 'gyur ro/ /zhes bshad cing mdo gang dag las zhes pa'i mdo ni drin lan bsab mdor grags pa de nyid do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
According to followers of the great way (including Nagabodhi), one aggregate of Dharma denotes the number of words or terms of Dharma, written without any borders or embellishments with a pen (the tip of which is as fine as a fraction of a hair’s tip) on white birch bark or palmyra paper as thin and light as the garment of the gods, that can be loaded onto the back of a full-grown elephant. Clear Words states:
The perspective of the unsurpassable way is that one aggregate of Dharma is however much can be written with the amount of ink that can be carried by Indra’s elephant, Steadfast. That being the case, some discourses quote exalted Dévadatta as stating that this would equal the number of volumes of scriptures, suitable for chanting, that five thousand elephants could carry. This seems logical.
“Some discourses” refers in fact to the one known as Returning the Buddha’s Kindness Discourse.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
[2. thun mong ma yin pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
The Extraordinary Wheel of Dharma according to the Secret Mantra Way [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa thun mong ma yin pa gsang sngags kyi chos 'khor bshad pa la lnga/ bya rgyud/ spyod rgyud/ rnal 'byor rgyud/ bla med rgyud/ gsungs tshul gzhan bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has five parts: (1) the origin of action tantra, (2) the origin of conduct tantra, (3) the origin of the yoga tantra, (4) the origin of the highest yoga tantra, and (5) other explanations of the origins of [tantra].
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="a">
dang po [a. bya rgyud] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="a">
The Origin of Action Tantra [a]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rgyud sde bzhi las bya rgyud 'og min dang*/ /ri rab rtse mo 'jam dpal sogs la gsungs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Among the four classes of tantra, action tantras were spoken to Gentle Splendor and others
In the Unsurpassed Pure Land and at the summit of Supreme Mountain.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gsang sngags rdo rje theg pa la rgyud sde rnam pa bzhir grags pa'i thog mar bya ba'i rgyud ni gnas 'og min du dkyil 'khor la bkod pa dang sangs rgyas byang sems dpag tu med pa'i 'khor la gtso bor gsungs shing*/ ri rab kyi rtse mo sum cu rtsa gsum dang mi yul sogs su 'jam dpal sogs gtso bor gyur pa'i 'khor lo ci rigs par gsungs pa dang*/ dpung bzang gi rgyud lcang lo can du gsungs par bshad pa sogs kyang yod do/ /de'ang ston pas zhal nas gsungs pa dang*/ ston pa'i mthus 'jam dpal/ spyan ras gzigs/ phyag rdor sogs kyi bshad pa dang*/ 'jig rten pa'i lha la sogs pas smras pa ston pas byin gyis brlabs pa sogs ci rigs par mchis so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Within the tradition of the secret mantra vajra way, four classes of tantra are known.
First, action tantra [was transmitted] in the Unsurpassed Pure Realm, where a sacred circle was arrayed, and the main tantra was taught to an infinite circle of buddhas and bodhisattvas. Various teachings on this tantra were spoken in the Heaven of the Thirty-three at the summit of Supreme Mountain, in the human realm, and in other locations, to circles of disciples led by Gentle Splendor and other bodhisattvas. There are other examples of this tantra, including The Questions of Subahu Tantra, said to be taught in Willow Grove.
Tantras [within this class] were taught in various ways, including spoken from our teacher’s mouth; taught by Gentle Splendor, All-Seeing One, Vajra Holder, and other bodhisattvas, as a result of our teacher’s power; and expressed by such beings as worldly gods, as a result of our teacher’s blessing, etc.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="b">
gnyis pa [b. spyod rgyud] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="b">
The Origin of Conduct Tantra [b]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
spyod rgyud rnam snang zhing dang zhing bar ma/ /rtsa gsum sogs su sras bcas rgyal la ste/ /
gsung ba po ni mchog gi sprul sku'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Conduct tantra was taught to buddhas accompanied by their spiritual heirs
In such locations as Buddha Illuminator’s realm, intermediate realms, and the Heaven of the Thirty-three.
The speaker appeared as a sublime body of emanation.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
spyod pa'i rgyud ni/ gnas rnam snang sangs rgyas pa'i zhing khams me tog gi snying po'i rgyan bkod pa dang*/ de'i zhing khams bar ma dang lcang lo can la sogs pa'i gnas su/ 'khor dkyil 'khor la bkod pa dang sras dang bcas pa'i rgyal ba rgya mtsho la bstan pa ste/ bya spyod gnyis ka'ang gsung pa po'i ston pa ni mchog gi sprul pa'i sku nyid kyi rnam pas so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Conduct tantra was spoken in such locations as Buddha Illuminator’s pure realm (Flower-Filled World), intermediate realms, and Willow Grove, where sacred circles were arrayed and the tantra was taught to an ocean of victors accompanied by their spiritual heirs.
Moreover, for both action and conduct tantras, the teacher who spoke them did so in the appearing aspect of a sublime body of emanation.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="c">
gsum pa [c. rnal 'byor rgyud] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="c">
The Origin of Yoga Tantra [c]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rnal 'byor rgyud ni ston pa 'og min du/ /sangs rgyas las sprul longs sku chung ngu yis/ /
ri rab rtse mor dkyil 'khor sprul pa dang*/ /gzhan 'phrul dbang byed la sogs ma nges gsungs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
[According to] yoga tantra, after the teacher’s enlightenment in the Unsurpassed Pure Land,
His emanation, a lesser body of rapture,
Emanated a sacred circle at the summit of Supreme Mountain.
Moreover, he spoke [yoga tantras] in unspecified locations, including the Heaven of Mastery Over Others’ Creations.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rnal 'byor rgyud ni ston pa 'og min du longs spyod rdzogs skur sangs rgyas nas/ longs sku chung ngu'am/ sprul sku'i rnam snang ri rab kyi rtse mor gshegs nas/ de bzhin gshegs pa'i dkyil 'khor chen por sprul bshad mdzad pa'i tshul gyis gtso bor gsungs shing*/ gzhan ni gzhan 'phrul dbang byed kyi gnas sogs su ma nges par bstan par mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
According to yoga tantra, after the teacher attained enlightenment as the body of perfect rapture in the Unsurpassed Pure Land, he went to the summit of Supreme Mountain as a lesser body of rapture or as Buddha Illuminator’s emanation body. There, he emanated and taught the transcendent buddhas’ supreme sacred circle, and thus spoke the main [yoga tantras].
In addition, he presented [yoga tantras] in unspecified other locations, including the Heaven of Mastery Over Others’ Creations.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="d">
bzhi pa [d. bla med rgyud] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="d">
The Origin of Highest Yoga Tantra [d]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bla med gsang 'dus ston pas bdud btul rjes/ /dga' ldan yang na gzhan 'phrul gnas su gshegs/ /
dkyil 'khor sprul nas mkha' khyab 'khor la gsungs/ /A lang+kA ra kun snying dag gis bzhed/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
[According to] the Matrix of Mystery tantra of highest yoga, after the teacher subdued demons,
He went to Joyful Heaven or to the Heaven of Mastery Over Others’ Creations.
He emanated a sacred circle and taught the tantra to a circle of disciples that filled space.
Alangkara-kalasha and Anandagarbha affirm this.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rnal 'byor bla na med pa'i rgyud rnams las pha rgyud gsang ba 'dus pa ni/ ston pa nam phyed la sangs rgyas pa'i tho rangs bdud btul te dga' ldan du byon nas/ der sku'i 'byung ba chen po las gzhal yas khang sprul/ phung khams sogs las dkyil 'khor bkod pa'i lha rnams sprul te/ 'khor nam mkha' khyab pas bcom ldan 'das la gsol ba btab pas 'dod chags can rjes su bzung ba'i phyir gsungs par bzhed cing*/ rab tu sgron gsal las kyang dga' ldan du gsungs par bshad/ yang na khyab 'jug sogs kyi rgyud la dga' ba'i skye bo 'dod chags can rnams kyi don du gzhan 'phrul dbang byed kyi gnas su gshegs nas dkyil 'khor sprul te mkha' khyab kyi 'khor la gsungs pa'ang bshad do/ /snga ma ni paN+Di ta a lang+kA ra ka lA sha dang*/ phyi ma ni yo ga'i shing rta pa chen po slob dpon kun dga' snying po dag gis bzhed pa yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Among the highest yoga tantras, the origin of the father tantra Matrix of Mystery is explained as follows: Our teacher attained enlightenment at midnight; he subdued demons at dawn and went to Joyful Heaven. There, he emanated a celestial palace from his wisdom body’s major elements; and from his aggregates, sense constituents, etc., he emanated deities arrayed in a sacred circle. His circle of disciples that filled space then supplicated the Transcendent Conqueror [to teach]. As a result, he taught the tantra to spiritually nurture passionate individuals. Conversely, The Radiant Lamp states that this tantra was taught in Joyful Heaven.
Another source relates that to aid passionate individuals attracted to the tantric systems of Vishnu and other [worldly gods], the teacher went to the Heaven of Mastery Over Others’ Creations, emanated a sacred circle, and taught a circle of disciples that filled space.
Scholar Alangkara-kalasha affirms the former account; the great leader of the chariot of yoga tantra, Master Anandagarbha, the latter.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bod sogs ston pa mnyan yod bzhugs pa'i tshe/ /in+d+ra b+hU tis gsol btab o rgyan gshegs/ /
sprul pa'i dal du dbang rgyud gnang bar bshad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Tibetan scholars and others state that while the teacher lived in Shravasti,
Indrabhuti supplicated him, and he went to Oddiyana.
He granted the empowerment and tantra in an emanated sacred circle.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bod kyi mkhas pa rnams dang sogs khongs nas rgya gzhung kha cig nas kyang ston pa mnyan yod na bzhugs pa'i tshe/ o rgyan gyi rgyal po in+d+ra b+hU tis bcom ldan 'das kyi che ba'i yon tan thos nas spyan 'dren pa'i gsol ba btab pas/ ston pa 'khor bcas byon pa la mchod de srid pa las thar bar gsol ba las/ rab tu byung zhig gsungs pa la 'dod yon spyod bzhin du 'tshang rgya ba zhig zhus pas/ ston pas sprul sku'i snang ba sdus te dpal gsang ba 'dus pa'i dkyil 'khor sprul nas/ in+d+ra b+hU ti sogs nyan pa'i skal ba can rnams la dbang bskur rgyud bstan nas rdo rje chos la rgyud gtad par bshad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Tibetan scholars and “others” (among whom are some Indian authors) explain that while the teacher lived in Shravasti, King Indrabhuti of Oddiyana heard about the Transcendent Conqueror’s superlative qualities, and invited him.
When the teacher and his circle arrived, the king made offerings and asked to be liberated from existence. The Buddha advised, “Renounce home life!” In response, Indrabhuti asked for [teachings to attain] enlightenment while he still enjoyed the senses’ pleasures. Thus, the teacher dissolved his emanated body’s appearance and manifested the sacred circle of glorious Matrix of Mystery. He then granted empowerment and taught the tantra to King Indrabhuti and others who had the fortunate connection to receive it. Then he entrusted the tantra to Vajra Dharma.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
gshed skor bdud dpung 'dul tshe gsang gsum gyi/ /rdo rje las byung dkyil 'khor sprul sogs mang*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
[According to] the cycle of Slayer of the Lord of Death, when the Buddha subdued the demons’ armies,
[Slayer of the Lord of Death] arose from [the Buddha’s] three secret vajras; he emanated a sacred circle. Many other accounts [of this tantra’s origins] exist.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gshin rje gshed kyi skor ni/ ston pa mngon par byang chub pa'i dus bdud dpung rnams kyis bar du gcod pa'i tshe/ ston pas bdud chen po las mchog tu rgyal ba zhes pa'i ting nge 'dzin la bzhugs te/ sku gsung thugs kyi rdo rje las khro bo gshin rje gshed phyung nas dkyil 'khor sprul te bdud thams cad btul nas rgyud rgyas par gsungs/ sogs khongs nas gshed skor so so la gleng bzhi yod pas mang ste/ ston pa gshin rje gshed lha bcu gsum dang bcas pa'i 'khor tshogs mang po dang thabs gcig tu bzhugs nas bsdus rgyud gsungs/ ston pa rdo rje btsun mo'i b+ha ga zhes pa chos 'byung gi nang gi gzhal yas khang na gti mug rdo rje sogs dang lhan cig bzhugs pa'i tshe/ phyag rdor la nyan par gdams pas des zhus nas gshed dmar gsungs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Slayer of the Lord of Death cycle is explained as follows: As our teacher reached manifest awakening, demons’ armies created obstacles. The teacher dwelt in a meditative state called “complete victory over the great demon.” Wrathful Slayer of the Lord of Death arose from the Buddha’s vajra body, speech, and mind, and he emanated the deity’s sacred circle. He subdued every demon and taught the extensive tantra.
Among the “other accounts,” each cycle of Slayer of the Lord of Death has its own framework story; thus, many exist. [For example,] when the teacher, Slayer of the Lord of Death, dwelled with many groups of disciples, including a thirteen-deity sacred circle, he enunciated the brief tantra. Another account relates that the teacher dwelled (with Vajra Stupidity and others [of his circle]) in a celestial palace inside a source of phenomena called “the Vajra Queen’s bhaga.” He advised Vajra Holder to listen, and that bodhisattva asked him to teach; he taught Red Slayer of the Lord of Death.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
dgyes rdor bdud 'joms tshe na chos 'byung du/ /rtsa ba'i rgyud bstan bshad rgyud gzhan du'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
[According to] the Vajra of Delight cycle, when the Buddha defeated demons, he taught the root tantra
While inside a source of phenomena. He spoke the explanatory tantra at another time.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
ma rgyud dgyes pa rdo rje ni/ rdo rje phreng ba'i 'grel par gnas dzam+bu'i gling du sprul pa'i skus ma ga ng+har bdud bzhi 'joms pa'i dus gsungs par bshad la/ de yang rdo rje btsun mo'i b+ha ga zhes pa chos 'byung ste/ de'i nang du gnas pa'i gzhal yas khang du ston pa bcom ldan 'das 'khor 'jig rten dang 'jig rten las 'das pa du mas bskor te bzhugs pa la/ rdo rje snying po dang bdag med ma la sogs kyis zhus nas rtsa rgyud rgyas pa dang bsdus rgyud brtag gnyis gsungs/ ston pa gzhal yas khang gi dbus su 'khor los sgyur ba lnga'i lha tshogs dang 'jig rten dang 'jig rten las 'das pa'i 'khor bcas te bshad rgyud rdo rje gur gsungs te dus rtsa rgyud las gzhan du'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
[The origin of] the mother tantra Vajra of Delight is explained as follows: The Vajra Garland commentary teaches that in the Land of Jambu, the Buddha’s emanation body defeated the four demons in Magadha and spoke [this tantra]. Moreover, when he dwelled in a celestial palace located within a source of phenomena called “the Vajra Queen’s bhaga,” a circle of various worldly and supramundane beings surrounded the teacher, the Transcendent Conqueror. When Vajra Essence, Selfless Goddess, and others requested his teaching, he spoke the extensive root tantra and the abridged tantra, The Vajra of Delight Tantra’s Two Chapters.
When the teacher appeared in the center of a celestial palace with the leader’s fivefold host of deities and a circle of worldly and supramundane beings, he spoke the explanatory tantra, The Vajra Tent. This occurred at another time than the enunciation of the root tantra.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bde mchog thog ma med nas rgyal bas gsungs/ /gnyis ldan dus su 'bras bu'i he ru kas/ /
dzam+bu'i gling du 'khor la bskyar nas bshad/ /rtsod dus drag po chung ma 'khor bcas kyis/ /
gnas yul dur khrod rnams la dbang byed tshe/ /sprul pas btul nas dkyil 'khor bkod de gsungs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
[According to] the Supreme Bliss tantra, victors have spoken this tantra since time immemorial.
During the era of decline by one half,
The fruition Héruka taught it again to his circle in the Land of Jambu.
During the era of conflict, when Fierce Terrifying Demon, his consort, and retinue
Controlled the sacred places, regions, and charnel grounds,
The Héruka’s emanation subdued them, arrayed a sacred circle, and spoke [the tantra].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'khor lo bde mchog gi rgyud rnams ni/ thog ma med pa'i dus nas sangs rgyas thams cad kyis bstan par bshad pa dang*/ thog ma med par ston pa 'di sangs rgyas nas bstan par bzhed pa dang*/ gnyis ldan gyi dus drag po 'jigs byed btul ba'i gnas dzam+bu'i gling 'dir ston pa sprul pa'i sku 'bras bu'i he ru kas 'khor sangs rgyas byang sems rigs lnga'i dpa' bo dang dpa' mo/ sdud pa po gsang bdag_/drag po 'jigs byed 'khor dang bcas pa rnams la dbang bskur zhing rgyud bskyar nas bstan par bshad pa dang*/ rtsod ldan gyi dus drag po 'jigs byed dbang phyug chen po zhi rgyas dbang drag gi sku bzhi chung ma dang bcas pas ri rab kyi byang shar dang dbus dang gzhan 'phrul dbang byed dang ma ga d+hA rnams su gnas te/ yul nyer bzhi dang dur khrod brgyad rnams de'i rjes 'jug gi lha dang dri za dang gnod sbyin dang srin po dang klu dang mi ma yin rnams bzhi bzhir dbye bas nyer bzhi dang*/ mi'am ci bzhi dang phra men bzhi ste brgyad kyis bzung nas dzam+bu'i gling thams cad dbang du bsdus shing las log pa la rang yang zhugs nas gzhan yang 'god par byed pa'i dus/ ston pa rdo rje 'chang byang chub pa lngas mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas te
</d>
<d e="2">
[The origin of] the Supreme Bliss tantra is explained as follows: It is said that from time immemorial, all buddhas have taught this tantra, and it is
thought that since time immemorial our teacher attained enlightenment and revealed it. It is taught that during the era [in which the merit of humanity had diminished by] one half, Fierce Terrifying Demon subdued this Land of Jambu. Our teacher’s emanation body, appearing as the fruition Héruka, then granted empowerment to his circle of buddhas, bodhisattvas, spiritual heroes and heroines of the five wisdom families, the tantra’s compiler Lord of Secrets, and to Fierce Terrifying Demon with his retinue, and he again revealed the tantra.
It is thought that during the era of conflict, the four bodies (peaceful, enriching, magnetizing, and wrathful) of the great lord Fierce Terrifying Demon, along with his consorts, dwelled on Supreme Mountain’s central and northeastern regions, in Heaven of Mastery Over Others’ Creations, and in Magadha [central India]. Their followers—gods, celestial musicians, noxious spirits, ogres, nagas, and nonhuman beings (four of each, twenty-four in all); four beings who appear as humans and four tramen spirits (eight in all)—seized the twenty-four sacred regions and eight charnel grounds. Thus, [this demon] brought the entire Land of Jambu under his control; he engaged in evil acts and enjoined others to do the same.
At that time, the teacher Buddha Vajra Bearer had attained manifest, perfect enlightenment through the five aspects of awakening.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
chos kyi dbyings kyi ngang nas 'og min du sangs rgyas byang sems dpag tu med pa la 'od gsal lhan cig skyes pa'i chos bstan/ drag po dbang phyug 'khor bcas 'dul ba'i dus la bab par mkhyen te/ sprul sku 'bras bu'i he ru kar bzhengs nas ri rab kyi rtse mor byon pa la/ rigs lnga'i rgyal bas gzhal yas khang dang dpa' bo dpa' mo la sogs pa'i lha rnams sprul te phul bas/ ston pa nyid longs sku'i ting nge 'dzin la bzhugs nas gdul bya la gzigs te/ gling bzhi bye ba phrag brgyar dkyil 'khor gyi 'khor lo sna tshogs pa spros/ dzam+bu'i gling 'dir bde mchog zhal bzhi phyag bcu gnyis par sprul nas 'jigs byed dang dus mtshan zhabs 'og tu mnan zhing btul/ sprul pa'i 'khor rnams kyis kyang yul nyer bzhi dang dur khrod brgyad bzung ba'i ma rungs pa rnams btul/ ri rab kyi rtse mor bcom ldan 'das gzhal yas khang du 'khod de/ 'khor dkyil 'khor la 'khod pa dang sangs rgyas byang sems ri rab kyi rdul dang mnyam pa dang*/ drag po 'jigs byed 'khor bcas dang*/ skal ba dang ldan pa'i lha mi dang bcas pa la/ rdo rje rnal 'byor mas zhus te rtsa rgyud dang*/ phyag rdor gyis zhus te bshad rgyud rnams gsungs par bzhed pa dang*/ gzhan yang bshad tshul sna tshogs pa snang ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Within the basic space of phenomena, he presented the teachings of innate clear light to infinite numbers of buddhas and bodhisattvas in Unsurpassed Pure Land. He knew the time had come to subdue the lord Fierce Terrifying Demon and his retinue: his emanation body arose as the fruition Héruka and appeared at Supreme Mountain’s summit. The five wisdom families’ victors emanated a celestial palace and deities such as spiritual heroes and heroines, and presented them as an offering. The teacher entered the body of rapture’s meditative state and surveyed those he was to guide. He emitted various wheels of sacred circles throughout one billion four-continent world-systems. In this Land of Jambu, he manifested as four-faced, twelve-armed Supreme Bliss, and defeated Fierce Terrifying Demon and [his consort] Sign of the Times, crushing them under his feet. His emanated circle subdued the wild beings who had seized control of the twenty-four sacred regions and eight charnel grounds.
At Supreme Mountain’s summit, the Transcendent Conqueror dwelt in a celestial palace. He taught the root tantra in response to Vajra Yogini’s request, and the explanatory tantras at Vajra Holder’s request, to his retinue who formed a sacred circle around him—buddhas and bodhisattvas gathered in numbers equal to Supreme Mountain’s atoms—and Fierce Terrifying Demon with his followers, along with fortunate gods and humans.
It appears that various other traditions of explanation [of this tantra’s origin] exist.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
dus 'khor mya ngan 'das pa'i snga logs kyi/ /nag nyar dpal ldan 'bras spungs mchod rten gyi/ /
'og tu chos dbyings gsung dbang steng mar ni/ /dpal ldan rgyu skar dkyil 'khor legs sprul nas/ /
zla bzang la sogs skal ldan 'khor la gsungs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
[According to] the Wheel of Time, before transcending sorrow,
On Chaitra month’s full moon, at glorious Treasure Mound Stupa,
Our teacher emanated Lord of Speech of the Basic Space of Phenomena below;
And above, the glorious constellations’ sacred circle.
He then spoke the tantra to a fortunate circle, which included King Suchandra.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dpal dus kyi 'khor lo ni/ ston pa mya ngan las 'das pa'i tshul bstan pa'i snga logs kyi lor/ nag pa'i nya la sangs rgyas kyi mthus lho phyogs dpal ldan 'bras spungs kyi mchod rten du gshegs te/ 'og tu chos dbyings gsung gi dbang phyug dang steng du dpal ldan rgyu skar gyi dkyil 'khor legs par sprul nas rdo rje seng ge'i khri la bzhugs te dkyil 'khor la bkod pa'i 'khor rnams dang*/ zhu ba po rgyal po zla ba bzang po dang gzhan yang rgyal po dgu bcu rtsa drug la sogs pa skal ba dang ldan pa'i 'khor rnams la rtsa ba'i rgyud kyi rgyal po stong phrag bcu gnyis pa gsungs so/ /'di ni kun mkhyen rang byung zhabs sogs bod kyi dus 'khor ba yongs grags rnams kyi lugs ltar bshad kyi/ jo nang rje btsun chen po rjes 'brangs dang bcas pa rnams ni ston pa sangs rgyas pa'i phyi lor gsungs par bzhed do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The origin of the glorious Wheel of Time tantra is explained as follows: In the year before our teacher transcended sorrow, on the full moon day of Chaitra [the third lunar] month, he traveled by the power of his enlightenment to the southern glorious Treasure Mound Stupa. Below, he emanated [the sacred circle] of Lord of Speech of the Basic Space of Phenomena; and above, the sacred circle of the glorious constellations. He then sat on a lion-supported vajra throne. To his entourage arrayed in his sacred circle [of deities], and to King Suchandra, who requested the tantra, and to a circle of fortunate disciples, including ninety-six kings, he delivered The Wheel of Time Root Tantra in twelve thousand verses.
This is the explanation according to the system of renowned Tibetan masters of the Wheel of Time, such as Rangjung Dorjé. The lord of Jonang [Taranata] and his followers consider that the teacher spoke [this tantra] in the year following his enlightenment.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="e">
lnga pa [e. gsungs tshul gzhan bshad pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="e">
Other Explanations of the Origin of Tantra [e]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
'bras spungs kho nar rgyud sde ma lus pa/ /bstan par bzhed dang kun rdzob don dam gyi/ /
tha dad gnas su 'khor lo'i mgon po'i skur/ /bzhengs te ston 'khor dbyer med bde chen dang*/ /
nA da'i dbyangs kyis dus kun bsgrags pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Some believe that all tantras were taught only at Treasure Mound Stupa.
Further, in different places, both relative and ultimate,
[The teacher] rose as the wisdom body of the lord of the wheel.
Within great bliss, the teacher and circle of disciples indivisible,
The nada’s melody proclaims the tantras at all times.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bshad ma thag pa de rnams kyang phyogs re ba'i dbang du byas pa yin gyi gzhan du na/ theg pa chen po gsang sngags kyi tshul ni zab pa dang rgya che ba'i mthar thug pa yin pa'i phyir/ 'di kho nar zad kyi 'di las gzhan ma gsungs so zhes smra bar mi nus te/ dpal ldan 'bras spungs kyi mchod rten kho nar rgyud sde ma lus pa rdzogs par bstan par bzhed pa'ang yod cing de la'ang phyogs 'dir ma byon pa'i rgyud sde du ma'i lung khungs grub thob brgyud pa'i bshad rgyun las byung bar grags pa dang*/ 'og min dang*/ dga' ldan dang*/ ri rab kyi rtse dang*/ auD+yan dang*/ dpal ldan 'bras spungs kyi mchod rten la sogs pa gnas kyi bye brag kun rdzob pa'i dbye ba bstan pa dang*/ rdo rje btsun mo'i b+ha ga dang*/ bde ba chen po'i gnas dang*/ chos kyi 'byung gnas thar pa chen po'i pho brang sogs spros mtshan gyi yul thams cad las 'das pa chos kyi dbyings 'gyur ba med pa don dam pa'i gnas rnams su ston pa dpal 'khor lo sdom pa dang*/ dgyes pa rdo rje dang*/ dus kyi 'khor lo la sogs pa dkyil 'khor rgya mtsho'i 'khor lo'i mgon po'i skur bzhengs te/ ji skad du/ 'chad pa po nga chos kyang nga*/ /rang gi tshogs ldan nyan pa nga*/ /'jig rten ston pa bsgrub bya nga*/ /'jig rten 'jig rten 'das pa nga*/ /zhes pa ltar ston 'khor tha mi dad pa bde ba chen po gcig gi rang bzhin las/ rdo rje nA da mi shigs pa'i sgra'i gsang ba chen pos chos kyi 'khor lo dus rtag tu bskor zhing bsgrags par shes par bya'o/ /lung gi chos 'khor bye brag tu dbye ba'i skabs gnyis pa'i 'grel pa'o// //
</d>
<d e="2">
Those explanations just given reflect specific perspectives. Nevertheless, the great way’s mode of secret mantra is the apogee of depth and vastness. Therefore, it is impossible to say, “It happened only in this way and no other; he did not impart tantra apart from this.”
Some believe that all tantras were taught in their entirety only at glorious Treasure Mound Stupa, yet the sources of scriptural transmission of many tantras have not appeared in that place, such as those known to have come from accomplished masters’ teaching lineages. Further, our teacher rose as the wisdom body of the lord of the wheel of an ocean of sacred circles, such as glorious Supreme Bliss, Vajra of Delight, or Wheel of Time [and taught those tantras] in specific places classified as relative, such as Unsurpassed Heaven, Joyful Heaven, Supreme Mountain’s summit, Oddiyana, and glorious Treasure Mound Stupa; and in ultimate places beyond the range of all formulations and characteristics, the changeless basic space of phenomena, such as the Vajra Queen’s bhaga, the place of supreme bliss, and the source of phenomena, the palace of supreme freedom. As is said,
I am the one who teaches.
I am the teaching.
I am the listeners replete with accumulations.
I am the world, the teacher, and the practice.
I am both the mundane and supramundane.
As stated, you should understand that the teacher and the circle of his disciples are inseparable. Within their single nature of great bliss, the indestructible sound (vajra nada) of supreme mystery forever turns the wheel of Dharma and proclaims the tantras.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="skabs gsum pa">
[3. bka'i bsdu ba 'byung tshul]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Chapter 3">
3. Compilations of the Buddha’s Word
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
!_skabs gsum pa bka'i bsdu ba bshad pa la gsum/ bka' bsdu dang po/ bar pa/ tha ma'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This chapter has three parts: (1) the first compilation, (2) the middle compilation, and (3) the final compilation.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
[I. bka' bsdu dang po]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
The First Compilation [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la bzhi/ bsdu ba bya ba'i dgos pa/ theg dman/ theg chen/ rdo rje theg pa bsdus tshul so so'i zhar byung bstan pa'i gnas tshad dang bcas pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has four parts: (1) the necessity for the compilation of the Buddha’s word, (2) compilation of the lesser way, (3) compilation of the great way, and (4) compilation of the vajra way. Each of the latter three is accompanied by a supplement that delineates the teaching’s duration.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
dang po [A. bsdu ba bya ba'i dgos pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
The Necessity for the Compilation of the Buddha’s Word [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
ston pa 'das pa'i phyi lor lha rnams kyis/ /'phya ba sel dang bstan pa yun gnas phyir/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
To dispel the gods’ scorn and to ensure the doctrine’s duration,
The year after the teacher transcended sorrow,
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
ston pa mchog zung 'khor dgra bcom pa du ma dang bcas mya ngan las 'das pa'i phyi lor bka'i bsdu ba dang po byung ste/ de'ang lha rnams kyis bcom ldan 'das dang dge slong dbang yod pa dag kyang 'das pas bcom ldan 'das kyi mdo sde dang 'dul ba dang ma mo dag mi sgrogs so zhes 'phya bar byed pa sel ba dang*/ ma 'ongs pa'i dus kyi dge slong rnams brjed ngas che ba sogs kyis tshig don 'dzin par mi nus pa la phan gdags shing bstan pa rin po che yun ring du gnas par bya ba'i phyir bsdu ba mdzad pa yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In the year after our teacher and the sublime pair [Shariputra and Maudgalyayana], accompanied by many arhats in their circles of disciples, had transcended sorrow, the first compilation of the canon took place.
The gods claimed, “The Transcendent Conqueror and monks with authority have passed away; [those who remain] do not proclaim the Transcendent Conqueror’s discourses, teachings on discipline, and mother teachings!” To dispel such scorn, and to aid ordained persons of future times who would be unable retain the words and their meanings due to severe forgetfulness and other causes, and to ensure the long term preservation of the precious teachings, compilations of the Buddha’s words were made.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
gnyis pa [B. theg dman] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
Compilation of the Lesser Way [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
n+ya gro d+ha yi phug tu dgra bcom pa/ /lnga brgya 'dus te kun dga' nye bar 'khor/ /
'od srung gsum gyis mdo 'dul mngon pa bsdus/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Five hundred arhats gathered in Nyagrodha Cave;
Three—Ananda, Upali, and the eminent Kashyapa—
Compiled the [collections] of discourses, on discipline, and on observed phenomena.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de yang 'od srung chen pos rtswa can nyid du dgra bcom pa gang po la dge 'dun sdus shig par bsgos pas/ des gaN+Di brdung pa dang ba lang bdag ma gtogs pa yul tha dad na gnas pa'i dge slong thams cad 'dus so/ /ba lang bdag sum cu rtsa gsum du 'gog snyoms la gnas pa gang po 'bod du phyin pas sangs rgyas mi bzhugs par shes nas mya ngan las 'das/ de phyin chad su'ang mya ngan las mi 'da' ba 'od srung chen pos khrims su bcas nas/ rgyal po ma skyes dgras yo byad bstabs te 'od srung chen po sogs dge slong lnga brgyar gcig gis lhag pa ma ga d+hA'i n+ya gro d+ha'i phug tu 'dus nas dbyar gnas par khas blangs so/ /de'i tshe sngon bcom ldan 'das kyis 'od srungs chen po la bzhugs gdan gyi phyed bstabs te/ ma mo'i sde snod gtso bor gyur pa'i bstan pa mtha' dag dang*/ sgra gcan zin dang kun dga' bo sogs 'khor bzhi dang bcas pa gtad nas rgyal tshab tu dbang bskur ba yin pa dang*/ bye brag tu mdo'i sde snod kun dga' bo dang*/ 'dul ba nye bar 'khor la gtad pa yin na'ang*/ dge slong lnga brgya las gzhan thams cad dgra bcom pa yin la/ kun dga' bo kho na slob pa rgyun zhugs yin pa'i phyir chags bral du ma gyur na chos bgro ba'i 'os ma yin pas/ 'od srungs chen pos de tshul ji lta bus 'dul bar gzigs te nyes pa brgyad glengs nas bskrad pa dang*/ kun dga' bo mya ngan dang bcas te mchog gi 'dus pa las phyir byung ste br-i dzi'i ljongs su dbyar tshul la zhugs nas br-i dzi'i bu sogs 'khor bzhi la chos ston pa na br-i dzi'i bus dgra bcom pa thob ste/ mngon par shes pas mkhan po'i sems la bltas pa dang*/ de 'dod chags dang ma bral ba'i slob par mthong ste smras pa/ gau tam khyod ni bag med ma mdzad par/ /shing drung thibs por brten nas mya ngan 'das/ /thugs la bzhag ste bsam gtan mdzod cig dang*/ /ring por mi thogs zhi ba'i gnas thob 'gyur/ /zhes bskul ba'i gdams ngag la brten nas rab tu bsgrims pas kun dga' bos dgra bcom pa nyid thob bo/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In Kushinagara [where the Buddha had transcended sorrow], the eminent Kashyapa ordered Arhat Purna, “Summon the spiritual community!” When he beat the wooden beam [as a signal], all monks living in different regions gathered, with the exception of Gavamyati, who had been dwelling in the Heaven of the Thirty-three in the meditative absorption of cessation. When Arhat Purna went to call him, he knew that the Buddha no longer lived [in the world], whereupon he transcended sorrow. Eminent Kashyapa decreed that from then on, no [arhat] could transcend sorrow [at that time].
Then, since King Ajatashatru provided their necessities, eminent Kashyapa and the others—five hundred monks with the exception of the one—assembled in Nyagrodha Cave in Magadha, then pledged to remain there for a monsoon season retreat.
Previously, the Transcendent Conqueror had bestowed half his seat to eminent Kashyapa and empowered him as regent by entrusting to him the entire body of teachings (the collection of mother teachings principal among them), and his four circles of followers—including Rahula and Ananda. Specifically, [the Buddha] entrusted Ananda with the discourses and Upali with the collection on discipline.
While all the other five hundred monks were arhats, only Ananda was still at the point of learning, a stream-enterer, and therefore was not yet free from attachment. Thus it was not suitable for him [to participate in their] religious council. Kashyapa saw how to guide Ananda: he publicly related his eight faults, then expelled him. Stricken with grief, Ananda left the sublime assembly and entered a monsoon-season-style retreat in Vriji province. When he taught the doctrine to the four circles of followers, including a Vriji man, the Vriji man attained the state of arhat. With clairvoyance, [this arhat] gazed at his preceptor’s mind; seeing that Ananda was still training to become free from attachment, [he exhorted him with] these words:
Gautama! Don’t be careless!
Sit in the shade at the foot of a tree, and place your mind
In the transcendence of sorrow! Practice concentration,
And without much delay you will attain the haven of peace!
Based on this profound advice, Ananda [meditated with] intense focus and attained the state of arhat.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de nas kun dga' bo'ang n+ya gro d+ha'i phug tu phyin nas dgra bcom pa lnga brgya dang lhan cig tu gnas pa'i tshe/ 'od srungs chen po dang dgra bcom pa rnams kyis chos bsdu bar bgros te thog mar kun dga' bo gsol gnyis kyi las kyis mdo sde sdud pa por bskos/ dgra bcom pa lnga brgyas snam sbyar bting ba'i khri la kun dga' bo bzhugs te byang chub snying po'i phyogs su rnam par bltas nas sangs rgyas rjes su dran bzhin du thal mo sbyar te sgras khyab par byas nas/ 'di skad bdag gis thos pa'i dus gcig na zhes gleng gzhi nas brtsams mdo sde thams cad rdzogs par bshad pa dang*/ dgra bcom pa de dag bsam gtan bzhi la snyoms par zhugs nas smon shes kyis bltas te ting nge 'dzin las langs nas phan tshun nges par byas/ de nas nye bar 'khor 'dul ba sdud pa por bskos te de nyid seng ge'i khri la 'dzegs pa dang*/ 'od srungs kyis bcom ldan 'das kyis dang por bslab pa'i gzhi gang du bcas/ des smras pa wa ra NA sir ro/ /gang dag gi don du/ dge slong lnga sde'i ched du ste/ gang gi phyir/ 'di lta ste sham thabs zlum por bgo bar bya'o/ /zhes bslab pa bca' bar mdzad do/ /zhes sogs dri lan gyi sgo nas 'dul ba yongs su rdzogs par bsnyad pa dang*/ de dag gis mngon par shes pas bltas te phan tshun nges par byas/ de nas 'od srungs chen pos rang nyid ma bskos par seng ge'i khri la 'khod de/ tshe dang ldan pa dag ma mo lta bu ma mo lta bu zhes bya ba de bdag kho nas smra bar bya ste/ ma mo lta bu ni shes bya'i mtshan nyid rab tu gsal bar byed pa yin te/ 'di ltar dran pa nye bar gzhag pa bzhi dang*/ zhes sogs bshad nas dgra bcom pa rnams kyis phan tshun du nges par byas nas sa bla'i lha rnams kyis kyang ched du brjod pa 'og min gyi bar du yud tsam gyis grags te bka' bsdu ba de la lnga brgyas yang dag par bsdus pa zhes grags so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Thereafter, Ananda returned to Nyagrodha Cave and dwelled among the five hundred arhats. Kashyapa and the arhats then conferred on the compilation of the doctrine. To begin, Ananda was appointed to compile the discourses through a two-stage formal procedure including proposal. The five hundred arhats spread out their upper robes as a throne, and Ananda took his place upon them. He turned his gaze toward Heart of Awakening and placed the palms of his hands together [at his heart] while remembering the Buddha. Filling space with his voice, he recited all the discourses in their entirety, beginning with the introductory formula: “At one time I heard these words. . .” The arhats entered absorption within the four levels of meditative concentration and considered [Ananda’s presentation] with clairvoyance. Once they rose from their meditative state, they collectively confirmed [the discourses as valid].
Then Upali was appointed to compile the discipline. He ascended a lion-supported throne, and eminent Kashyapa asked, “Where did the Transcendent Conqueror first codify the foundation of training?” Upali replied: “At Varanasi.” “For whose sake?” “For the sake of the five monks.” “Why?” “To establish [such] precepts as, `You will wear the lower robe draped evenly around.’“ After the discipline had been presented in its entirety by way of such questions and answers, the arhats considered it with clairvoyance and collectively affirmed it.
Then, on his own, without having been appointed, eminent Kashyapa took his place on the lion-supported throne and announced:
Elders! Of those teachings “commensurable with the mother teachings,” “commensurable with the mother teachings,” [sic] I alone should speak! The teachings commensurable with the mother teachings clarify the attributes of observed phenomena. They consist of the four foundations of mindfulness,...
After his presentation and the arhats’ collective affirmation, even the gods in the sky proclaimed [their approval], which resounded in an instant throughout space up to Unsurpassed Heaven.
This compilation of the canon is known as “the correct compilation by the five hundred.”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
de yang phung po rten 'brel byang phyogs lung*/ /ring po bar ma gcig las 'phros sogs bzhag_/
'dul dang mngon pa dag kyang de bzhin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Aggregates, Interdependence, and Factors of Awakening
Were placed into the Long, Medium-Length, and Increasing-by-One Scriptures, etc.
[Collections on] discipline and observed phenomena, too, [were compiled] in the same way.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang bsdu ba'i tshul ji ltar zhe na/ mdo sde rnams ni phung po dang rab tu ldan pa phung por/ skye mched du ldan pa skye mched du/ rten cing 'brel 'byung 'phags pa'i bden pas rig pa dang yang dag par ldan pa ni/ de gleng gzhi dang ldan par/ nyan thos kyi bshad pa mang ba ni nyan thos kyi bshad par/ sangs rgyas kyi bshad pa mang ba ni sangs rgyas kyi bshad par/ byang phyogs so bdun dang ldan pa lam gyi yan lag tu/ yang dag par brjod pa mang ba yang dag par brjod pa'i sder/ tshigs bcad dang ldan pa yang dag par ldan pa'i lung rnams su so sor bsdus shing*/ gang mdo sde dang po ni lung ring por/ bar ma ni lung bar mar/ tshigs gcig nas tshig bcu'i bar ni gcig las 'phros pa'i lung sogs su bzhag go_/'dul ba'ang ltung ba sde lnga/ rtsod pa zhi byed kyi chos bdun/ bcas pa dang rjes bcas/ so sor spang ba dang gnang ba/ gsol ba'i las/ gzhi bcu bdun sogs sde sder bsdu ba dang so sor dbye ba'i sgo nas gzhung du byas shing*/ mngon pa'ang sde tshan du bsgril ba'i tshul de bzhin du mdzad do/ /de ltar bka' bsdu dang por grags pa 'di ni nyan thos pa rnams dang thun mong gi sde snod bsdu ba'i dngos gzhi yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
How were the teachings compiled? The discourses were compiled as follows: discourses primarily concerned with the aggregates were compiled as Aggregates. Those concerned with the sense bases were compiled as The Sense Bases. Those concerned with knowledge gained through the noble truth of interdependent arising were compiled as [the branch of teachings called] accounts to provide a framework. Those mainly composed of explanations of the pious attendant system were compiled as The Pious Attendants’ Explanations. Those mainly composed of the Buddha’s explanations were compiled as The Buddha’s Explanations. Those concerned with the thirty-seven aspects of awakening were compiled as Branches of the Path. Those mainly composed of correct declarations were compiled as the class of correct declarations.
Discourses expressed in verse were compiled separately into The Authoritative Scriptures. The first discourses [i.e., Aggregates,] were placed into The Long Scriptures; the middle ones [i.e., Interdependent Arising,] into The Medium-Length Scriptures; and those expressed in [groups of enumerated things] from one to eleven [Steps on the Path, etc.], into The Increasing-by-One Scriptures, and so on.
In the collection on discipline, the five classes of downfalls, the seven means to settle disputes, established precepts and subsequent precepts, the different things to be relinquished or permitted, the formal procedures involving proposal, the seventeen bases [of training], etc., were compiled into their respective divisions, and each expanded upon: this constituted the major work. The collection on observed phenomena was similarly composed through gathering [materials pertaining to the same subject] into sections.
Thus, what is known as the “first compilation of the canon” is the main part of the pious attendants’ collection and of the collections held in common [with the great way].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bstan pa'i gnas tshad lo grangs stong du bshad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The measure of the doctrine’s duration is said to be one thousand years.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
nyan thos kyi lugs 'di la bstan pa'i gnas tshad 'dul ba lung phran tshegs las bshad pa ltar gtso cher lo grangs stong phrag gcig tu gnas par 'dod cing*/ de'ang lnga brgya ni bstan pa dngos dang lnga brgya ni gzugs brnyan du 'gyur pa'o/ /ring mtha' dga' ba'i bshes kyi rtogs brjod las yar 'phel drug brgya'i bar du gnas pa'ang bshad de rags pa tsam 'og tu 'byung ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The duration of this system of the pious attendants is as discussed in Various Scriptures on Monastic Discipline, which believes that the main doctrine’s duration would be one thousand years. During the first five hundred years, the doctrine was valid; for the next five hundred years, a mere semblance. As to the doctrine’s farthest limit, The Legend of the Joyful Spiritual Friend states that it would endure until the human life span has increased to six hundred years. I will return to this last point in general below.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="C">
gsum pa [C. theg chen] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="C">
Compilation of the Great Way [C]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
thun min theg pa che rnams ma ga d+hA'i/ /lho phyogs dri med 'byung ba zhes bya'i rir/ /
byang sems 'bum phrag bcu 'dus rdo rje 'dzin/ /byams dang 'jam dpal mdo 'dul mngon pa bsdus/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
For the extraordinary great way teachings,
One million bodhisattvas gathered on Vimalasambhava Mountain in south Magadha.
Vajra Holder, Loving-Kindness, and Gentle Splendor
Compiled the [collections] of discourses, on discipline, and on observed phenomena.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
thun mong ma yin pa'i bsdu ba la rgyu'i theg pa chen po'i sde snod rnams ni/ 'phags yul gyi mkhas pa dag gis yul ma ga d+hA na grong khyer rgyal po'i khab kyi lho phyogs/ bi ma la sam b+ha ba zhes bya ba'i ri la/ byang chub sems dpa' 'bum phrag bcu 'dus te/ phyag na rdo rjes ni mdo sde/ byams pas ni 'dul ba/ 'jam dpal gyis mngon pa rnams bsdus par bshad do/ /rtog ge 'bar ba las kyang*/ theg pa chen po sangs rgyas kyis gsungs pa yin te/ rtsa ba'i sdud pa byed pa po kun tu bzang po dang*/ 'jam dpal dang*/ gsang ba pa'i bdag po dang*/ byams pa la sogs pa rnams kyis bsdus pa'i phyir ro/ /bdag cag gi rtsa ba'i sdud par byed pa nyan thos ni ma yin te/ theg pa chen po'i gsung ni de dag gi yul ma yin pa'i phyir ro/ /zhes bshad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The extraordinary compilation, the collection of cause-based great way teachings, occurred as follows: Scholars of the land of exalted beings convened a million bodhisattvas upon what is called Vimalasambhava Mountain south of Rajgir city in the region of Magadha. It is said that Vajra Holder compiled the [collection of] discourses; Loving-Kindness, [the collection on] discipline; and Gentle Splendor, [the collection on] observed phenomena. Blaze of Reasoning states:
The Buddha spoke the teachings of the great way, since [bodhi sattvas] such as Ever Excellent, Gentle Splendor, Lord of Secrets, and Loving-Kindness were their compilers. Pious attendants were not the compilers of our source teachings because the teachings of the great way are not within the realm [of their comprehension].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
lugs 'dir bstan pa'i gnas tshad mang na yang*/ /yongs grags lnga brgya phrag bcu da lta ni/ /
lung gi le'u yin gsungs klong chen sogs/ /sgrub dus gsum las shes rab skabs su bzhed/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Although this system proposes many measures of the doctrine’s duration,
The most prevalent states that, among ten five-hundred-year periods,
The present is the era of scriptural transmission.
Of the three parts of the spiritual practice era, Longchenpa and others consider this to be the period of training in sublime insight.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
theg pa chen po'i lugs 'dir thun mong la snang ba'i dbang du byas nas tshad ring thung mdo sde so so'i dgongs pa ltar bshad pa dang*/ thun mong ma yin pa'i dbang du byas nas tshad med par gsungs pa sogs mang du snang na'ang*/ ljongs 'di'i dpyod ldan rnams la yongs su grags shing don la gnas par bzhed pa ni lnga brgya phrag bcu ste lnga stong du gnas pa nyid yin la/ de las da lta'i skabs su 'bras bu dang sgrub pa'i skabs yol nas lung gi le'u'i skabs yin par gsungs shing*/ kun mkhyen klong chen pa sogs ni lung dang sgrub pa go brjes nas sgrub dus gsum las tshul khrims dang sems kyi dus rdzogs zin nas shes rab kyi bslab pa gtso bor sgrub pa'i skabs su slebs par bzhed do/ /
bstan pa'i gnas tshad snga phyi thams cad kyi bzhed pa snying por dril na/ lo chen d+harma shrIs/
</d>
<d e="2">
Within our great way system, the extent of the doctrine’s duration in the common perception [of most beings] is as taught according to the intent of each discourse. From an uncommon perspective, many statements appear, such as that the doctrine’s duration is limitless. Nevertheless, the opinion most prevalent among this country’s researchers, and accepted as reasonable by them, is that [the doctrine] will endure for ten five-hundred-year periods—five thousand years. From that total, it is said that the periods of fruition and spiritual practice have elapsed, and that this present period is that of scriptural transmission.
Omniscient Longchenpa and others consider that the times of scriptural transmission and spiritual practice are reversed, and that of the three parts of the spiritual practice era, the periods of ethical conduct and meditation are complete: we have arrived in the period of spiritual practice during which training in sublime insight is foremost.
Lochen Dharmashri writes this distillation of the essence of earlier and later perspectives on the doctrine’s duration:
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
mdo lugs bstan pa'i gnas tshad ni/ /
bskal bzang 'dul lung phran tshegs dang*/ /
'phags pa blo gros mi zad pas/ /
bstan pa'i mdo yi 'grel pa dang*/ /
gser phreng can gyi rtogs brjod dang*/ /
mdzod 'grel rnams las thub pa'i bstan/ /
dngos btags lnga brgya lnga brgya ste/ /
lo stong bar du gnas par gsungs/ /
snying rje pad+ma dkar po las/ /
dngos stong btags pa lnga brgyar bshad/ /
zla ba'i snying pos zhus pa'i mdor/ /
nyis stong gnas par gsungs pa dang*/ /
chos nyid rang ngo mi g.yo bar/ /
tha dad snang ba'i mdo dang ni/ /
rdo rje gcod pa'i 'grel pa las/ /
nyis stong lnga brgyar gnas par gsungs/ /
dga' ba'i bshes kyi rtogs brjod las/ /
skye dgu'i tshe lo yar 'phel gyi/ /
drug brgya'i bar du gnas par bshad/ /
daMSh+Ta? se na'i 'bum TIka? dang*/ /
dbyig gnyen zhabs kyi gnod 'joms dang*/ /
slob dpon 'jam dpal grags pa rnams/ /
lnga stong bar du gnas par bzhed/ /
de yang lnga brgya phrag bcu las/ /
lnga brgya dang por dgra bcom dang*/ /
de bzhin gnyis par phyir mi 'ong*/ /
gsum pa la ni rgyun zhugs te/ /
ye shes khong chud le'u gsum/ /
de nas lnga brgya phrag gsum la/ /
rim par shes rab ting 'dzin dang*/ /
tshul khrims bslab pa gtsor ston gsum/ /
sgrub pa'i dus kyi le'u zer/ /
de nas lnga brgya phrag gsum la/ /
mngon pa mdo sde 'dul ba rnams/ /
ston pa mang du 'byung bas na/ /
lung gi le'u gsum du grags/ /
bcu pa lnga brgya tha ma la/ /
rab byung rtags tsam ma gtogs pa/ /
lta spyod rnal ma med pa'i phyir/ /
rtags tsam 'dzin pa'i le'ur bzhed/ /
de las gzhan rnams dgongs pa can/ /
lnga stong don la gnas par zung*/ /
zhes gsungs pa ltar ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The duration of the discourse system’s doctrine is as follows:
The Fortunate Age Discourse, Various Scriptures on Monastic Discipline, The commentary to The Discourse Requested by Bodhisattva Infinite
Wisdom, The Story of the Gold-Garlanded One,
And The Commentary on “The Treasury of Observed Phenomena”
All state that the Sage’s doctrine will last
In valid form and nominally, for five hundred years each—
One thousand years.
The White Lotus of Compassion Discourse states
The valid doctrine will last one thousand years; the nominal doctrine, for five hundred years.
The Discourse Requested by Chandragarbha
States that the doctrine will abide for two thousand years.
The Discourse of Separate Appearances Within the Unmoving Nature
of Reality, And A Commentary on “The Vajra Cutter Discourse” State that it will abide for two thousand, five hundred years.
The Legend of the Joyful Spiritual Friend
States that the doctrine will abide until the human life span Has increased to six hundred years.
Damshtasena’s Commentary on “The Perfection of Sublime Insight in One Hundred Thousand Verses,” Venerable Vasubandhu’s Defeat of Harm to the Three Versions of the
Mother of Sublime Insight,
And master Manjushrikirti
Consider that the doctrine will abide for five thousand years—
That is, in ten five-hundred-year periods. During the first five hundred, [the fruit of spiritual practice was]
the state of arhat,
Likewise, in the second, the state of non-returner, And in the third, the state of stream-enterer — These are three phases of comprehending wisdom.
During the next three five-hundred-year periods, The three main teachings are training in sublime insight, In meditative states, and in ethical conduct— These are called phases of the period of spiritual practice. During the next three five-hundred-year periods, Many teachers will appear [Who are versed in the collections] on observed phenomena, of
discourses, and on discipline. That period is known as the three-part phase of scriptural transmission.
During the tenth and final five hundred [years], leaving home life
is only an outward show, And there are neither genuine views nor genuine conduct. Therefore, it is said to be the phase of preserving outward appearances only.
Except for this, all other frameworks have underlying intentions;
One should accept this five-thousand-year outline as true.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag 'das lus blta ba'i gzhi sangs rgyas kyi 'khrungs lo'i rnam grangs dang*/ 'das lus rnam grangs tha dad pa ni gsar rnying gi mkhas pa dag gis mdzad pa'i bstan brtsis kyi yig cha du ma las khong du chud par bya'o/ /
'dir bstan pa gnas mi gnas kyi mtshams 'dzin kyang*/ bslab pa gsum brjod byed sde snod dang bcas pa la slob pa yod med dang*/ las brgya rtsa gcig gi cho ga'i lag len nub ma nub dang*/ nyan thos kyi rtags dang cha lugs tshul bzhin 'dzin pa yod med la ltos pa yin gyi/ nges don gyi dbang du byas na mdo sde gser 'od dam pa las/ sangs rgyas mya ngan yongs mi 'da'/ /
chos kyang nub par mi 'gyur te/ /
sems can yongs su smin mdzad phyir/ /
yongs su mya ngan 'da' bar ston/ /
sangs rgyas bcom ldan bsam mi khyab/ /
de bzhin gshegs pa rtag pa'i sku/ /
sems can rnams la phan pa'i phyir/ /
bkod pa rnam pa sna tshogs ston/ /
zhes gsungs pa dang*/ snga 'gyur yid bzhin rnam par bkod pa'i rgyud las/ sems can kun gyi tshogs chen po/ /
ji srid rnam par gnas de srid/ /
sangs rgyas sprul pa rgyun mi 'chad/ /
grol ba'i chos kyang nub pa med/ /
ces gsungs pa ltar ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The basis for these determinations of what has passed and what remains [of those five thousand years], calculations of the Buddha’s birth year, and different calculations of what has passed and what remains, are found within various texts on the doctrine’s chronology written by scholars of the early and later translation schools. You should learn them.
In this case, whether the doctrine abides or not is determined on the basis of whether or not the three trainings, and the collections that explain them, are studied; whether or not the monastic community’s one hundred and one formal procedures are put into practice; and whether or not there are those who keep the outer signs and attire of the pious attendant tradition. From the perspective of the definitive meaning, The Sacred Golden Light Discourse states:
The Buddha does not transcend sorrow, Nor will the teachings disappear.
To fully ripen beings
[The Buddha] demonstrates transcending sorrow.
The Buddha, Transcendent Conqueror, is inconceivable;
For sentient beings’ sake,
The Transcendent Buddha’s eternal body
Is shown in arrays of many forms.
The early translation’s The Wish-Fulfilling Design Tantra states:
As long as the great mass
Of all sentient beings exists,
The flow of enlightenment’s emanations is continuous
And the teachings that liberate do not disappear.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="D">
bzhi pa [D. rdo rje theg pa bsdus tshul] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="D">
Compilation of the Vajra Way [D]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bya spyod rnal 'byor rgyud rnams sum rtsen byang*/ /lcang lo can tu phyag na rdo rjes bsdus/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
At Willow Grove in the North, where the three lords enjoy themselves,
Vajra Holder compiled action, conduct, and yoga tantras.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rgyud sde bzhi las bya ba'i rgyud ni/ gtso bor sum rtsen te sum cu rtsa gsum gyi gnas kyi mtha' ri rab kyi byang phyogs kyi lcogs lcang lo can na sa bcu'i byang chub sems dpa' kun tu bzang po dang*/ rdo rje chos la sogs pas bla gos lnga brgya bting ba'i steng du lag na rdo rje bzhugs te/ 'di skad bdag gis thos pa zhes sogs bshad pa'i tshul gyis bsdus pa yin te/ gtsug tor gdugs dkar gyi 'grel pa shU rAng+ga warmas mdzad pa las de ltar du bshad pa'i phyir/ spyod pa'i rgyud kyang lag na rdo rje dang kun tu bzang po sogs kyis bsdus par gsal te snga ma des de ltar bshad pa dang*/ phyag na rdo rje dbang bskur ba'i rgyud las ston pas gsang ba'i bdag por dbang bskur cing bstan pa gtad pa'i tshul sogs 'byung ba'i phyir ro/ /rnal 'byor rgyud ni lcang lo can du rdo rje 'chang sa bcu'i dbang phyug gi tshul bstan pa phyag na rdo rje nyid kyis kun tu bzang po la sogs pa byang chub sems dpa' chen po rnams kyis gsol ba btab pa'i ngor bsdus pa yin te/ slob dpon kun dga' snying po'i yo ga'i 'grel par tshul de gsal bar bshad pa'i phyir ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Among the four classes of tantra, action tantra [was compiled as follows]: At Willow Grove, Supreme Mountain’s northern turret, border of Heaven of the Thirty-three, where “the three lords enjoy themselves,” tenth-stage bodhisattvas Ever Excellent, Vajra Dharma, and others spread five hundred upper robes on the ground, upon which Vajra Holder took his seat. He compiled the tantra, beginning with the formal presentation, “Thus I have heard. . .” So it is taught in Shurangamavarma’s Commentary on the White Umbrella Crown Tantra.
Vajra Holder, Ever Excellent, and others evidently compiled conduct tantra, since the formerly cited source states this. Further, The Vajra Holder Empowerment Tantra relates such events as how the teacher empowered Lord of Secrets and entrusted him with the teachings.
Yoga tantra [was compiled as follows]: At Willow Grove, Buddha Vajra Bearer took the guise of a sovereign bodhisattva of the tenth stage of awakening, Vajra Holder himself. At the request of sublime bodhisattvas, including Ever Excellent, he compiled the tantra. Master Anandagarbha’s A Commentary on Yoga Tantra clearly describes this.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
bla med zhu ba po dang gtad pa des/ /bsdus shing ston pa pos kyang sdud sogs las/ /
bye brag ma rgyud rdo rje mkha' 'gro rnams/ /dri ba dris lan tshul gyis gtan la phab/ /
brtag pa gnyis pa rdo rje snying pos te/ /dus 'khor rtsa rgyud zla ba bzang po dang*/ /
bsdus rgyud 'jam dpal grags pas snying por dril/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Highest yoga tantras were compiled by those who requested them and by those to whom they were entrusted.
Those who taught them also compiled them, etc.
Specifically, mother tantras were established
In dialogues of questions and answers among vajra dakinis.
Vajra Essence compiled The Vajra of Delight Tantra’s Two Chapters.
King Suchandra compiled The Wheel of Time Root Tantra; Manjushrikirti encapsulated its essence in The Concise Tantra of the Wheel of Time.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rnal 'byor bla na med pa'i rgyud sde rnams ni rgyud thog mar zhu ba po dang rgyud gang la gtad pa des bsdus pa/ dper na dus 'khor rtsa ba'i rgyud chos rgyal zla ba bzang pos bsdus pa lta bu mang zhing*/ dpal gsang ba grub pa'i rgyud las/ 'di yi sdud par byed pa po/ /gzhan dag yod pa ma yin zhes/ /bdag nyid 'ba' zhig smra bar byed/ /zhes gsungs pa ltar/ rgyud ston pa pos kyang bsdus par bshad pa sogs yod pa las/ bye brag ma rgyud 'ga' zhig ni rdo rje phag mo sogs rnal 'byor ma rnams kyis rdo rje'i gnas rnams su dri ba dang dris lan gyi tshul gyis gtan la phab pa mkha' 'gro rgya mtsho las bshad pa dang*/ dgyes pa rdo rje'i rtsa ba'i rgyud brtag pa gnyis pa ni sa bcu'i dbang phyug rdo rje snying pos bsdus shing 'grel pa'ang mdzad pa dang*/ dus kyi 'khor lo'i rtsa ba'i rgyud stong phrag bcu gnyis pa chos rgyal zla ba bzang pos bsdus shing 'grel chen stong phrag drug cu pa'ang mdzad/ bsdus pa'i rgyud ni 'phags pa 'jam dpal gyi sprul pa'i sku rdo rje'i rigs ldan 'jam dpal grags pas rtsa ba'i rgyud las snying por dril te phreng 'dzin gyi sdeb sbyor gyis bcings pa'i le'u lnga par mdzad pa sogs mtha' yas so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The highest yoga tantras were compiled by those who first requested them and by those to whom they were entrusted. An example is The Wheel of Time Root Tantra, compiled by Buddhist King Suchandra; many others follow that pattern. The Glorious Secret Accomplishment Tantra states:
There are no other compilers
Of this tantra:
I alone proclaimed it.
As stated, it is taught that in some cases a tantra’s teacher also compiled it. Among these, in some specific mother tantras, yoginis such as Vajra Sow codified the tantra in dialogues of questions and answers in vajra sacred places. This is taught in An Ocean of Dakas Supreme Bliss Tantra.
In the case of Vajra of Delight’s root tantra, The Vajra of Delight Tantra’s Two Chapters, the sovereign bodhisattva of the tenth stage of awakening Vajra Essence compiled the tantra and also commented upon it. Buddhist King Suchandra compiled The Wheel of Time Root Tantra in twelve thousand verses; he also composed a sixty-thousand-verse major commentary. Exalted Bodhisattva Gentle Splendor’s emanation, vajra Lineage Bearer Manjushrikirti encapsulated the essence of that root tantra in The Concise Tantra of the Wheel of Time. Its five-chapter composition comprises [one thousand and thirty] four-line stanzas of twenty-one syllables each. There are limitless examples such as these.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
kun kyang gsang bdag rnam par rol pa'i phyir/ /sdud po gcig cing gsang chen bstan pa ni/ /
yun ring khyad par ma rgyud nub pa med/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
All were manifestations of Lord of Secrets; thus, the compilers were the same.
The doctrine of supreme mystery long endures;
In particular, the mother tantras will not disappear.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
ston pa po de dag kyang gsang ba'i bdag po dngos sam de'i rnam par rol pa mtshan gzhan du bstan pa tsam yin pa'i phyir thams cad kyang sdud pa po ni gsang ba'i bdag po nyid du gcig ste/ pha rgyud la mtshon na gsang ba 'dus pa las rdo rje chos la rgyud gtad par gsungs shing*/ rdo rje chos ni phyag na rdo rje la rgyud gtad cing dbang bskur ba'i mtshan du zla ba bzang po sogs bzhed cing*/ sdud pa po'ang de yin par bshad pa dang*/ ma rgyud phal che ba gsang bdag dngos kyis bsdus par gsungs shing in+d+ra b+hU ti rdo rje snying po zla ba bzang po rnams kyang gsang bdag gi sprul pa 'ba' zhig tu nges pa'i phyir ro/ /de ltar gsang chen sngags kyi bstan pa ni gnas gcig tu nub kyang gcig tu snang ba dang*/ thun mong du ma grags kyang skal ldan dag gi ngor snang ba sogs yun ring por gnas shing*/ khyad par rnal 'byor ma'i rgyud rnams nam du'ang nub pa med par gnas par gsungs te/ mkha' 'gro rgya mtsho las/ shes rab rgyud ni rang byung nyid/ /rang gi rang bzhin rtag tu gnas/ /byang chub phyogs kyi chos rnams su/ /mi 'jig go 'phang rjes 'gro ba/ /bskal pa bsreg pa'i dus su ni/ /gzhan du song nas yang dag gnas/ /zhes gsungs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
All those teachers of the tantras were Lord of Secrets in person or manifestations of him, merely presented under different names; thus, the sole compiler of all [tantras] was Lord of Secrets.
To illustrate this with the father tantras, The Matrix of Mystery Tantra states that the tantra was entrusted to Vajra Dharma. It is thought that Vajra Dharma is Vajra Holder, to whom the tantra was entrusted; his empowerment name was Suchandra, who was, moreover, the compiler. Most of the mother tantras are said to have been compiled by Lord of Secrets in person, since Indrabhuti, Vajra Essence, and Suchandra are definitely all just his emanations.
The secret mantra doctrine of supreme mystery may vanish in one place but appear in another. Although the tantras are not commonly proclaimed, they appear to fortunate individuals; thus, they endure for a long time. In particular, it is said that the tantras of the yoginis will last without ever disappearing. An Ocean of Dakas Supreme Bliss Tantra states:
The wisdom tantras are self-occurring;
Their nature abides forever.
They follow the indestructible state
Of the factors of awakening.
When this eon burns,
They travel elsewhere and remain intact.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="II">
gnyis pa [II] bka' bsdu bar pa ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="II">
The Middle Compilation [II]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
ston pa gshegs nas brgya dang bcu lon tshe/ /rung ba min pa'i gzhi bcu sun dbyung phyir/ /
grags pa la sogs dgra bcom bdun brgya ni/ /kusma pu ri'i gtsug lag khang du 'dus/ /
bdun brgyas yang dag brjod pa zhes bya ba/ /cha shas bsdu bar mdzad cing*/
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
One hundred and ten years after the teacher had departed to peace,
Seven hundred arhats, including Kirti,
Assembled in the Kusmapuri Temple
To refute ten points of inappropriate conduct.
They carried out a partial compilation
Known as “the correct declaration of the seven hundred.”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
zhes pa ste/ ston pa zhi bar gshegs nas lo grangs brgya dang bcu lon pa'i tshe/ yangs pa can gyi dge slong rnams kyis rung ba ma yin pa'i gzhi bcu byas te/ de'ang ji skad du/ hu lu[1] hu lu yi rangs[2] dang*/ /kun[3] spyod snod[4] dang lan[5] tshwa dang*/ /lam[6] dang sor gnyis[7] dkrug[8] dang 'ding[9]/ /gser gyi rung[10] ba dag dang bcu/ /zhes pa ste/ chos min gyi las byas shing 'jug tu thal mo brdabs te hu lu hu lu zhes brjod pa'am/ yang na dge 'dun lhag ma rnams rjes su yi rangs byas bcug pas dag go zhes pa dang*/ sa gzhi 'di kun gyis spyod rung bas nyes pa med pa yin zhes khyim pa bzhin du sa brko ba dang*/ na bar gyur na chang snod srin bu pad pas 'jib pa ltar gzhib nas chang btung rung ba dang*/ lan tshwa 'debs na zas kyi ro 'gyur bas dus min gyi kha zas za rung ba dang*/ zas spangs zin nas rgyang grags phyed tsam lam du brgal nas slar yang zar rung ba dang*/ zas spangs nas lhag po byas mi dgos par slar sor mo gnyis kyis reg nas zar rung ba dang*/ 'o ma dang zho gnyis bre gang re bsres te dkrugs nas phyi dro 'thung rung ba dang*/ gding ba rnying pa nas bde bar gshegs pa'i mtho gang lhan mi dgos zhes pa dang*/ dge tshul gyi mgo la khri'u cing*/ de'i steng du me tog gi phreng bas brgyan pa'i lhung bzed bzhag ste/ gser dngul sogs 'bul ba der 'phen bcol na phyis dge slong rang nyid kyis reg chog par 'dod pa bcas rung ba ma yin pa'i bzhi bcu spyod nas 'di ni chos yin/ 'dul ba yin/ ston pa'i bstan pa yin no zhes bsgrags pa
</d>
<d e="2">
After one hundred and ten years had elapsed since our teacher had departed to peace, the monks at Vaishali instituted ten points of inappropriate conduct. As is said,
Ten [points of conduct claimed to be pure]:
[1] “Alas!” [2] rejoicing [in wrong conduct], [3] general [land] use,
[4] Use of drinking vessels, [5] using salt, [6] [eating after traveling on] a path, [7] [touching food with] two fingers,
[8] Stirring [milk and yogurt], [9] [discarding the old] mat, and [10] [handling] gold.
[1] Having done what was inappropriate, they afterwards clapped their hands and uttered: “Alas!” [2] On the other hand, they rejoiced in the partially defeating acts and allowed them, saying, “They are pure!” [3] They tilled the soil like laypeople, claiming: “This land can be used by everyone; there is no fault in it.” [4] When sick, they sucked on a vessel [of alcohol] like a leech, claiming that it was admissible to drink alcohol. [5] Since adding salt makes food tasty, [they claimed it] permissible to eat food at inappropriate times. [6] After having stopped eating food [for the rest of the day, they claimed it] permissible to eat again after having traveled a path only half an earshot. [7] Having stopped eating food [for the rest of the day], [they claimed it] permissible to eat again without doing the remainder ritual, having touched the food with two fingers. [8] Having blended a liter of milk and yogurt, and stirred it, [they claimed it] permissible to drink it in the afternoon. [9] They claimed it unnecessary to use a patch the size of the Joyful Buddha’s hand span from one’s old mat [when making a new one]. [10] They fastened a small frame upon a novice monk’s head, and placed a begging bowl decorated with garlands of flowers upon it. If offerings of gold and silver, etc., were tossed into it, the fully ordained monks believed it permissible for them to later handle [such offerings]. Having conducted themselves in these ways, they proclaimed, “This is the Dharma! This is the discipline! This is the Master’s teaching!”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag sun dbyung zhing bstan pa'i dri ma bsal ba'i slad du/ rnam thar brgyad dang ldan pa'i dgra bcom pa grags pa la sogs pa gnyis ga'i cha las rnam par grol zhing mang du thos pa'i dgra bcom pa bdun brgya/ kusma pu ri zhes bya ba'i gtsug lag khang du 'dus te/ li ts+tsha bI'i rigs las byung ba'i rgyal po dga' byed ces bya bas sbyin bdag byas te/ dngos po bcu bsgrags nas/ de dag mdo sde la mi 'jug_/'dul ba la mi snang*/ chos nyid dang 'gal bas dor bar bya bar bcas te mi rung bar spyod pa rnams bsnyil bas/ 'di la bdun brgyas yang dag par brjod pa zhes grags shing cha shas kyi bsdu ba mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
To refute those statements and to rid the doctrine of this corruption, seven hundred arhats who were liberated from the two [obscurations] and were well educated—including Arhat Yashah who possessed the eight [qualities of] liberation—assembled in Kusmapuri Temple. King Nandin, descendant of the Licchavi clan, was their patron. Theyenumerated the ten issues; since these were not included in the discourses, did not appear in the discipline, and contradicted the nature of reality, it was decided to reject them. Thus, they eliminated these inappropriate practices. This is referred to as “the correct declaration by the seven-hundred”; it constitutes a partial compilation.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="III">
gsum pa [III] bka' bsdu tha ma ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="III">
The Final Compilation [III]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
de yi rjes/ dge slong ma hA de ba slob mar bcas/ /
gzhi lnga bsgrags pas rtsa ba'i sde bzhi dang*/ /de las gyes pa bco brgyad nyid du gyur/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Following that,
The monk Mahadéva, together with his followers,
Proclaimed five points, through which the four basic orders
And the branches of these, the eighteen orders, developed.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'i rjes gtad rabs bdun po sogs rdzogs pa'i phyis zhig na yul ma ru Da'i tshong dpon gyi bu lha chen po zhes pa mtshams med gsum byas pa zhig rang gi sdig pa gsang ste kha cher byin nas/ rab tu byung*/ sde snod gsum ga byang bar shes nas dben par ting nge 'dzin la brtson pa na bdud kyis byin gyis brlabs te dgra bcom par grags shing rnyed bkur dang grags pa 'phel nas 'khor mang po dang bcas gtsug lag khang 'dam bu can du 'ongs pa na dge slong rnams kyis so thar gyi mdo res mos su 'don pa'i tshe/ lha chen pos mdo bton pa'i 'jug tu/ lha rnams ma rig pa yis slus/ /lam ni sgra yi rgyun las byung*/ /the tshom can rnams gzhan gyis 'jug_/'di ni sangs rgyas bstan pa yin/ /zhes bton pas 'phags pa rnams dang dge slong rgan po mang du thos pa dag gis mdo'i tshig ma yin no zhes brjod pa na/ gzhon pa phal cher lha chen po'i grogs byas te rtsod par gyur cing*/ gzhan yang des bka'i don la log par brtags pa mang du byas so/ /de shi nas de'i slob ma bzang po zhes pas kyang bka'i don la brgal brtag dang the tshom gyi gnas mang po bskyed nas gzhan la lan gdab pa dang*/ mi shes pa dang*/ yid gnyis dang*/ yongs su brtag pa dang*/ bdag nyid gsob ste gzhi lnga yongs su bsgrags pas dge 'dun so so'i skye bo rnams the tshom dang yid gnyis kyis bstan pa la mi mthun par zing zing por gyur te/ mdo 'don pa'ang sna tshogs su gyur cing dgra bcom pa rnams kyis kyang rtsod pa zhir ma btub/ de dag shi ba na dge slong rnams kyis shes so/ /de'i rjes su dge slong klu zhes bya bas kyang gzhi lnga bsgrags pas slar yang dge 'dun gyi rtsod pa cher bskyed nas phal chen pa/ thams cad yod smra ba/ gnas brtan pa/ mang bkur ba ste rtsa ba'i sde pa bzhir gyes/ klu'i slob ma yid brtan ces bya bas kyang gzhi lnga bsgrags te rtsod pa rgya cher bskyed pas rtsa ba'i sde pa bzhi po dag kyang rim gyis gyes nas bco brgyad du gyur to/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Following the middle compilation, after the line of the seven patriarchs and others had ended, Mahadéva, son of a great merchant from the country of Maruta, committed three of the [five] acts of immediate fruition, but hid his misdeeds, went to Kashmir, and renounced home life. After he became well versed in all three collections, he diligently applied himself to meditative states in seclusion. Blessed by demons, he became known as an arhat; his riches, honor, and fame swelled. When he went with many followers to Nalanda Temple, the monks would recite The Individual Liberation Discourse in turns. At the conclusion of the discourse’s recitation, Mahadéva chanted,
The gods are deceived in ignorance!
The path has arisen from the continuity of sound!
The doubters are converted [to the doctrine] by others!
This is the teaching of the Buddha.[5]
Exalted beings and elder, learned monks exclaimed, “These are not words from the discourses!” while the majority of young monks sided with Mahadéva. A dispute erupted. Moreover, Mahadéva distorted many aspects of the canon’s meaning.
After his death, his follower Bhadra also fostered many ideas that contradicted the canon’s meaning and raised many points of doubt. He then proclaimed five ways [of challenging the doctrine]: refutation, non-discernment, uncertainty, critical examination, and self-indulgence. In doubt and uncertainty, the monastic community of ordinary individuals fell into chaotic disagreement on the doctrine, and The Individual Liberation Discourse was recited in many different styles. Even arhats were unable to settle the controversy. When Bhadra and his followers died, the monks understood [Bhadra’s errors].
Later, a monk called Naga also proclaimed those five ways [of challenging the doctrine] through which he again incited a serious dispute. Thus, the monastic community split into the four main orders—majority, substantialist, elders, and followers of Mahasammata. Naga’s disciple, known as Stiramati, also proclaimed these five ways, provoking a far-reaching debate. Thus, the four basic orders gradually divided into eighteen.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de las gyes pa bco brgyad ni/ sde pa tha dad bklag pa'i 'khor lo las/ /shar[1] dang nub[2] dang gangs[3] rir gnas/ /'jig rten 'das[4] par smra ba'i sde/ /btags par[5] smra ba'i sde pa dang*/ /lnga tshan dge 'dun phal chen pa/ /gzhi[1] kun pa dang 'od srung[2] sde/ /sa[3] ston sde dang chos srung[4] sde/ /mang thos[5] gos dmar[6] slob ma dang*/ /rnam par phye ste smra[7] ba'i sde/ /thams cad yod par smra ba yin/ /rgyal byed[1] tshal gnas 'jigs med[2] gnas/ /gtsug lag[3] khang chen gnas brtan pa/ /sa[1] sgrogs ri dang srung ba[2] pa/ /gnas ma[3] bu yi sde rnams ni/ /kun gyis bkur ba rnam pa gsum/ /yul don slob dpon bye brag gis/ /tha dad rnam pa bco brgyad gsungs/ /zhes pa ltar yin zhing*/ 'di skabs rtsa ba'i sde pa'i grangs dang*/ de las gyes tshul sogs sde pa rnams kyi 'dod tshul mi 'dra ba yod mod kyi 'dir bkod pa ni thams cad yod smra nyid kyi lugs ltar ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Wheels of Reading of the Various Schools enumerates these eighteen secondary orders:
[1] The dwellers in the east, [2] dwellers the west, [3] dwellers in the Himalayas;
[4] The order of the assertion of the transcendence of the world, And [5] the nominal assertion order— These five [were the divisions of the] majority order.
[6] The basis of all, [7] the order of eminent Kashyapa,
[8] The world expression order, [9] the Dharma preservation order,
[10] The well-educated order, [11] the students of Red-Robed, And [12] the analysis and assertion order Were the [seven divisions of the] substantialist order.
[13] The dwellers in Jetavana, [14] dwellers in Abhayagiri,
and [15] dwellers in the large temple were the [three divisions of the] elders’ order.
[16] Kaurukulla order, [17] the guardians’ order, And [18] Vastiputra’s order Were the three divisions of the followers of Mahasammata’s
[order].
[These] eighteen distinct divisions have been taught
Based upon differentiation in terms of place, tenet, or master.
Although at that time there were different beliefs concerning the number of basic orders and the process through which they divided, etc., what is recorded here corresponds to the view of the substantialist order.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rtsibs logs la sogs dgra bcom lnga brgya dang*/ /btsun pa bzhi brgya rgyal po ka naSh+kis/ /
spyan drangs gyes pa dkar bsgrubs sde snod gsum/ /yi ger bkod de bka' bsdu gsum par mdzad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
King Kanishka summoned five hundred arhats, including Parshva,
And four hundred venerable monks.
The [different] orders were established as the canon and the three collections were committed to writing.
Thus, the third compilation of the canon was carried out.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'i tshe 'phags pa rtsibs logs zhes bya ba mang du thos pa mthar phyin pa gtso bor gyur pa'i dgra bcom pa lnga brgya dang*/ ba su mi tra la sogs pa'i btsun pa bzhi brgya rnams dang*/ byang chub sems dpa' lnga brgya rnams kyang rgyal po ka niSh+kas spyan drangs/ kha che'i yul du rna rgyan gyi gtsug lag khang gsar du bzhengs pa la bzhugs su gsol zhing bsnyen bkur te/ gyes pa bco brgyad po thams cad kr-i kr-i rmi lam lung bstan gyi mdo las/ rgyal po chen po khyod kyis ras yug gcig mi bco brgyad kyis bgos kyang ma ral ba rmi lam du mthong ba gang yin pa de ni de nyid kyi bstan pa sde bco brgyad du gyes par gyur kyang rnam par grol ba'i ras ni ral bar bya bar mi nus te de'i snga ltas yin no/ /zhes pa'i lung gis bkar bsgrubs shing chos mngon pa rnam par bshad de 'di la bka' bsdu gsum par grags/ de'i tshe 'dul ba thams cad yi ger bkod/ mdo sde dang mngon pa sngar yi ger ma 'khod pa rnams kyang yi ger bkod/ bkod pa rnams la dag ther byas so/ /'di skabs kha che ba rnams kyis 'di ltar 'dod pa las yul dbus kyi mkhas pa dag gis ni dzA lan+d+hA ra'i dgon par ku sa na zhes bya ba'i gtsug lag khang du de ltar bka' bsdu gsum pa mdzad par bzhed do/ /bka'i bsdu ba rnams bshad pa skabs gsum pa'i 'grel pa'o// //
</d>
<d e="2">
At that time, King Kanishka summoned five hundred arhats, the consummately learned noble Parshva chief among them; four hundred venerable monks, including Vasumitra; and five hundred bodhisattvas. He welcomed them to stay at the newly built Karnikavana Temple in Kashmir, where he served them. [The council] stated,
Concerning all eighteen divisions, we consider what appears
in The Discourse on the Prophetic Dreams of King Kriki to be an
omen. The discourse states:
Great King! What you have seen in your dream—a bolt of cloth worn by eighteen men without being torn—means that, although this very doctrine will split into eighteen orders, the cloth of liberation cannot be rent.
This scriptural transmission established [all eighteen orders] as the canon. Then the collection on observed phenomena was taught in its entirety. This is known as the third compilation of the canon. At that time, the complete collection on discipline was committed to writing. Those parts of the [collections] of discourses and on observed phenomena that had not previously been written down were also recorded, and all that had been recorded was subjected to revision.
Kashmiri [scholars] believe that these events took place as just described, whereas scholars of the central regions [of India] think that the third compilation of the canon was carried out in the Kusana Temple at Jalandhara Monastery.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="skabs bzhi pa">
[4. snga 'gyur rnying ma'i babs lugs bye brag tu bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Chapter 4">
4. The Origins of the Early Translations’ Ancient Tradition
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
!_skabs bzhi pa snga 'gyur rnying ma'i bab lugs bshad pa la gnyis/ rgyud sde'i bab lugs spyir bshad pa/ sgrub sde bye brag tu dbye ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This chapter has two parts: (1) a general explanation of the descent of the tantras and (2) a classification of their specific meditation practices.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
[I. rgyud sde'i bab lugs spyir bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
The Descent of the Tantras [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la gnyis/ mdor bstan/ rgyas bshad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) a brief presentation and (2) a full explanation of the descent of the tantras.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
dang po [A. mdor bstan] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
A Brief Presentation [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
snga 'gyur rnying ma'i lugs su gsang chen gyi/ /bstan pa'i bab lugs chen po rnam pa gsum/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In the tradition of the Ancient school of the early translations,
The doctrine of great mysteries has three major styles of descent.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
snga 'gyur rnying ma'i rang lugs su gsang chen rdo rje theg pa'i bstan pa la bab lugs chen po gsum gyi tshul du rnam par bzhag pa yin te/ bshad rgyud rgya mtsho las/ rgyal ba sems dpa' rnal 'byor ma/ /dgongs pa rig pa rna bar brgyud/ /gang la thug gi bar du'o/ /zhes gsungs pas so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In the Ancient tradition of the early translations, the vajra way’s doctrine of great mysteries is presented as having three major styles of descent. The Ocean Tantra of Explanation states:
Victorious buddhas, bodhisattvas, and yoginis Transmitted [their teachings in lineages] through wisdom mind, awareness, and hearing To specific [lineage holders].
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
[B. rgyas bshad]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
The Full Explanation of the Descent of the Tantras [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa rgyas par bshad pa la gsum/ rgyal ba dgongs brgyud/ rig 'dzin brda brgyud/ gang zag snyan brgyud zhar 'phros dang bcas pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: (1) the victors’ lineage transmitted through wisdom mind, (2) awareness holders’ lineage transmitted through symbols, and (3) human individuals’ lineage transmitted through hearing (and a supplementary section).
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
[1. rgyal ba dgongs brgyud]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
The Victors’ Lineage Transmitted through Wisdom Mind [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la gsum/ ston pas gsungs tshul/ 'khor gyis bsdus tshul/ bstan pa'i gnyer gtad tshul lo/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: (1) how the teachers spoke the teachings, (2) how the retinue compiled the teachings, and (3) how the doctrine was entrusted.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="a">
dang po [a. ston pas gsungs tshul] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="a">
How the Teachers Spoke the Teachings [a]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rang snang rnam dag 'og min chos dbyings su/ /kun tu bzang pos ye shes rgya mtsho la/ /22
'od gsal 'dus ma byas pa'i dgongs pa ni/ /bsam mi khyab dus rang bzhin snang bar mdzad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In the self-manifest pure Unsurpassed Realm, the basic space of phenomena,
To [his retinue,] oceans of wisdom, throughout inconceivable time,
Buddha Ever Excellent naturally illuminates
The wisdom mind of uncompounded clear light.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
ston pa la chos sku gzugs sku'i rnam bzhag gnyis su yod pa'i dang po ni/ ngo bo ka nas dag cing glo bur rang snang 'khrul pa'i dri ma gzhi thog tu rnam par dag pa la 'og min ces sgras btags pa'i chos kyi dbyings snying po byang chub kyi dkyil 'khor rang snang ba phyogs bcu'i rgyud du mi gtogs shing rgya tshad ris su ma chad pa'i gnas su/ ston pa rang byung rig pa'i ngo bo chos nyid bya rtsol las 'das pa sangs rgyas thams cad kyi spyi mes 'khor 'das kun gyi spyi dpal gdod ma'i mgon po kun tu bzang pos/ 'khor gdangs gsal ma 'gag par sku dang ye shes kyi dkyil 'khor rgya mtsho cir yang snang ba la/ 'khor 'das thams cad ye nas mngon par byang chub pa'i ngo bo lhun gyis grub pa'i 'od gsal zang thal 'dus ma byas pa'idgongs pa/ skye 'gag 'pho 'gyur med pa bsam gyis mi khyab pa'i dus su rang bzhin gyis snang bar mdzad pa ste/ 'di ltar chos sku'i phun sum tshogs pa lnga ldan ni dbyings stong pa ngo bo nyid gzhon nu bum pa sku'i yon tan gyi cha la ming gis sgro btags pa tsam las mtshan mar bzung ba gang yang ma mchis so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The teacher is presented in two frameworks: as the body of ultimate enlightenment and as a wisdom body that has form.
First, the essence of being is originally pure and, in relation to its self-manifestation, [is free from] transitory defilements of delusion, which have been purified directly upon the basis of being. This essence of being is designated by the term “Unsurpassed Realm.” It is the basic space of phenomena, the self-manifest sacred circle of essential awakening not belonging to [the dualistic] minds [of beings in] the ten directions, and not defined by size, limits, or orientation. In that location, the teacher is the primordial lord Buddha Ever Excellent, himself the essence of self-arisen awareness, the nature of reality that transcends activity and eff ort, forefather of all buddhas, and sovereign splendor of all the wheel of life and transcendent states. His circle of disciples is his unobstructed manifest expression—ocean-like sacred circles of enlightenment’s bodies and wisdom, appearing as anything whatsoever. [His teaching is] wisdom mind, unimpeded and unconditioned clear light, spontaneously present as the essence of the wheel of life’s and transcendent states’ primordial manifest awakening. He naturally manifests during inconceivable time without arising, ceasing, or change.
That which is endowed with these five marvels [of location, teacher, disciples, teaching, and time] of the body of ultimate enlightenment, the very essence of empty basic space, can be embroidered with names for aspects of the youthful vase body’s qualities, yet within it, it is impossible to grasp any inherent attributes whatsoever.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
snang char stug po bkod par mtshan rdzogs skus/ /rang snang 'khor la dus bzhi mnyam nyid dang*/ /
rdzogs pa chen po ming tshig rang mtshan las/ /'das pa'i gsung gis rgyun mi 'chad du spro/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In Richly Adorned, [wisdom’s] manifest aspect, a wisdom body with the complete marks and signs of physical perfection,
Expresses great perfection
In ceaseless wisdom speech beyond self-characterized words and terms
To self-manifest disciples within evenness, the fourth time.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa gzugs sku rnams kyi thog mar rang snang longs sku ni/ chos sku'i dbyings las gzhi snang ye shes chen po'i snang char rang byung ba'i gnas lhun grub stug po bkod par/ ston pa rigs thams cad kyi khyab bdag rdo rje 'chang mtshan dpe gsal rdzogs kyi skur shar bas/ rigs lnga'i tshom bu ye shes kyi rang mdangs su snang ba gcig dang tha dad kyi spros pa dang bral ba'i 'khor la/ dus bzhi mnyam pa nyid 'pho 'gyur dang bral ba'i ngang du/ chos rang bzhin rdzogs pa chen po bstan pa thams cad kyi snying po yang dag pa'i dgongs pa nyid ming tshig rang mtshan las 'das pa'i gsung gis dus gsum rgyun mi 'chad du spro bar mdzad de gdul bya 'dul byed du shar ba ma yin pas sa bcu pa rnams kyi spyod yul las kyang 'das par bzhugs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Second, the first wisdom body that has form is the self-manifest body of complete rapture.
The basis of being’s appearances that arise from the body of ultimate enlightenment’s basic space, supreme wisdom’s manifest aspect, constitute the self-occurring location—the spontaneously present Richly Adorned Realm. There, the teacher is Buddha Vajra Bearer, lord who pervades all families of wisdom, and who arises as a wisdom body complete with the distinct marks and signs of physical perfection. His circle of disciples comprises the five families’ gatherings, appearing as wisdom’s natural inner glow, free from formulations of being identical or different. To them, in the continuum of unchanging evenness, the fourth time, he expresses the teachings of natural great perfection, essence of all teachings, his true wisdom mind. Throughout the three times, he unceasingly projects his wisdom speech beyond the scope of self-characterized words and terms.
Since a teacher who guides and those to be guided do not arise at this level, he dwells beyond the experiential range of even those [bodhisattvas who dwell on] awakening’s tenth stage.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
thugs rje'i gzhan snang rigs lnga'i khang brtsegs su/ /ston pa rnam lngas zab dbang gsum la sogs/ /
dgongs pa brda dang 'chad pa'i tshul drug gis/ /thabs kyi theg pa rgyal tshab rnams la ston/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
As compassionate manifestations perceived by others,
Five teachers grant three profound empowerments in the five wisdom families’ palaces.
With wisdom mind, symbols, and six modes of exposition,
They teach the way of techniques to their regents.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'i ngang las gdul bya rnams la yang dag pa'i thugs rje'i dbang gis/ sa bcu'i dbang phyug rnams kyi gzhan snang du/ dbus na stug po bkod pa/ shar du mngon dga'/ lhor rin po ches brgyan pa/ nub tu bde ba can/ byang na las rab grub pa ste rigs lnga'i zhing khams 'od kyi khang bu brtsegs pa rnams su/ ston pa de bzhin gshegs pa rigs lnga'i rgyal ba rnam pa lngas/ lhan cig pa'i 'khor rnams la zab mo'i dbang gsum bskur bas brjod bya don gyi rgyud rtogs te rang don du sangs rgyas so/ /de nas gzhan don du zhu ba phul bas ston pa thugs rje skyes te/ dgongs pa brda'i gsung dang 'chad pa'i tshul drug gis nang pa dbang sgyur thabs kyi theg pa'i chos sgo rgyal tshab kyi sa la gnas pa'i 'khor rnams la bstan par mdzad do/ /'dir 'chad tshul drug ni/ sku drang por bsrangs/ smin ma gzengs gtod/ spyan zim bur gzigs/ zhal gyi sgo dbye/ dung gi tshems bar nas ljags kyi dbang po brkyangs te tshangs pa'i dbyangs su gsungs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
With true compassion for disciples, the transcendent buddhas appear within the constant state [just described].
In the objective perception of sovereign bodhisattvas of awakening’s tenth stage, palaces of light stand in the five wisdom families’ realms— Richly Adorned in the center, Truly Joyful to the East, Adorned with Jewels to the South, Blissful to the West, and Fulfilled Action to the North. In them, the teachers, transcendent buddhas, the five wisdom families’ victors, grant their coexistent circle of disciples the three profound empowerments. They thereby realize the subject, the ultimate tantra, and attain enlightenment, accomplishing their goal.
Subsequently, in response to requests made to the teachers to aid others, compassion arose in them: with wisdom mind, symbolic speech, and six modes of exposition, they teach approaches to the inner way of mastery, the way of techniques, to circles of disciples who dwell at the level of regents.
The six modes of exposition are keeping the body straight, eyebrows heightened, eyes gazing half-closed, mouth open, tongue extended between conch-white teeth, and speech in Brahma’s melodious voice.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
de tshe ma dag zhing du bca' gzhi yi/ /ston pa drug gis lam stegs chos sgo spro/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
At that time, they produce in impure realms’ perceptions
Six teachers who disseminate approaches to the teachings that support the path.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
phyed sprul longs sku'i chos bstan pa de'i tshe ma dag pa'i zhing 'gro ba rigs drug gi gnas rnams su thun mong bca' gzhi'i ston pa drug spros te/ de dag gis 'dul bya rgyud ma dag pa dang blo dman pa rnams la thun mong lam stegs kyi theg pa'i chos sgo mtha' yas pa bstan cing spro bar mdzad do/ /gzhan yang de dag gi tshe drag po 'jigs byed gtum po sogs gdul bya gdug pa can rnams kyi ngor dpal he ru ka'i rnam par snang bas khro bo'i dkyil 'khor sprul par mdzad pa sogs gang 'dul zhi khro'i rnam pa dpag tu med pa ston par gsungs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
While presenting the teachings of the partially apparent body of rapture, [the buddhas] send forth the six teachers to impure realms, abodes of the six kinds of beings, to appear in their common perception. To disciples with impure minds and inferior attitudes, the six present and disseminate infinite approaches to the teachings that support the common spiritual path.
Moreover, during these times, in the presence of beings to be subdued, such as wrathful Fierce Terrifying Demon, buddhas are said to appear in the aspect of Glorious Héruka, who emanates wrathful deities’ sacred circles. In this and other ways, they display infinite peaceful and wrathful forms to guide others in modes attuned to individuals’ needs.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
gtsang ma'i gnas su sangs rgyas 'byung ba'i sngon/ /chos mthun longs skus grub pa'i rig 'dzin la/ /
pha rol phyin dang phyi rgyud sde gsum gsungs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
In the pure domains, before the Buddha appears [in this world],
A body with qualities similar to the body of rapture
Teaches the transcendent perfections and the three outer tantras to accomplished masters and awareness holders.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
mi mjed la sogs pa'i gnas kyi mchog gtsang ma ris kyi 'og min du 'jig rten na sangs rgyas 'byung ba'i sngon rol du/ longs sku chen po dang chos mthun pa'i mtshan dpe rgyan ldan gyi sangs rgyas su bstan nas/ lha dang grub pa dang rig pa 'dzin pa'i 'khor tshad med pa la/ kun 'byung 'dren pa'i theg pa pha rol tu phyin pa dang*/ dka' thub rig byed kyi theg pa phyi rgyud sde gsum gsungs pa yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In Unsurpassed [Heaven] of the pure domains, the most sublime place in Endurance and other [world-systems], before the Buddha appears in the world, he presents himself as a buddha endowed with the adorning marks and signs of physical perfection similar to the qualities of the supreme body of rapture. To an immeasurable circle of gods, accomplished masters, and awareness holders, he teaches the transcendent perfections of the way that liberates from the origin of suffering, and the three outer tantras of the way of vedic asceticism.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="b">
gnyis pa [b. 'khor gyis bsdus tshul] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="b">
How the Retinue Compiled the Teachings [b]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
gzhan snang brda dang tshig las byung ba'i rgyud/ /rdo rje chos rab mi yi thod pa can/ /
DA ki pUr+Na nyer zhi sogs kyis bsdus/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
As a manifestation perceived by others, the tantras arisen from symbols and words
Were compiled by sublime Vajra Dharma, Holder of a Human Skull,
Dakini Calm Purna, and others.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
thugs rjes gzhan snang du snang ba'i ston pa rnams kyis gzhan snang tsam du brda yis go bar mdzad pa dang*/ rnga sgra dang sgra brnyan bzhin ngag tshig tu nye bar snang ba las byung ba'i rgyud rnams ni/ gsang bdag rdo rje chos dang*/ bram ze mi yi thod pa can/ DA ki ma pUr+Na nye bar zhi ba dang*/ sogs khongs nas man ngag rdzogs pa chen po rnams rgyal tshab rdo rje sems dpa' dang*/ lung a nu yo ga rig 'dzin gyi rgyal po kuny+dza ra sogs kyis sangs rgyas rnams kyi sku'i rnam 'gyur/ gsung gi brda/ thugs kyi dgongs don ma lus pa rgyud kyi rang bzhin du gtan la phab nas mi mngon rig pa 'dzin pa'i gnas su bsdus shing sdud pa po de dag kyang gdod ma'i mgon po'i thugs ye shes chen po'i rang rtsal bcom ldan 'das gsang ba'i bdag po'i ngo bor gcig pas ston 'khor dbyer med dgongs pa mnyam nyid ngang las gang zag gzhan rgyud kyis bsdus pa ma yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
All teachers who compassionately appeared in modes perceptible by other beings imparted understanding through symbols only in others’ perceptions. The tantras that arose from appearances as spoken words, [audible] like the sound of a drum or an echo, were compiled by Lord of Secrets Vajra Dharma, Brahmin Holder of a Human Skull, and Dakini Calm Purna.
The “others” [referred to in the root text] include the regent Vajrasattva, who compiled great perfection’s pith instructions; and Kunjara, sovereign awareness holder, who compiled the scriptural transmission anuyoga. They finalized every expression of the buddhas’ wisdom bodies, every symbol of their wisdom speech, and every intent of their wisdom minds as the nature of tantra, and compiled them in the non-manifest domains of awareness holders.
Further, these compilers are the self-manifestation of the primordial lord’s supreme wisdom, one in essence with Transcendent Conqueror Lord of Secrets. Therefore, the teacher and his circle of disciples were indivisible within the constant state of equanimity of their wisdom minds; individuals with autonomous mind streams did not perform this compilation.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="c">
gsum pa [c. bstan pa'i gnyer gtad tshul] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="c">
How the Teachings Were Entrusted [c]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rigs gsum mkha' 'gro chos kyi spyan can la/ /bstan pa'i gnyer gtad mdor na sku gsum gyi/ /
ston pa'i gleng gzhi rgyal ba dgongs brgyud do/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The doctrine was entrusted to the lords of the three kinds of beings,
To the dakinis, and to those possessing the eyes of the Dharma.
In short, the teacher’s three-body framework is the victors’ wisdom mind transmission.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de lta bu'i rgyud sde zab mo rnams sdud pa po gsang ba'i bdag po gtso bor gyur pa'i rgyal sras rigs gsum mgon po dang*/ 'khor 'das thams cad kyi bdag mo sku gcig la mtshan gyi rnam grangs du ma dang ldan pa mkha' 'gro ma las kyi dbang mo che ye shes kyi mkha' 'gro ma'i tshogs dang bcas pa rnams la dngos su gnyer gtad nas bka' bsgos shing*/ brgyud nas phyi rabs brgyud 'dzin gyi gang zag chos kyi spyan can rnams la'ang lung bstan cing bstan pa'i gnyer gtad de/ khog gzhung las/ sdud pa po dang bud med dang*/ /rnal 'byor mig ldan sogs la'o/ /zhes gsungs pas so/ /de ltar bshad pa de dag mdor bsdu na/ ston pa sku gsum gyi gleng gzhi dang 'brel ba dgongs pa ro gcig tu mnyam pas chos bstan bya ston byed med kyang ye shes kyi rtsal las tshul tsam du snang bas rgyal ba dgongs pa'i brgyud pa zhes bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
[The teacher] directly entrusted and assigned all these profound tantras to compilers: the Victor’s spiritual heirs, lords of three kinds of beings, led by Lord of Secrets; and the queen of the wheel of life and transcendent states, great Dakini Sovereign of Activity, who has one form but many names, together with her host of wisdom dakinis. He predicted the individuals in future generations who would be lineage holders endowed with the eyes of the Dharma, thus entrusting them with the teachings. The Framework Scripture states:
...to the compilers, the women,
Adepts endowed with the eyes [of Dharma], and others.
To summarize these explanations, within the context of the framework of the teacher’s three bodies, wisdom mind has a single flavor within evenness. Thus, there is nothing to teach and no teaching, yet the teachings appear as a seeming process that unfolds from wisdom’s manifest expression. Thus it is called, “the victors’ wisdom mind transmission.”
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
[2. rig 'dzin brda brgyud]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
Awareness Holders’ Lineage Transmitted through Symbols [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa rig 'dzin brda brgyud bshad pa la gnyis/ a ti'i lugs/ yo ga phyi ma gnyis kyi lugs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the ati system and (2) the systems of the two other yogas [i.e., mahayoga and anuyoga].
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="a">
dang po [a. a ti'i lugs] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="a">
The Ati System [a]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
dus drug tshe na rtsol med theg pa ni/ /sems lhag can la rdor sems dbang skur stsal/ /
lha yi gnas dar de nyid mi yul du/ /sprul pa'i skur bzhengs dga' rab rdo rje yis/ /
dbang rgyud mdzod thob bstan pa'i bdag por gyur/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
When six [conditions prevailed], the effortless way
Was given through empowerment by Vajrasattva to a god named Altruistic;
It spread in the gods’ realm.
[The god Altruistic] then rose in the human world as enlightenment’s manifestation Garab Dorjé,
Who received empowerment and the tantras’ treasury, and became the doctrine’s chief.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rdzogs pa chen po'i bstan pa ni/ ji skad du/ nyon mongs[1] rgyud drag nus mthu[2] zhan/ /las kyis tshe thung[3] bka'i don stor[4]/ /bstan snying grub mtha'[5] ngan pas bsgyur/ /gnyen pos[6] mi non sgrub tshug zhan/ /de tshe rig pa'i rnam rtog shar/ /zhes gsang chen gyi bstan pa 'byung ba'i dus drug la bab tshe shan 'byed/ la bzla/ rang grol/ mngon sum du ston pa rtsol med a ti'i theg pa 'byung ba'i dus la babs pas/ sum cu rtsa gsum gyi lha de ba bzang skyong gi bu sems lhag can la rmis ltas khyad par can bzhi byung ba dang mthun par rdo rje sems dpas rgyal thabs spyi blugs kyi dbang bskur zhing man ngag byin pas lha'i gnas su dar/ de nas mi yul du dar tshul ni/ rgya gar nub phyogs o rgyan gyi rgyal po d+harma a sho ka'i sras mo pra ha ra Ni mtsho 'gram du khrus la zhugs tshe gsang bdag sprul pa'i ngang pa zhig gis sems lhag can yi ge  du bsdus te zhal du mid nas sras mo'i thugs kar mchu lan gsum gtugs nas hU~M 'od 'bar ba zhig thugs kar bstims pas/ zla dus rdzogs pa na sras mo'i thugs ka nas gser gyi rdo rje rtse dgu 'od 'bar ba zhig byung ste 'od du zhu ba las sras khye'u mtshan dpe dang phyag rgyas spras pa rdor sems nam mkha' che'i rgyud zhal 'don mdzad bzhin du byon pa de ni mi las 'das pa'i skyes mchog sprul sku dga' rab rdo rje ste/ slar yang rdor sems mngon du byon nas dbang bskur rdzogs pa chen po'i rgyud 'bum phrag drug cu rtsa bzhi'i mdzod rang dbang du thob ste bstan pa'i bdag por gyur to/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Of great perfection’s doctrine, it is said,
The thought of awareness dawns
When afflictive emotions are intense, when strength is weak,
When life span is short due to karma, when the canon’s meaning
is lost,
When evil tenets transform the doctrine’s essence,
And when meditation practice is weak due to ineffective antidotes.
When these six conditions for the doctrine of supreme mystery’s arising prevailed, the time had come for the effortless way of ati, which teaches discernment of differences, resolution, self-liberation, and manifest sight. Four special prophetic signs occurred in the dreams of Altruistic, son of Déva Excellent Protector, a god of Heaven of the Thirty-three. As the omens indicated, Buddha Vajrasattva conferred upon him the empowerment of the vase of complete coronation and bestowed pith instructions. [These teachings then] circulated in the gods’ realm.
How they then spread in the human world is as follows. Praharani, daughter of Dharma Ashoka, king of Oddiyana in western India, went to bathe at the bank of a lake. A swan, emanation of Lord of Secrets, gathered Altruistic into the form of a Hung syllable, which he swallowed. The swan touched its beak to the princess’ heart three times, then had the glowing Hung melt into her heart.
After the full number of months passed, a golden nine-spoked vajra ablaze with light emerged from the princess’ heart, melted into light, and became her son, a small child adorned with symbolic emblems and the marks and signs of physical perfection. When he appeared, he chanted The Vajrasattva Great Sky Tantra. That child, a sublime individual who surpassed human limits, was enlightenment’s manifestation, Garab Dorjé.
Later, Vajrasattva appeared and empowered him; he gained mastery over the treasury of great perfection’s six million, four hundred thousand tantras, and thus became the doctrine’s chief.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
'od du thim tshe 'jam dpal bshes gnyen sogs/ /rgyal tshab rnams la 'das rjes rim par babs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
When [Garab Dorjé] dissolved into light, Manjushrimitra received his testament.
Likewise, all the other regents successively received [a testament].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
mthar gdod ma'i zad sar 'od phung du thim pa'i tshe slob dpon chen po 'jam dpal bshes gnyen la 'das rjes stsal zhing*/ sogs khongs nas/ shrI sing ha/ dz+nyA na sU tra/ bi ma la ste rim par so so'i rgyal tshab tu dbang bskur ba'i 'das rjes rim par babs/ slob dpon chen po pad+mA ka ras kyang dngos su shrI siM ha bla mar bsten cing*/ dga' rab rdo rje'i ye shes kyi sku dang yang mjal nas gdos bcas 'od phung du grol ba'i tshul bstan nas 'pho ba chen po rdo rje'i skus 'khor ba ji srid du 'gro ba'i don mdzad cing da lta pad+ma 'od kyi gzhal med khang chen por dngos su 'tsho zhing gzhes la chos kyang ston pa yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Finally, when [Garab Dorjé] dissolved into a mass of light in the ground of primordial exhaustion [of phenomena], he bestowed his testament to the great master Manjushrimitra. Among the “other regents” [in the root text], Shri Singha, Jnanasutra, and Vimalamitra were each successively empowered as regent by receiving a testament [from his predecessor].
Great Master Padmakara relied on Shri Singha as his spiritual master and met Garab Dorjé’s wisdom body. Padmakara demonstrated the way of liberation of the material body into a mass of light, and his vajra body of supreme transference continues to aid beings for as long as the wheel of life lasts. At present, he lives in the magnificent celestial palace Lotus Light, where he expounds the teachings.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="b">
[b. yo ga phyi ma gnyis kyi lugs]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="b">
The Systems of the Two Other Yogas [b]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la gnyis/ rig 'dzin mi ma yin pa las brgyud pa dang*/ mi dang mi ma yin pa gnyis ka las brgyud pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the transmission among nonhuman awareness holders and (2) the transmission among both human and nonhuman beings.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="i">
dang po [i. rig 'dzin mi ma yin pa las brgyud pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="i">
The Transmission among Nonhuman Awareness Holders [i]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rig gsum mkhyen brtse nus pa'i mnga' bdag gis/ /lta ba sgrub pa spyod phyogs gtso bor bshad/ /
lha klu gnod sbyin tshom bu 'bum sde grol/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
[The lords of] the three kinds of beings, masters of knowledge, compassion, and power,
Chiefly taught the view and conduct of meditation practice:
Gods, nagas, and noxious spirits in groups of hundred thousands attained liberation.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rgyal sras sems dpa'i 'khor rgya mtsho tsam gyi nang nas ston pa nyid kyi sprul pa rigs gsum mgon po mkhyen rab kyi mnga' bdag 'phags pa 'jam dpal/ thugs rje'i mnga' bdag spyan ras gzigs/ mthu stobs nus pa'i mnga' bdag phyag na rdo rje gsum gyis/ rim bzhin lha dang klu dang mi rnams kyi gnas su lha grags ldan mchog skyong*/ klu rgyal mgrin pa nag po/ gnod sbyin kun tu bzang po rnams la lta ba dang sgrub pa spyod pa'i phyogs gtso bor smos pa'i tshul gyis bshad pas so so'i gnas su rim par brgyud de dar zhing lha dang klu dang gnod sbyin tshom bu 'bum sde dang bcas pa grol zhing*/ de dag kyang byang chub sems dpa'i tshul 'dzin cing sangs rgyas kyi gdung gsob par gyur to/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Among ocean-like circles of bodhisattvas, the Victor’s spiritual heirs, the lords of the three kinds [of beings] are the teacher’s own emanations: the master of knowledge, exalted Gentle Splendor; the master of compassion, All-Seeing One; and the master of power, strength, and ability, Vajra Holder. Respectively, they taught in the abodes of gods, nagas, and human beings—[principally to] the god Renowned Eminent Protector, the naga king Black Neck, and the noxious spirit Ever Excellent—emphasizing the view and conduct of meditation practice. Thus, the teachings were gradually transmitted and spread in their worlds. [The three disciples] attained liberation, together with groups of hundred thousands of gods, nagas, and noxious spirits. Moreover, they took the forms of bodhisattvas and became the Buddha’s successors.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="ii">
gnyis pa [ii. mi dang mi ma yin pa gnyis ka las brgyud pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="ii">
The Transmission Among Both Human and Nonhuman Beings [ii]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rgyal ba 'das nas nyi shu rtsa brgyad lor/ /ma la ya rtser rigs can dra ma lngas/ /
gdung tshig nyer gsum bton pas gsang ba'i bdag_/mngon sum byon nas gsang rgyud zlos te bstan/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
Twenty-eight years after the Victor transcended [sorrow],
Five lineage-holding nobles at Mount Malaya’s summit
Uttered twenty-three verses of lamentation:
Lord of Secrets manifestly appeared; he recited and taught the secret tantras.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rgyal ba shAkya'i dbang po mya ngan las 'das pa'i tshul bstan nas bgrang bya nyi shu rtsa brgyad kyi lo grangs brgal ba'i tshe/ dam pa'i rigs can dra ma lnga nang du yang dag 'jog las langs pa na 'jig rten gyi sgron me nub par shes te/ ri ma la ya gnam lcags yod pa'i rtser rdzu 'phrul gyis 'dus nas rigs can dra ma lnga pos phyogs bcu'i sangs rgyas yid la byas te/ kye ma kye hud kye ma blong*/ /ston pa sgron me'i 'od nub na/ /'jig rten mun pa gang gis sel/ /zhes sogs gdung tshig nyi shu rtsa gsum bton pas/ rgyal ba rnams kyis gsang ba'i bdag po bskul te don du khyab bdag rigs drug pa nyid gsang ba'i bdag po'i rnam par mngon sum du byon nas/ sngon 'og min dang*/ dga' ldan dang*/ sum cu rtsa gsum ste lha gnas gsum du bstan cing grags pa'i gsang ba'i rgyud thams cad zlos te bstan par mdzad do/ /de la dam pa'i rigs can dra ma lnga ni/ lha grags ldan mchog skyong*/ klu rgyal 'jog po/ gnod sbyin skar mda' gdong*/ srin po blo gros thabs ldan/ mi lits+tsha bI dri ma med par grags pa rnams so/ /gdung tshig nyer gsum ni spyi mdo dgongs 'dus kyi le'u gsum pa las 'byung ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Twenty-eight years after the Victorious Lord of the Shakyas demonstrated the process of transcendence of sorrow, five nobles who held the sacred lineage rose from perfect contemplation and knew that the Light of the World had set. The five nobles gathered miraculously at Mount Malaya’s meteorite summit, directed their minds toward the buddhas of the ten directions, and uttered twenty-three verses of lamentation such as these:
Alas, alas! What immense sadness!
Once the lamp light of our teacher has waned,
Who will dispel the world’s darkness?
The victors therefore summoned Lord of Secrets; in fact, the lord who pervades the six wisdom families [Buddha Vajra Bearer] manifestly appeared in the form of Lord of Secrets. He repeated and taught all the secret tantras that had been previously divulged and proclaimed throughout three heavens—Unsurpassed, Joyful, and Heaven of the Thirty-three.
Here, “the five nobles who held the sacred lineage” refers to the god Renowned Eminent Protector, the naga king Takshaka, the noxious spirit Shooting Star Face, the ogre Skillful Intelligence, and the human Vimalakirti of the Licchavi clan. Their twenty-three verses of lamentation can be found in the third chapter of The General Discourse That Gathers Wisdom’s Realization.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
de dag srin po blo gros thabs ldan gyis/ /yi ger bkod nas mkha' la rtsal gyis sbas/ /
de ni rig 'dzin brda yi brgyud pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The ogre Skillful Intelligence
Recorded [the teachings] and concealed them in the sky with the energy [of perfect intent].
The transmission among awareness holders passed through symbols [occurred in this way].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de ltar gsang bdag gis gsungs pa'i theg pa mtha' dag srin po blo gros thabs ldan gyis gser gyi glegs bam la baiDUr+Ya zhun mas yi ger bris nas nam mkha' la dgongs pa'i rtsal bdun gyis sbas so/ /de la dgongs pa'i rtsal bdun ni/ gser gyi byang bu bri gzhi phun sum tshogs par dgongs pa/ baiDUr+Ya zhun mas bris pa rgyud phun sum tshogs par dgongs pa/ rin po che sna tshogs pa'i sgrom bu snod ngo mtshar ba'i dgongs pa/ nam mkha' 'byung bzhis mi 'jig pas gter gnas dam par dgongs pa/ ma dang mkha' 'gro rnams ye shes kyi spyan dang ldan pas gter srung khyad par can du dgongs pa/ chos bdag rgyal po dzaHlas can dbang po yang rab rtogs grol dus mnyam du dgongs pa/ skye 'phags byang sems sa la gnas pa sogs grub brnyes brgyud 'dzin dar rgyas su 'byung ba la dgongs pa rnams so/ /de dag ni chos don ma lus pa brda tsam gyis khong du chud pas rig 'dzin brda'i brgyud pa zhes bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
As described, the ogre Skillful Intelligence recorded every way of spiritual development spoken by Lord of Secrets in liquid lapis on folios of gold, and concealed them in the sky with the energy of his sevenfold perfect intent.
The sevenfold perfect intent is as follows: Folios of gold were intended as the perfect basis for the writing. Liquid lapis was intended as the perfect ink. Treasure chests of various types of precious substances were intended as wondrous vessels. The sky was intended as the sublime location for the treasure, since the four elements never destroy it. Since mamos and dakinis possess wisdom eyes, they were intended as special guardians of the treasure. The custodian of the teachings, King Ja, was intended as the destined being of the very highest degree of acumen whose realization and liberation were simultaneous. Exalted beings, such as bodhisattvas who dwelled upon awakening’s stages, were intended to serve as accomplished lineage holders, to make [the teachings] spread and flourish.
In all these cases, since the doctrine’s every meaning was comprehended merely through symbolic indications, this transmission is known as “the transmission among awareness holders passed through symbols.”
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="3">
gsum pa [3] gang zag snyan brgyud ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="3">
Human Individuals’ Lineage Transmitted through Hearing [3]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
de tshe de yi byin rlabs snang ba las/ /rgyal po dzaHla rmis ltas bdun shar te/ /
phyag rdor sku dang tan+t+ra sde bco brgyad/ /yang thog babs shing rim par don rtogs nas/ /
ku ku rA dza sogs las brgyud de dar/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
At that time, seven signs appeared in King Ja’s dreams
As the manifestation of the blessings [of Lord of Secrets’ teaching].
[He found] a statue of Vajra Holder and the eighteen sections of tantra
Descended upon the roof of his palace. He gradually realized their meaning,
Then transmitted them to Kukuraja. [The transmission] continued and the teachings flourished.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang sdom 'byung gi rgyud phyi ma las/ nga ni 'di nas mi snang nas/ /lo ni brgya dang bcu gnyis na/ /lha gnas gsum du grags pa yi/ /bstan pa'i snying po dam pa zhig_/'dzam gling shar gyi phyogs mtshams kyi/ /rgyal po dzaHzhes grags pa la/ /bsod nams chen po'i mthus snang ba'i/ /gsang ba'i bdag pos snang bar 'gyur/ /zhes gsungs pa dang mthun par/ gsang ba'i bdag pos rigs can dra ma lnga la chos bstan pa de'i tshe de'i byin rlabs kyi snang ba las sa ho ra'i rgyal po dzaHla rmis ltas ngo mtshar ba bdun rmis te/ ji skad du/ sku gsung thugs rtags thim pa dang*/ /rin chen gleng bam babs pa dang*/ /chos kyi bgro ba byas pa dang*/ /kun gyis dam par bsgrags pa dang*/ /mchod pa chen po byas pa dang*/ /rin chen char du babs pa dang*/ /sangs rgyas sa la lung bstan pa'o/ /zhes pa'i rmis ltas dang mthun par thog mar phyag rdor gyi sku khru gang pa rnyed/ de la brten te sgrub pa zla ba bdun mdzad pas khang pa'i yang thog tu tan+t+ra chen po sde bco brgyad kyi glegs bam rnams dngos su babs/ rdo rje sems dpa' zhal mthong gi le'u brda mjal te bsgrubs pas rdo rje sems dpa'i zhal mjal zhing byin gyis brlabs/ bskyed rim gyis phung po sbyangs pas gsang ba'i bdag pos zhal bstan cing dbang bskur rgyud bshad pas don rtogs nas rim par slob dpon ku ku rA dza/ in+d+ra bo d+hi/ siM ha rA dza sogs la brgyud de dar ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Latter Tantra of Binder of the Wheel states:
A hundred and twelve years After I cease to appear here, The doctrine’s sublime essence Renowned throughout the three heavens Will appear to one known as King Ja At the Land of Jambu’s eastern border. Through the power of his tremendous merit, Lord of Secrets will make it appear.
As written, when Lord of Secrets taught the doctrine to the five lineage-holding nobles, his blessings’ illumination produced seven wondrous omens in King Ja of Sahor’s dreams. As is said,
The insignia of wisdom body, speech, and mind dissolved
into him, Precious volumes descended, He discussed the doctrine, Everyone proclaimed him to be an exalted being, He presented vast offerings, A rain of precious gems fell, And his reaching the ground of enlightenment was foretold.
Consistent with these dream omens, he first acquired a statue of Vajra Holder, one cubit [in height]. He used it to practice meditation [on Vajra Holder] for seven months: the volumes of the eighteen tantras actually fell upon the uppermost roof of his palace. He read the chapter on seeing Buddha Vajrasattva’s face; by practicing it, he saw Vajrasattva and received his blessing. Once he had purified his aggregates with the creation phase of meditation, Lord of Secrets appeared to him, bestowed empowerments, and taught the tantras. He realized their meaning, then imparted the transmission to Kukuraja, [from whom it passed] in turn to Indrabodhi, Singharaja, and others. [In this way, the teachings] spread.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
de dang dus mtshungs phyi rgyud sde gsum ni/ /wa ra NA si bya rkang me ri 'bar/ /
a nu sing+ga gling gi nags tshal du/ /glegs bam dngos su babs shing a ti yang*/ /
d+ha na ko Shar dga' rab rdo rje la/ /rdo rje sems dpas gsungs te yi ger bkod/ /
gzhan dang gzhan nas byung ba ches mang ngo*/ /de dag gang zag snyan khung brgyud pa ste/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
At the same time, the three classes of exoteric tantra
Descended to Varanasi, Bird-Foot Mountain, and Blazing Mountain.
Anuyoga’s volumes
Descended to Singha Island’s forest.
Vajrasattva taught atiyoga at Lake Dhanakosha
To Garab Dorjé, who wrote it down.
Tantras appeared from a great variety of other sources.
These teachings are called the transmission among individual masters through hearing.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag dang dus mtshungs par phyi rgyud sde gsum sogs gnas so sor rim par babs te/ kri ya'i rgyud rnams wa ra nA si dang*/ u pa ya'i rgyud rnams ri bo bya rkang can dang bsil ba'i tshal du babs/ yo ga'i rgyud rnams dur khrod me ri 'bar ba'i rtser babs/ a nu yo ga'i rgyud rnams lang+ka'i yul du grags pa sing+ga la'i gling du glegs bam dang bcas te dngos su babs/ lugs 'di'i bshad srol du a ti yo ga'i rgyud rnams kyang nub phyogs o DI ya na'i bye brag d+ha na ko Shar slob dpon chen po dga' rab rdo rje la rdo rje sems dpas dngos su gsungs shing yi ger bkod par mdzad do zhes 'byung ngo*/ /grub pa'i slob dpon rnams la lhag pa'i lhas stsal ba sogs gzhan dang gzhan dag nas byung ba'i ches mang bas gsang sngags kyi rgyud sde la mtha' yod pa ma yin no/ /de dag ni gang zag gcig nas gcig tu tshig gi sgra la brten te rna bar brgyud pas gang zag snyan khung brgyud pa zhes bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
At the same time, teachings including the three exoteric tantras gradually descended to separate places: kriya tantras in Varanasi, upa tantras on Bird-Foot Mountain and in Cool Grove, and yoga tantras at the summit of Blazing Mountain of Fire charnel ground. Anuyoga tantras, along with their volumes, actually descended upon Singhala Island, known as the region of [Sri] Lanka.
According to this system’s explanation, at Lake Dhanakosha, a specific area of Oddiyana in western India, Vajrasattva overtly taught atiyoga tantras to the great master Garab Dorjé, who wrote them down. So [this system] relates.
Tantras appeared from a great variety of other sources, such as exalted deities who granted them to accomplished masters. Secret mantra’s tantras have no limit. These teachings depended on the sounds of words which were transmitted from one individual to another. Because these teachings were received through the process of hearing, this [transmission] is called “the transmission among individual masters through hearing.”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
rtogs 'dul dbang gis theg pa ji snyed pa/ /rang bzhin rdzogs pa che las 'phros pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
To subdue thoughts, as many approaches to ways of spiritual development as there are
Issue from natural great perfection.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de ltar 'gro ba mtha' yas pa'i rnam par rtog pa mtha' yas pa 'dul ba'i dbang gis chos kyi 'khor lo dang theg pa'i sgo mo ji snyed par snang ba de dag thams cad rang bzhin rdzogs pa chen po'i bstan pa byin rlabs las 'phros pa ste/ dpal gsang ba'i snying po las/ sku dang gsung dang thugs kyi rgyud/ /phyogs bcu kun tu rab grags pa/ /gsang ba'i snying po las 'phros te/ /zhes gsungs pa bzhin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
As many wheels of Dharma and approaches to ways of spiritual development as there are appear in order to subdue infinite beings’ boundless thoughts. All such teachings issue from the blessings of natural great perfection’s doctrine. The Secret Essence Tantra states:
Tantras of wisdom body, speech, and mind Resound throughout the ten directions; They issue from The Secret Essence Tantra.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="II">
gnyis pa [II] sgrub sde'i bab lugs bye brag tu bshad pa ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="II">
The Transmission of the Means of Attainment [II]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
</d>
<d e="2">
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="3">
sgrub sde zhi khros gsungs shing gsang bdag bsdus/ /mkha' 'gror gnyer gtad mchod rten bum par sbas/ /
slob dpon brgyad kyis dgung bdun dgongs pa'i tshe/ /las kyi dbang mos sgrom bu so sor gtad/ /
kun 'dus bka' babs slob dpon chen po'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="3">
The peaceful and wrathful deities taught the means of attainment; Lord of Secrets compiled them.
He entrusted them to the dakini, who concealed them in a stupa’s vase.
When eight masters meditated for seven nights,
Dakini Sovereign of Activity entrusted each with a treasure chest.
The designated inheritor of the convergence of them all is the magnificent master.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sgrub pa'i sde rnams ni/ gnas 'og min gsang ba mchog gi dkyil 'khor chos 'byung dbyings kyi zhing me ri 'bar bar/ ston pa dpal chen kun bzang rdo rje sems dpa' zhi ba dang*/ rang byung che mchog he ru ka khro bo'i dkyil 'khor du bzhengs nas 'khor rang rig gi tshom bur snang ba rnams la/ dus thog mtha' med pa mnyam pa nyid kyi ngang du chos nyid rdo rje'i rang sgras rdo rje theg pa spyi dang*/ bye brag tu bde gshegs 'dus pa'i spyi rgyud lnga/ sgos rgyud bcu/ yan lag so so'i sgrub lugs dpag tu med pa la sogs par gsungs pa'i rgyud rnams/ gsang bdag rdo rje chos kyis rang nyid tshom bu dgu'i dkyil 'khor gyi nang du snang bar mdzad nas thog mar ngag tu bsdus/ de nas glegs bam la bkod de dgongs 'grel du lung lnga yang mdzad nas mkha' 'gro ma las kyi dbang mo che la gtad/ des spyi dang bye brag gi rgyud rnams phyes nas rin po che'i sgrom so sor bcug ste mchod rten bde byed brtsegs pa'i bum pa gtso bor gyur pa'i gnas rnams su sbas pa/ nam zhig gi tshe dpal he ru ka'i thugs ye shes dgu'i rang mdangs las shar ba rang byung grub pa brnyes pa'i rig 'dzin chen po rnam pa dgu las pad+ma saM b+ha ba ma gtogs pa'i slob dpon brgyad kyis dus la babs par mkhyen te rdzu 'phrul gyis 'dus nas dgung zhag bdun du dgongs pa la bzhugs pa'i tshe/ mkha' 'gro ma las kyi dbang mo ches/ 'jam dpal bshes gnyen la lcags kyi sgrom bu sogs rig 'dzin brgyad la sgrom bu rnams so sor gtad cing 'jam dpal gshin rje'i gshed la sogs pa so so'i bka' babs/ sgrub pa'i tshul mdzad pas sgrub sde so so la mkhas shing dngos grub brnyes te rigs kyi gtso bo rnams dang mi gnyis pa'i go 'phang thob/
</d>
<d e="2">
The transmission of the means of attainment is as follows: In the sacred place Unsurpassed Realm, the sacred circle of sublime mysteries, a source of phenomena, the pure land of the basic space of phenomena, Blazing Mountain of Fire, the teacher arose as the peaceful sacred circle of glorious Buddha Ever Excellent Vajrasattva and as the wrathful sacred circle of self-occurring Great Supreme Héruka. To his circle of disciples, his own awareness appearing as a group [of wisdom deities] within the continual state of evenness of time without beginning or end, [he taught] with the nature of reality’s indestructible self-appearing sound. He taught the vajra way in general, and specifically The Gathering of Joyful Buddhas’ five general tantras, ten specific tantras, and infinite ways to practice each aspect [of the tantras], etc.
Lord of Secrets Vajra Dharma illuminated these tantras within his own nine-deity sacred circle, and first compiled them verbally. Then he wrote them in volumes and composed five scriptures as commentaries. He entrusted these texts to the supreme Dakini Sovereign of Activity. She separated the general and specific tantras, placed them in individual treasure chests of precious substances, and concealed them in various places, principally the vase of Bliss-Giving Pinnacle Stupa.
At some time, the natural radiance of the nine wisdoms of glorious Héruka’s enlightened mind manifested as nine supreme awareness holders who gained self-occurring accomplishment. Eight (all except Padmasambhava) knew that the time had come: they convened miraculously and dwelled in meditation for seven nights. At that time, the supreme Dakini Sovereign of Activity entrusted each of these eight awareness holders with a treasure chest (such as Manjushrimitra with an iron treasure chest), and she bestowed a transmission to each of them (such as that of Gentle Splendor, Slayer of the Lord of Death [to Manjushrimitra]). In applying themselves to meditation practice, each became proficient in their respective means of attainment. They attained accomplishment and achieved the state of indivisibility from the chief buddha of their respective wisdom family.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag la gsung rdo rje pad+ma ka ras so sor zhu ba'i tshul bstan cing sgrub pa mdzad pas slob dpon so so las kyang mkhas shing grub pa'i go 'phang mthon por gshegs pa na/ mkha' 'gro mas bskul te mchod rten bde byed brtsegs pa nas sngar rgya ma khrol ba'i spyi rgyud kyi sgrom bu rin po che sna brgyad las byas pa sogs rgyud lung man ngag yongs rdzogs spyan drangs pas kun 'dus bka' bab yongs su rdzogs pa ni slob dpon chen po nyid la 'dus shing gsang sngags kyi ston pa chen por gyur te dus gsum du 'gro ba'i don mdzad pa ni nam mkha' dang mnyam pa'o/ /snga 'gyur rnying ma'i bab lugs bshad pa skabs bzhi pa'i 'grel pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The vajra of wisdom speech, Padmakara, demonstrated the process of requesting the teachings from each of these masters; in meditation practice, he reached a state of knowledge and accomplishment superior to each of them. At that point, urged by the dakini, he retrieved from the Bliss-Giving Pinnacle Stupa all the still-sealed tantras, scriptures, and pith instructions, such as treasure chests of eight precious substances containing the general tantras. Thus, the complete transmission, convergence of them all, was gathered in this supreme master, who became the foremost teacher of secret mantra. Throughout past, present, and future, his acts to aid beings equal the sky’s breadth.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="">
theg pa'i sgo kun las btus pa gsung rab rin po che'i mdzod bslab pa gsum legs par ston pa'i bstan bcos shes bya kun khyab ces bya ba las bstan pa dam pa'i chos kyi rim par phye ba ste gnas gsum pa'i rnam par bshad pa grub bo// //
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="">
* * *
</d>
</f>
</b>
</book>
