<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<book xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../books.xsd">
<editions ul="The Treasury of Knowledge" checked="true">
<edition id="1" lang="tib-wylie" title="shes bya kun khyab ces bya ba las 'dul byed ston pa byon tshul" author="karma ngag dbang yon tan rgya mtsho"/>
<edition id="2" lang="en" title="The Treasury of Knowledge. Book Two. The Light of the World" author="Jamgön Kongtrul Lodrö Tayé" translator="Kalu Rinpoché translation group"/>
</editions>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="gnas gnyis pa">
['dul byed kyi ston pa ji ltar 'byon pa'i rim par phye ba ste gnas gnyis pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Book Two">
The Treasury of Knowledge
Book Two
The Light of the World
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
@#/ /de ltar gdul zhing snod bcud kyi 'jig rten de'i rgyu dang bcas pa legs par bshad nas/ de nyid 'dul byed kyi ston pa ji ltar 'byon pa'i rim par phye ba ste gnas gnyis pa la skabs bzhi/ bdag cag gi ston pa byang chub lam du ji ltar gshegs pa'i tshul/ sangs rgyas pa'i tshul theg pa so so'i bzhed pa/ sprul pa'i skus zhing 'dir mdzad pa bcu gnyis bstan pa'i tshul/ 'od gsal rdo rje rtse mo'i lugs kyi sku dang zhing khams khyad par du dbye ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
I have thoroughly presented [in The Treasury of Knowledge: Book One: Myriad Worlds] the realms the buddhas guide—world-systems of environments and inhabitants, vessels and contents, along with their causes.
Book Two, how the teacher who guides our realm appears within it, has four chapters:
(1) how our teacher traversed the path to awakening,
(2) the Buddha’s enlightenment according to the perspective of each Buddhist way,
(3) the twelve deeds the Buddha’s manifest body demonstrated in this realm, and
(4) enlightenment’s bodies and pure realms according to the clear light vajra pinnacle system.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="skabs dang po">
[1: bdag cag gi ston pa byang chub lam du ji ltar gshegs pa'i tshul]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Chapter 1">
1: Our Teacher’s Path to Awakening
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la lnga/
sangs rgyas spyi las bdag cag gi ston pa khyad par du phye ba/
de'i rnam thar sdoms su bstan pa/
dang po thugs bskyed pa'i tshul/
bar du byang chub spyod pa spyad tshul/
zhar byung dbang po'i rim pa bstan pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This chapter has five parts: (1) distinguishing our teacher from buddhas in general, (2) a concise presentation of the story of the Buddha’s liberation, (3) how the Buddha initially developed the aspiration to attain awakening, (4) how the Buddha performed a bodhisattva’s conduct until his enlightenment, and (5) a supplementary explanation of bodhisattvas’ levels of capability.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
dang po [I. sangs rgyas spyi las bdag cag gi ston pa khyad par du phye ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
Distinguishing Our Teacher from Buddhas in General [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
'jig rten 'dren pa'i rgyal ba dpag med las/ /bskal bzang 'dir 'byung sangs rgyas stong gi dbus/ /
pad dkar ltar bsngags mnyam med shAkya'i rgyal/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Among infinite numbers of victors, guides of this world,
In the midst of this Fortunate Age’s thousand buddhas,
One was praised as like a white lotus: the incomparable King of the Shakyas.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
ji srid nam mkha'i khams ma zad pa de srid du gdul bya'i khams mi zad la/ de srid sangs rgyas rnams kyi thugs rje dang smon lam phrin las zad pa mi mnga' bas phyogs bcu'i 'jig rten gyi khams tshad med pa rnams su kha lo sgyur ba'i 'dren pa mi mchog rgyal ba zhes bya ba'i mtshan gyis brjid pa'i de bzhin gshegs pa mi'i zla ba dang rin chen snying po la sogs pa brjod kyis mi long ba sngon du byon cing*/ da ltar mngon par dga' ba'i 'jig rten na mi 'khrugs pa dang*/ bde ba can gyi 'jig rten na 'od dpag med dang*/ pad+mo'i dpal gyi 'jig rten na sangs rgyas dpal bzang po la sogs pa tshad med cing grangs med pa rnams 'tsho zhes la chos kyang ston par mdzad do/ /ma 'ongs pa na 'jig rten gyi khams rdul bral yang dag bsags zhes bya bar ngo mtshar ba'i de bzhin gshegs pa mgon po kun tu gzigs la sogs pa dpag gis mi long zhing bsam las 'das pa'i 'dren pa mi yi seng ge rim par 'byon par 'gyur ba yin la/ de ltar sangs rgyas byon pa'i bskal pa rnams ni sgron bskal dang*/ mi byon pa'i bskal pa rnams ni mun bskal zhes bya zhing mun bskal ni shin tu mang la sgron bskal dkon pa ste/ bskal pa bzang po 'di 'das pa'i 'og tu mun bskal bskal chen drug cu rtsa lnga 'das pa dang snyan pa chen po zhes bya ba'i sgron bskal la sangs rgyas khri byon/ de nas mun bskal brgyad khri 'das nas skar ma lta bu zhes bya ba'i sgron bskal la sangs rgyas brgyad khri 'byon/ de nas mun bskal sum brgya 'das nas yon tan bkod pa zhes bya ba'i sgron bskal la sangs rgyas brgyad khri bzhi stong 'byon par mdo sde bskal pa bzang po las gsungs pas mtshon/
</d>
<d e="2">
As long as the element of space exists, the realms of sentient beings to be guided to enlightenment will continue endlessly. During that time, enlightened beings’ compassion, aspirations, and activity will be inexhaustible. Therefore, in the ten directions’ measureless world-systems, those celebrated with the titles of “victor,” “leader who guides the way,” and “supreme human being,” such as Transcendent Buddha Moon of Humanity and Transcendent Buddha Jewel Heart, have appeared in the past in inexpressible numbers. At present, incalculable buddhas live and impart the teachings, such as Buddha Unshakable in the world-system Truly Joyous, Buddha Infinite Light in the world-system Blissful, and Buddha Splendid Excellence in the world-system Lotus Splendor. In the future, indeterminable numbers of inconceivable guides, lions of humanity, will appear in succession, such as wondrous Transcendent Buddha All-Seeing Lord in the world-system called Perfect Collection Without Particles.
Ages during which buddhas appear are called ages of illumination. Ages when none appear are called dark ages. Dark ages are very numerous; ages of illumination are rare. After this present Fortunate Age has passed, sixty-five great ages of darkness will elapse until an illuminated age called Great Fame, during which ten thousand buddhas will appear. Eighty thousand dark ages will ensue, after which eighty thousand buddhas will appear during an illuminated age called Star-like. Then, after three hundred dark ages have elapsed, eighty-four thousand buddhas will appear in an illuminated age called Array of Qualities. These details are presented in The Fortunate Age Discourse and serve here to illustrate this point.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gsung rab rnams las mtha' yas pa 'byung ba las/ bye brag pad+mo stong mthong gi bskal pa bzang po 'di la bar gyi sangs rgyas zhes bya ba grangs nges med pa kha cig kyang 'byon par bzhed la/ sangs rgyas stong 'byung ba'i grangs nges su mdzad pa ni theg pa che chung thun mong du grags pa dang*/ sngon byang chub kyi spyad pa spyod pa'i tshe thugs bskyed smon lam lhan cig tu tshogs pa rnams yin la/ de'ang theg dman pa dag 'jig rten 'di'i mar 'grib kyi tshe lo brgyad khri nas brgya'i bar la sangs rgyas byon te/ de las snga bar sems can rnams skyo shas chung zhing chos don du mi gnyer bas mi 'byon la brgya las phyi na'ang snyigs ma ha cang shas che bas mi 'byon zhing*/ yar 'phel la mi dge ba ngang gis spong ba dang dge ba'i stobs 'phel bas 'byon mi dgos zhes 'dod cing*/
</d>
<d e="2">
Some believe that among the infinite [buddhas] mentioned within the scriptures of the Buddha’s word, an undetermined number of so-called buddhas of the interval will appear during our specific Fortunate Age, which was heralded by the [gods’] sight of one thousand lotuses. Nevertheless, the fixed number of one thousand buddhas to appear is prevalent within the great and lesser ways in common. Further, in the past during the period when these thousand buddhas engaged in bodhisattvas’ conduct, they together formulated aspirations to reach awakening [as recounted later in this chapter].
Followers of the lesser way believe that buddhas appear as the human life span in this world declines from eighty thousand to one hundred years. Buddhas do not appear earlier because sentient beings, having few sorrows, do not strive in their spiritual lives. They do not appear after the life span is less than one hundred years since the world’s degeneration is by then far too advanced. When the life span again increases, buddhas need not appear because beings naturally spurn nonvirtuous acts and the strength of virtuous acts increases.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bskal pa 'di'i tshe lo bzhi khri'i dus su sangs rgyas stong gi thog ma 'khor ba 'jig_/sum khri la gser thub/ nyi khri la 'od srung*/ brgya pa la shAkya thub pa/ brgyad khri'i dus su byams pa 'byon pa sogs sangs rgyas re re'i yul dang rigs dang 'od dang yab dang yum dang sras dang rim gro pa dang shes rab can dang rdzu 'phrul can gyi mchog dang 'khor dang sku tshe dang bstan pa'i gnas tshad dang sku gdung ste don bcu gsum dang bcas mdo sde bskal bzang las zhib par bstan cing*/ kun gyi tha mar sangs rgyas de dag gi sku tshe phrin las gcig tu bsdams pa de bzhin gshegs pa mos pa'am snang mdzad ces bya ba'i 'jig rten 'dren pa 'byon par gsungs pa las/ de dag gi dbus na sangs rgyas kun gyis spangs pa'i rtsod dus kyi gdul bya bzung ba'i snying stobs la sus kyang 'gran zla med pas/ e ma byang chub sems dpa''di ni pad+ma dkar po lta bu'o zhes rgyal ba sras dang bcas pas bsngags shing ched du brjod pa ni bdag cag gi ston pa mnyam med shAkya'i rgyal po 'di nyid yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
During this present age, when the human life span was forty thousand years, the first of the thousand buddhas appeared—Destroyer of the Wheel of Life; when thirty thousand years, Golden Sage; when twenty thousand [years], Guardian of the Light; and when one hundred [years], Shakyamuni. [When the life span again reaches] eighty thousand years, Loving-Kindness will appear. Regarding such buddhas, The Fortunate Age Discourse describes thirteen features in detail: each buddha’s home region, caste, measure of physical radiance, father, mother, children, attendants, foremost disciple in terms of knowledge, foremost disciple in miracles, [number of] disciples, life span, doctrine’s duration, and relics. Further, it is said that a guide of this world known as Transcendent Buddha Devotion (or as Transcendent Buddha Illuminator) will appear as the last of the [thousand] buddhas and will embody the totality of all of their life spans and activities.
Among this age’s thousand buddhas is one who has the courage, unrivaled by any other, to accept disciples in this age of confl ict abandoned by all other buddhas. The victors and their spiritual heirs praised him, proclaiming, “How marvelous! This bodhisattva is like a white lotus.” This lauded our own teacher, the incomparable King of the Shakyas.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="II">
gnyis pa [II. de'i rnam thar sdoms su bstan pa]
ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="II">
A Concise Presentation of the Story of the Buddha’s Liberation [II]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
thog mar thugs bskyed bar du spyod pa spyad/ /tha mar mngon sangs rgyas te 'gro don mdzad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Initially, he developed the aspiration to awaken; subsequently, he performed bodhisattvas’ conduct.
Finally, [he demonstrated] manifest enlightenment and aided beings.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
ston pa thugs rje can 'di nyid don dam par thog ma med pa'i dus nas mngon par byang chub ste sangs rgyas dang byang chub sems dpa'i rnam par 'phrul pas 'gro ba'i don dus gsum du mdzad pa las/ rtsod pa'i dus kyi gdul bya rnams kyi don du thog mar byang chub mchog tu thugs bskyed/ bar du grangs med gsum la sogs par spyod pa spyad/ tha mar ma ga d+ha rdo rje'i gdan la mngon par rdzogs par 'tshang rgya ba'i tshul bstan te 'dul ba bzhi'i cho 'phrul chen pos 'gro ba'i don rgyun chad med par mdzad do/ /zhes bya ba 'di ni rnam par thar pa'i mdor bstan nam sdom tshig tu bzung bar bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Here is a concise presentation or synopsis of the story of the Buddha’s liberation:
Ultimately, our compassionate teacher has been manifestly awakened since time immemorial. He appeared throughout past, present, and future as various buddhas and bodhisattvas, acting for the welfare of beings. For the benefit of disciples in the age of conflict, he initially developed the supreme aspiration to attain awakening. Subsequently, he performed bodhisattvas’ conduct during three incalculable ages and other periods of time. Finally, he demonstrated manifest, complete enlightenment at Vajra Seat in Magadha, then unceasingly aided beings by performing the four great miracles to guide them.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="III">
[III. dang po thugs bskyed pa'i tshul]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="III">
How the Buddha Initially Developed the Aspiration to Attain Awakening [III]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gsum pa la gnyis/ theg dman pa'i lugs/ theg chen gyi lugs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) how the Buddha initially developed the aspiration to attain awakening according to the lesser way’s tradition and
(2) how the Buddha initially developed the aspiration to attain awakening according to the great way’s tradition.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
dang po [A. theg dman pa'i lugs] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
How the Buddha Initially Developed the Aspiration to Attain Awakening according to the Lesser Way’s Tradition [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
de yang theg dman ltar na 'od ldan rgyal/ /gsum la brten nas dang por thugs mchog bskyed/ /
de nas shAkya thub chen tshangs pa'i lha/ /mthong nas thugs bskyed grangs med dang po brtsam/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
According to the lesser way, King Luminous first developed the supreme aspiration to awaken for three reasons.
Later, [our teacher] developed the mind of awakening upon seeing the great buddhas Shakyamuni and God of the Pure.
[This marked] the beginning of the first incalculable age of his spiritual path.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang ston pa nyid kyis thugs bskyed pa'i tshul la theg dman nyan thos pa rnams kyi 'dod pa ltar na/ sngon 'das pa'i dus na ston pa 'di rgyal po 'od ldan du gyur pa'i tshe/ rgyu mtshan gsum la brten nas sbyin pa byin smon lam btab cing bla na med pa'i byang chub tu thugs mchog bskyed par gsungs te/ 'dul ba lung las kun dga' bos/ 'jig rten gtso bo rnam 'dren pa/ /thub pa khyed kyis byang chub thugs/ /thog mar gang du bskyed pa dag_/skal ldan chen pos bdag la gsung*/ /zhes sogs zhus pa na/ sangs rgyas 'dod chags bral thos shing*/ /glang po dregs pa'i shas chen dang*/ /'jig rten sdug bsngal gyur mthong nas/ /ngas ni byang chub sems bskyed do/ /zhes sogs bka' stsal par gsungs pas so/ /de nas ston pa 'di yangs pa'i grong khyer du rdza mkhan yangs pa'i 'od ces bya bar gyur pa'i tshe bcom ldan 'das shAkya thub pa zhes bya ba 'jig rten du byung ba de'i sku la mar dang til mar gyis byugs shing bur chu'i btung ba sogs gsol te/ bdag kyang rab tu sbyin pa 'di yis shAkya'i rigs skyes pa/ /yon tan rigs dang rus dag mnyam pa'i sangs rgyas nyid gyur cing*/ /bdag gis tshangs pa'i 'jig rten bar gyi nyam thag 'ching ba yi/ /pha rol zhi ba rgya chen 'jigs pa med par sgrol bar shog_/ces smon lam btab cing thugs bskyed/ yang gnas brtan pa rnams kyi 'dod pa/ stobs bcu dpal bshes gnyen gyis 'dus byas dang 'dus ma byas rnam par nges pa'i bstan bcos su bkod par/ bcom ldan 'das lhag pa'i lha zhes bya ba 'khor los sgyur ba mi'i bdag por gyur pas/ thog ma med pa'i 'khor ba ru sngon ma mthong ba sangs rgyas tshangs pa'i lha mthong bas rnam pa 'di lta bur bdag sangs rgyas nyid du gyur cig ces bsam pa tsam gyi mngon par 'dod do/ /zhes bshad de gang ltar rgyal ba de dag mthong nas thugs bskyed de grangs med gsum gyi dang po'i 'go brtsam par 'dod do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
How did our teacher develop the aspiration to awaken? According to the viewpoint of the lesser way’s pious attendants, in the past, during our teacher’s lifetime as King Luminous, he had three reasons to make off erings, formulate prayers of aspiration, and develop the supreme aspiration to achieve highest awakening. [This viewpoint is substantiated] by the following dialogue [recorded in] The Scripture on Monastic Discipline:
Ananda asked such questions as,
Principal guide of the world, Most fortunate one, Tell me how you, the sage, First developed the aspiration to awaken.
To this, [the Buddha] replied,
I heard that the buddhas are free from attachment, Witnessed the elephant’s overpowering arrogance, And saw the world’s suff ering, Then gave rise to the mind of awakening.
In a later life, when our teacher was a potter named Vast Light in the city of Vaishali, a transcendent conqueror called Shakyamuni appeared in this world. Anointing [that buddha’s] body with butter and sesame oil, and presenting sweet drinks and other offerings, he developed the mind of awakening and formulated this aspiration:
May my perfect offerings ensure my rebirth in the Shakya clan To become a buddha with qualities, class, and family lineage equal to yours. May I fearlessly liberate those bound by misery in this world, up to Heaven of the Pure, In vast transcendent peace.
Dasabala Shrimitra in his treatise Certainty about the Conditioned and the Unconditioned presents the elders’ viewpoint:
The Transcendent Conqueror was a wheel-monarch, lord of humanity, by the name of Exceptional God. Since time immemorial within the wheel of life, he had not seen [a buddha]. Upon seeing Buddha God of the Pure, he thought, “May I become an enlightened being like him!” That mere thought is believed to have produced [the aspiration to awaken].
In any case, [the lesser way] believes that [the Buddha first] gave rise to
the aspiration to awaken upon seeing those victors, and then began the
first of three incalculable ages of his spiritual path.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
gnyis pa [B. theg chen gyi lugs] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
How the Buddha Initially Developed the Aspiration to Attain Awakening according to the Great Way’s Tradition [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
theg chen lugs su bram ze rgya mtsho'i rdul/ /rang sras rgyal ba rin chen snying po la/ /
srog chags bye ba khrag khrig 'bum phrag 'bum/ /byang chub 'dzin du bcug mthar rang nyid kyis/ /
rtsod pa'i dus bzung smon lam lnga brgya btab/ /lung bstan thob cing gzhan yang dmyal me'i gyad/ /
don yod mthong la bskyed sogs du mar gsungs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The great way’s tradition includes many accounts,
Such as that of Brahmin Ocean Particles:
His son, the Victor Jewel Heart
Caused three trillion living beings to grasp the mind of awakening.
Finally, [the brahmin] made five hundred prayers of aspiration to care for the age of conflict, and he received a prophecy [of his enlightenment].
Other accounts include that [the future Buddha] engendered the mind of awakening
As a strong man in Fire Chariot Hell or in the presence of Buddha Sight of the Meaningful.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
theg pa chen po'i sde snod rnams las 'byung ba'i lugs su bshad na/ snying rje pad dkar las/ sngon byung ba bskal pa grangs med pa gad+gA'i bye ma snyed 'das pa na sangs rgyas kyi zhing 'dir bskal pa chen po 'dzin pa zhes bya ba zhig byung ste/ bskal pa chen po de la gling bzhi pa'i sangs rgyas kyi zhing 'dir gling bzhi pa'i 'khor los sgyur ba'i rgyal po rtsibs kyi mu khyud ces bya ba zhig byung ngo*/ /de'i mdun na 'don gyigtso bo bram ze rgya mtsho'i rdul zhes bya ba'i sras rgya mtsho'i snying po mngon pa sangs rgyas nas mtshan rin chen snying por gyur pa de/ rtsibs kyi mu khyud sras stong dang bcas pa'i 'byor pa bla na med pas mngon par mchod cing*/ mthar bram ze chen pos kyang de bzhin du mchod do/ /de nas dus gzhan zhig na bram ze des dzam+bu'i gling pa'i mi rnams bslab pa'i gzhi lnga dang byang chub kyi sems la bkod cing*/ rgyal po rtsibs kyi mu khyud dang mig mi 'dzum sogs sras stong dang bcas pa byang chub tu sems yang dag par bskyed du bcug go_/de nas de dag gis lo bdun du so so'i zhing gi yon tan dag bsams nas bcom ldan 'das kyi spyan sngar sems bskyed cing zhing bzung nas smon lam btab pas/ de bzhin gshegs pa rin chen snying po rtsibs kyi mu khyud ni bde ba can gyi zhing du tshe dpag med du 'tshang rgya bar lung bstan/ de bzhin du sras thu bo mig mi 'dzum ni spyan ras gzigs su ming btags nas tshe dpag med srod la mya ngan las 'das pa'i tho rangs su 'od zer kun 'phags dpal brtsegs rgyal por 'tshang rgya ba dang*/ gnyis pa ni mthu chen thob ste rab tu brtan pa nor bu brtsegs pa'i rgyal por/ gsum pa dbang po'i tshogs 'jam dpal te kun tu gzigs nas/ rgyal sras dgu pa sdig med ni mi 'khrugs pa ste mngon dga'i zhing du mi 'khrugs par 'gyur ba sogs stong tshang bar lung bstan to/ /de nas khams kyi rgyal phran dang rgya mtsho'i rdul gyi sras dang slob ma'i tshogs la sogs pa srog chags bye ba dung phyur mang po lung bstan cing*/ 'jig rten gyi khams mi mjed du bskal pa bzang po 'di nyid la/ skar ma skyong 'khor ba 'jig nas/ stobs chen shugs 'chang mos pa'i bar du lung bstan kyang
</d>
<d e="2">
The following presents the great way’s tradition derived from its own sources. The White Lotus of Compassion Discourse states:
Long ago, incalculable ages ago—as many as there are grains of sand in the Ganges—a great age called Holder occurred in this buddha realm. During that great age in this four-continent buddha realm, there lived a four-continent wheel-monarch called Spoke’s Rim. His principal priest, a brahmin called Ocean Particles, had a son called Ocean Heart who, having realized manifest enlightenment, was called Buddha Jewel Heart. King Spoke’s Rim, together with his thousand sons, offered him unequaled wealth. Afterward, the great Brahmin Ocean Particles made similar off erings.
Later on another occasion, Brahmin Ocean Particles placed all humans of the Land of Jambu [our continent] within the five basic precepts and the mind of awakening, and induced King Spoke’s Rim, together with his thousand sons, including Open Eyes, to develop the mind of true awakening. For seven years thereafter, they contemplated the qualities of their respective realms [of future activity], then formally developed the mind of awakening in the Transcendent Conqueror’s presence, accepted their [respective] realms, and formulated prayers of aspiration.
Subsequently, Transcendent Buddha Jewel Heart foretold that Spoke’s Rim would attain enlightenment as Boundless Life in the realm Blissful. Likewise, he foretold the enlightenment of all one thousand sons: To the eldest, Open Eyes, he gave the name All-Seeing One and foretold his enlightenment as King Radiant Noble Manifold Glory at dawn following the evening when Boundless Life transcends sorrow. He foretold the enlightenment of the second son, Attainment of Great Strength, as King Perfectly Stable Cluster of Jewels and that of the third son, Glorious Gentle Accumulation of Power, as All Seeing; and he foretold that the ninth prince, Sinless, being imperturbable, would attain enlightenment in the pure land Truly Joyful as Buddha Unshakable, and so on.
He then foretold the enlightenment of trillions of living beings, including the kingdom’s governors and Ocean Particles’ children and disciples. As well, he predicted who, during this excellent age, would become buddhas in our world-system, Endurance. [He predicted all thousand buddhas, from] Star Protector who would be [the first,] Buddha Destroyer of the Wheel of Life, to Strong Holder of Force [who would be the last,] Buddha Devotion.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
khyab 'jug rlung ma gtogs pa gzhan gyis rtsod pa'i dus spangs pas/ rang nyid kyis lhag par rtsod pa'i dus bzung nas smon lam bya bar brtsams pa na 'jig rten gyi khams rab tu g.yos shing ngo mtshar gyi snang ba du mas khyab par gyur cing*/ rang re snyigs ma lnga bdo ba'i 'gro ba rnams sgrol bar mdzad pa'i slad du snying stobs zla med pa'i shugs bskyed nas smon lam chen po lnga brgya btab bo/ /de'i tshe rgyal ba rin chen snying pos brtson 'grus sogs yon tan dpag tu med pa'i sgo nas bsngags pa cher mdzad cing phyogs bcu'i sangs rgyas dang byang chub sems dpa' rnams kyis kyang bsngags shing ched du brjod nas/ 'jig rten gyi khams mi mjed du bskal pa bzang po la skye dgu'i tshe lo brgya nyi shu thub pa'i tshe/ de bzhin gshegs pa shAkya thub pa zhes bya bar lung bstan par mdzad do/ /zhes byung ngo*/ /gzhan yang sangs rgyas kyi drin lan bsabs pa'i mdo las/ byang chub sems dpa' dga' ba'i rgyal pos/ bcom ldan 'das la thog mar sems gang du bskyed zhus pa la/ sngon gyi tshe me'i shing rta'i dmyal bar dmyal srung a wang sdod pa'i me'i shing rta 'dren mkhan gyi gyad du 'khrungs pa'i tshe/ nyid kyi grogs shig stobs chung bas shing rta 'dren mi nus pa na/ a wang gis lcags mdung rtse gsum pas bsnun cing*/ lcags thos brdegs nas khrag char phab bo/ /der snying rje mi bzod pa skyes pa'i rkyen gyis byang chub tu thugs bskyed nas/ a wang la snying rje'i sems cung zad skyed cig par gsol bas/ de khros te lcags kyi rtse gsum gnya' bar btsugs pas tshe 'phos te/ bskal pa brgyad kyi sdig byang nas dmyal ba'i gnas de las thar bar gyur pa'i tshul rgyas par 'byung ba dang*/
</d>
<d e="2">
All others, with the exception of Vishnu Wind, abandoned our age of conflict; therefore, Ocean Particles especially embraced this age of conflict. When he began to formulate his aspirations, the worldly realm shook strongly and was filled with many awesome appearances. To liberate us beings [living at the time of] the five degenerations’ proliferation, he developed the force of incomparable courage and made five hundred prodigious prayers of aspiration.
At that time, Victor Jewel Heart lauded his innumerable qualities, such as diligence. Buddhas and bodhisattvas of the ten directions also praised him and made proclamations. Having done so, they foretold that in this world-system Endurance, during the Fortunate Age when the human life span is one hundred and twenty years, [Ocean Particles] would become Transcendent Buddha Shakyamuni.
Returning the Buddha’s Kindness Discourse relates another account [of the Buddha’s initial development of the aspiration to attain awakening] in detail:
Bodhisattva King of Joy asked the Transcendent Conqueror,
“How did you first develop the aspiration to awaken?”
He replied, “In the past, I took birth in Fire Chariot Hell as a strong man, who pulled a chariot of fire upon which stood Avang, a custodian of hell. At that time, a companion of mine was weak and could not pull the chariot. Avang prodded him with an iron trident and struck him with an iron hammer, causing a torrent of blood. Upon seeing this, unbearable compassion arose within me, which inspired me to develop the mind of awakening. I begged Avang, ‘Be a little kind!’ That infuriated him; he pierced the nape of my neck with the iron trident, killing me. I was purified of eight ages of negative acts and freed from the hell realm.”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
phung po gsum pa'i mdo las/ ji ltar bcom ldan 'das de bzhin gshegs pa shAkya thub pa tshong dpon gyi bu mngon dgar gyur pa na/ bcom ldan 'das de bzhin gshegs pa mdzes chen la brten te/ dang por byang chub tu thugs bskyed pa de bzhin du zhes kyang gsungs pa dang*/ rgya cher rol par/ thog mar khyod kyis don yod mthong la sA la'i me tog gis ni mchod/ ces de bzhin gshegs pa mngon sum du mdzad nas thugs bskyed pa'i thog ma de bzhin gshegs pa don yod mthong gi drung du yin par yang gsungs so/ /de ltar thog mar thugs bskyed tshul theg pa che chung gi khyad par dang*/ theg chen nyid la'ang mdo rnams su mi 'dra ba du mar 'byung ba rnams ni gdul bya'i skabs bsam pa'i khyad par dang*/ smon 'jug don dam gyi thugs bskyed pa'i khyad par sogs dgongs gzhi mang pos tha dad du gsungs par mngon pas/ thugs bskyed kyi thog ma 'di kho na'o zhes phyogs gcig tu mngon par zhen cing go rim dkrigs char bsgrigs pa la ni snying po med do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Three Practices Discourse states:
Just as the Conqueror, Transcendent Buddha Shakyamuni, when the merchant’s son called Truly Joyous, first developed the mind of awakening by relying on the Conqueror Transcendent Buddha Great Beauty, likewise . . .
The Vast Enjoyment Discourse states:
At first you off ered a sala flower to Buddha Sight of the
Meaningful.
When the future Buddha met Transcendent Buddha Sight of the Mean
ingful, his initial development of the aspiration to awaken is said to have
been in that buddha’s presence. Thus, the lesser and great ways differ in regard to our teacher’s initial development of the mind of awakening, and even within the great way, the discourses present many different accounts. Evidently, these are taught with many differing underlying intents, such as suitability in relation to disciples’ specific times, circumstances, or mentalities; or in relation to different aspects of the mind of awakening—aspiration, application, or ultimate. Therefore, rigid adherence to a single viewpoint, as if to say, “This event alone marked the Buddha’s initial development of the mind of awakening,” while fitting them into a set chronological order, is pointless.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="IV">
[IV. bar du byang chub spyod pa spyad tshul]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="IV">
How the Buddha Performed a Bodhisattva’s Conduct until His Enlightenment [IV]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bzhi pa la'ang gnyis/ theg dman gyi lugs dang*/ theg chen gyi lugs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: how the Buddha performed a bodhisattva’s conduct until enlightenment according to (1) the lesser way’s tradition and (2) the great way’s tradition.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
dang po [A. theg dman gyi lugs] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
How the Buddha Performed a Bodhisattva’s Conduct until Enlightenment according to the Lesser Way’s Tradition [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
bye smras grangs med gsum gyis mthar phyin 'dod/ /de la 'dul mdzod 'jog mtshams 'dra min gnyis/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The materialist school asserts that he reached perfection over three incalculable [ages].
Concerning these ages, the collection on discipline and The Treasury of Observed Phenomena present two different delineations.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bar du byang chub kyi spyod pa spyad pa'i tshul ni/ 'dul ba lung las/
sangs rgyas shAkya thub pa nas/ /
'dren pa yul 'khor skyong gi bar/ /
de'i bar bdun khri lnga stong gi_/
sangs rgyas rnams ni ngas mchod do/ /
grangs med gcig gi gnas pa yis/ /
rgyal ba ngas ni mchod byas te/ /
zhes dang*/ sangs rgyas mar me mdzad nas ni/ /
dbang po'i rgyal mtshan thub pa'i bar/ /
bdun khri drug stong dag gi ni/ /
sangs rgyas rnams ni nga yis mchod/ /
grangs med gnyis po tshang bar ni/ /
zhes dang*/
sangs rgyas legs mdzad nas bzung ste/ /
sangs rgyas 'od srung bar dag tu/ /
bdun khri bdun stong nga yis mchod/ /
grangs med gsum po de la ni/ /
zhes gsungs pa dang*/ mdzod las/
rnam gzigs mar me rin chen gtsug_/
grangs med gsum gyi tha mar byung*/ /
dang po shAkya thub pa yin/ /
zhes bshad pa las/ bye brag tu smra ba rnams ston pas bskal pa grangs med gsum gyis lam bgrod par 'dod cing*/ 'di'i lugs kyi grangs med brtsam pa'i thog ma'ang*/ nyid kyis de bzhin gshegs pa la mngon sum du bsnyen cing thugs bskyed pa nas brtsam par gsal lo/ /
des na grangs med gsum la shAkya thub pa nas brtsams te sangs rgyas 'od srungs kyi bar du/ de bzhin gshegs pa 'bum phrag gnyis dang khri phrag gsum la bsnyen bkur mdzad de tshogs bsags pa yin cing*/ mdzod kyi lugs de ltar na shAka thub nas rin chen gtsug tor gyi bar gyis grangs med dang po/ de nas mar me mdzad kyi bar grangs med gnyis pa/ de nas rnam gzigs kyi bar gsum pa 'das shing*/
kun la thams cad snying rje yis/ /
sbyin par byas pas sbyin pa rdzogs/ /
chags bcas yan lag bcad kyang ni/ /
mi 'khrugs bzod dang tshul khrims kyi/ /
skar rgyal bstod pas brtson 'grus kyi/ /
zhes pas
</d>
<d e="2">
How did the Buddha carry out a bodhisattva’s conduct until his enlightenment? The scriptures on discipline state:
I made offerings
To seventy-five thousand buddhas
From Buddha Shakyamuni
Until the guide Protector of the Region.
Throughout an incalculable age
I venerated the victors.
Further,
For the entirety of a second incalculable age,
I made offerings
To seventy-six thousand buddhas
From Buddha Lamp Radiance
Until Sage Victory Banner of Power.
Further,
Throughout a third incalculable age,
I made offerings
To seventy-seven thousand buddhas
From Buddha Excellent Deeds
Until Buddha Guardian of the Light.
The Treasury of Observed Phenomena states:
[Buddhas] All Seeing, Lamp Radiance, and Jewel Crown
Each appeared at the end [of one of] three incalculable ages.
The first [buddha of the first incalculable age] was Shakyamuni.
Among the lesser way’s views, proponents of the materialist school believe that our teacher traversed the spiritual path during three incalculable ages. Their system clearly states that the incalculable ages begin with [the future Buddha’s] development of the mind of awakening while personally serving a transcendent buddha. His subsequent veneration during three incalculable ages of two hundred and thirty thousand transcendent buddhas, from Buddha Shakyamuni until Buddha Guardian of the Light, constitutes his gathering of the accumulations.
On the same subject, The Treasury of Observed Phenomena system asserts a literal account [of the Buddha’s path to enlightenment], including that the first incalculable age extends from [his veneration of] Shakyamuni to Jewel Crown; the second, from that point until [his veneration of] Lamp Radiance; and the third, from that point until All Seeing.
Motivated by universal compassion,
He gave gifts, thus completed generosity.
Although he still had attachment and they cut off his limbs,
He demonstrated unshakable patience and ethical conduct.
When praising Star Monarch, he demonstrated diligence.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'i tshe phar phyin dang po gsum rdzogs par mdzad de/ de nas phug cig tu de bzhin gshegs pa skar rgyal gzi brjid kyi dbyings su snyoms par zhugs pa mthong zhing*/ shin tu dad pas rkang pa ya gcig gis 'greng ba'i brtson 'grus kyis nyin zhag bdun du/ skyes bu khyu mchog khyod 'dra'i dge sbyong chen po gzhan dag lha yul sa la med/ /
'jig rten 'di na'ang yod pa ma yin rnam thos bu yi gnas na'ang yod ma yin/ /
lha yi pho brang gnas mchog dag na'ang yod min phyogs dang phyogs mtshams dag na'ang med/ /
ri dang nags su bcas pa'i sa steng rgyas par kun tu yul gcig ga la yod/ /
ces pa'i tshigs bcad kyis bstod pas brtson 'grus rdzogs shing tshogs bzlums nas bskal pa dgu bcu rtsa gcig tu mtshan bzang gi las bsgrubs te dga' ldan gyi gnas su de nyid kyi tshe tshad dang mtshungs par bzhugs pa sogs sgra ji bzhin par 'dod la/ de ltar 'dul mdzod kyi 'jog mtshams cung zad 'dra min gnyis su byung ba las/ mdzod lugs ni gzhi thams cad yod par smra ba las kha che bye smra'i 'dod pa dngos yin la/ lung las byung ba ni/ 'phags yul du sde pa rnams 'don tshul tha dad du yod pas sde pa gzhan gyi klog tshul zhig dang 'dres par mngon no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
During the events mentioned in this quote, he completed the first three transcendent perfections. Later, in a cave, he saw Transcendent Buddha Star Monarch who dwelled in the meditative absorption of brilliant basic space. In great faith, he diligently stood on one leg for seven days as he praised Buddha Star Monarch with these words:
Leader of beings, there is no mendicant like you in the lands of gods’ domains! In this world there is none, nor in the abode of Son of Renown! In the gods’ supreme citadels there is none, nor in any quadrant or direction! Where on the vastness of the earth’s surface with its mountains and forests [is there one like you]?
By having done this, he completed [the perfection of] diligence. He combined his accumulations, then over a period of ninety-one ages he accomplished the acts necessary [to produce a buddha’s] marks of physical perfection. He then lived in Joyful Heaven for a period comparable to the duration of a lifetime in that realm.
Thus, the collection on discipline and The Treasury of Observed Phenomena have produced two slightly different delineations [of the Buddha’s life as a bodhisattva]. Of the two, The Treasury of Observed Phenomena system represents the actual belief of the Kashmiri materialist school, derived from the substantialist order. What appears in the scriptures on monastic discipline is evidently mixed with the reading of another order, since such orders in the land of exalted beings maintained diff erent styles of recitation.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
gnas brtan pa rnams smon sems grangs med bdun/ /de nas grangs med dgu ru spyod pa spyad/ /
bzhi yis sgo gsum spyod la 'grub par mdzad/ /'bum gyis las phran rdzogs nas 'tshang rgyar 'dod/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The elders’ order asserts that for seven incalculable ages, the future Buddha fostered the mind of aspiration,
Then engaged in [a bodhisattva’s] conduct for nine incalculable ages.
For four ages he was diligent in physical, verbal, and mental conduct.
For one hundred thousand ages, he completed minor acts, then attained enlightenment.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rtsa ba'i sde pa bzhi las gnas brtan pa'i lugs ni sangs rgyas tshangs pa'i lha la thog mar thugs bskyed pa nas brtsams te bskal pa grangs med bdun du sangs rgyas chig 'bum lnga khri lnga stong mnyes par byas shing byang chub la smon pa tsam mdzad do/ /de nas bskal pa grangs med dgur sangs rgyas sum 'bum brgyad khri bdun stong mchod cing byang chub kyi spyod pa spyad/ sems dang ngag gis smon lam mdzad do/ /de nas grangs med bzhis sangs rgyas bcu gnyis mchod nas sgo gsum gyis byang chub kyi spyad pa la 'grus par mdzad cing*/ de nas bskal pa 'bum phrag gcig gis sangs rgyas bco lnga mnyes par byas te sgo gsum gyis byang chub spyod pa'i las phran thams cad rdzogs par mdzad nas sangs rgyas so zhes 'dod do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Among the [pious attendants’] four main orders, the elders’ system asserts that [the future Buddha] first developed the resolve to awaken in [the
presence of] Buddha God of the Pure, then he pleased one hundred and fifty-five thousand buddhas over seven incalculable ages, during which he merely aspired to attain awakening. Then, over nine incalculable ages, he venerated three hundred and eighty-seven thousand buddhas, and made prayers of aspiration both mentally and verbally. Then, over four incalculable ages, he venerated twelve buddhas and diligently engaged in a bodhisattva’s conduct in thought, word, and deed. Then, over one hundred thousand ages, he pleased fifteen buddhas, completed all the physical, verbal, and mental minor acts of a bodhisattva’s conduct, and attained enlightenment.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
phal chen sde pas bcu nas sum cu'i bar/ /grangs med ci rigs tshogs gsog dgos par bzhed/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The majority order asserts that it is necessary
To gather accumulations for a period of ten to thirty incalculable [ages].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
phal chen sde pas sangs rgyas rnams grangs med bcu yan sum cu man las gang yang rung ba zhig gis tshogs bsags dgos par 'dod kyang*/ ston pa 'di ci tsam gyis lam bgrod pa gsal ka yod pa'i gzhung ma mthong ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The majority order asserts that buddhas must cultivate accumulations for a period of ten to thirty incalculable ages. Nevertheless, I have not seen a major text that explicitly states that our teacher traversed the path for such a period.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
[B. theg chen gyi lugs]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
How the Buddha Performed a Bodhisattva’s Conduct until Enlightenment according to the Great Way’s Tradition [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la gsum/
grangs kyi rnam grangs dang de dag gi dgongs gzhi dang dgos pa bstan pa/ spyad pa spyod tshul dngos/ spyad bya'i chos bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: (1) a presentation of systems to calculate the duration of the spiritual path, their intent, and purposes; (2) the actual way [the Buddha] engaged in a [bodhisattva’s] conduct; and (3) an explanation of the practices in which [the Buddha] engaged.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
dang po [1. grangs kyi rnam grangs dang de dag gi dgongs gzhi dang dgos pa bstan pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
Systems to Calculate the Duration of the Spiritual Path, Their Intent, and Purposes [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
theg chen la yang gsum dang so gsum dang*/ /du mar bzhed rnams grangs gnas bgrang tshul dang*/ /
rtsom pa'i thog ma smon sems tshogs lam che/ /
dang po'i sa nas 'dzin sogs dgongs pa'i gzhi/ /
rnyed dka' bstan dang sgyid lug spong ba dang*/ /dus kyang bsam mi khyab bstan dgos pa'i dbang*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The great way presents many systems of calculation of time — Three, thirty-three, or many [ages of traveling the spiritual path];
And intents—[the ages are said to begin with] the development of the aspiration to attain awakening,
The great [stage of] the path of accumulation, or awakening’s first stage, etc.
These teachings’ purposes are to show difficulty, to avert indolence,
And to show time as inconceivable.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
theg pa chen po'i lugs la'ang mdo rgyud phal che ba zhig las grangs med gsum du tshogs bsags shing lam bgrod par gsungs te/ de'ang rje btsun ma pham pas/ sa ni dang po yin par 'dod/ /'di ni bskal pa dpag med kyis/ /zhes dang*/ grangs med gnyis ni rdzogs pa yis/ /sgom pa'i lam ni tshar phyin te/ /zhes sogs dang*/ de dang mthun par 'jigs med zhabs kyis/ de ltar bskal pa grangs med pa dang pos tshogs kyi sa nas brtsams nas sa dang po'i bar rdzogs par byed do/ /gnyis pas ni dri ma med pa la sogs pa drug go_/gsum pas ni mi g.yo ba'i sa nas brtsams te sangs rgyas kyi sa yi bar ro zhes mdo las so/ /zhes bshad do/ /tshigs le nyer gnyis par/ 'di na bcom ldan 'das bskal pa grangs med pa gsum mam bdun du bar chad med pa'i tshul gyis brtson pa zhes 'byung zhing*/ mdo rgya cher rol pa las kyang*/ bskal pa grangs med pa bdun du dge ba'i rtsa ba yang dag par bsgrubs pa/ zhes gsungs pa dang*/ a b+h+ya dang stobs bcu dpal bshes kyis/ 'di ltar byang chub sems dpa'i tshogs kyi kun tu rdzogs pa ni bskal pa grangs med gcig 'da' bar 'gyur ro/ /de'i rjes su mos pas spyod pa'i sa yongs su rdzogs par 'gyur ba ni bskal pa grangs med gnyis 'da'o/ /de'i rjes su sa dang po rab tu dga' ba nas bzung ste sa bcu pa chos kyi sprin gyis ji srid du so sor bskal pa grangs med gsum gyis rdzogs par byas te/ sangs rgyas kyi sa kun tu bzang po sgrub par byed par 'gyur ro/ /
de ltar bskal pa grangs med sum cu rtsa gsum gyis sangs rgyas nyid thob bo zhes zer ro zhes na yam tsam du bkod pa dang*/
</d>
<d e="2">
In the great way tradition, most discourses and tantras state that the Buddha spent three incalculable ages gathering the accumulations and traversing the path. On this subject, noble Ajita [i.e., Maitreya] states [in The Ornament of the Discourses]:
It is believed that this marked awakening’s first stage;
This, attained by an incalculable age . . .
Further,
On completion of the second incalculable age,
The path of meditation reached its conclusion.
Likewise, Venerable Abhayakaragupta states:
During the first incalculable age, he started at the stage of accumulation and completed awakening’s first stage. During the second, [he completed] six stages of awakening, including [the second, called] Stainless. During the third, he started from the [eighth] stage, Unwavering, and attained enlightenment. This is stated in the discourses.
The Twenty-two Verses states:
The Transcendent Conqueror exerted himself uninterruptedly for three or seven incalculable ages.
The Vast Enjoyment Discourse states:
Over the course of seven incalculable ages, I accomplished all true roots of virtue.
Abhayakaragupta and Dasabala Shrimitra present this approximation:
When the bodhisattvas’ path of accumulation is fully complete, one incalculable age will have elapsed. Following that, when the stage of devoted conduct is perfectly complete, two [more] incalculable ages will have passed. After that, each stage of awakening, from its first stage, Great Joy, up to its tenth stage, Cloud of Dharma, requires three incalculable ages to complete. Finally, the stage of enlightenment, Ever Excellent, is achieved.
Thus, enlightenment is attained after thirty-three incalculable ages, so it is said.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dkon mchog sprin gyi mdor/ de bzhin gshegs pa ni bskal pa grangs med pa du mas yang dag par bsgrubs pa yin te/ rigs kyi bu/ de bzhin gshegs pa ni dpag pa dang*/ bsam pa dang*/ brtag par mi nus so/ /zhes gsungs pa sogs bzhed pa mang po byung ba de dag gi kha cig grangs kyi gnas bgrang tshul tha dad pa la'ang dgongs pa ste/ byang sa las/ bskal chen re la lo zla zhag dus skad cig sogs grangs med pas grangs med du btags pa'i phyogs gcig dang*/ bskal chen nyid bgrang ba las 'das pa la grangs med du btags pa'i phyogs gcig ste rnam gzhag gnyis gsungs pa dang*/ 'phags pa gnas brtan pa dag gis/ grangs kyi gnas lnga bcu rtsa lnga la grangs med chung ngu/ de grangs gnas gcig tu brtsis pa'i lnga bcu rtsa lnga'i bar du bsgres pa grangs med chen por 'dod pa dang*/ mdzod gzhung 'grel dang mthun par a b+ha ya sogs mkhas pa mang pos grangs kyi gnas drug cu pa'i grangs med nyid bshad cing*/ rgya rol dang phal chen sogs las 'phags pa rnams kyi spyod yul du gyur pa'i grangs kyi rnam gzhag shin tu rgya chen po dag kyang bstan pas/ grangs kyi tshul 'di lta bu mang po dag la so sor dgongs te gsungs pa dang*/
</d>
<d e="2">
The Rare and Sublime Cloud Discourse states:
The state of a transcendent buddha is fully accomplished after many incalculable ages. Child of my spiritual family, you cannot measure, conceive of, or evaluate a transcendent buddha!
Among these and many other viewpoints, some differ with regard to systems of calculation. The Stages of Awakening presents two frameworks. One attributes “incalculable” to the incalculable years, months, days, moments of time, etc., of each great age; the other, to the great ages themselves that are beyond calculation. The exalted elders’ order believes that a number with fifty-five digits is a “small incalculable number.” Counting this as a single unit, and multiplying it to the fifty-fifth power is a “large incalculable number.” Many scholars, including Abhayakaragupta, teach in accord with The Treasury of Observed Phenomena’s main text and commentary that “incalculable” refers to a sixty digit number. Further, The Vast Enjoyment Discourse, The Flower Ornament Discourse, and other texts present very extensive frameworks for numbers that are the experiential domain [only] of exalted beings. Such a variety of systems of enumeration were taught in relation to specific considerations.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
grangs med rtsom pa'i thog ma'ang thog ma'i smon sems nas bgrang bar gsungs pa dang*/ theg bsdus las/ bzang dang smon pa'i stobs can dang*/ /sems brtan khyad par 'gro ba yi/ /byang chub sems dpa' grangs med gsum/ /kun tu rtsom par mdzad pa yin/ /zhes tshogs lam chen po nas rtsom par gsal zhing*/ dkon mchog sprin las/ don dam byang chub kyi sems ji lta ba bzhin thog mar mngon du gsal bar mdzad pa sa dang po thob pa nas bgrang bar gsungs pa sogs dgongs pa'i gzhi sna tshogs pa dang*/ skabs 'gar bsod nams dang ye shes kyi tshogs shin tu rgya chen po bstan pas sangs rgyas 'byung ba rnyed dka' ba'i phyir dus ring por gsungs pa dang*/ 'ga' zhig des sgyid lug par 'gyur zhing byang chub mchog la mi 'jug pa dag kyang yod pas de rnams gzhug pa'i phyir dus thung ngur gsungs pa dang*/ don dam par grangs dang bgrang ba sogs rang bzhin gyis dben zhing dus gcig la dus du ma mi 'gal ba dang*/ du ma la'ang gcig tu sdud pa sogs bsam gyis mi khyab pa'i de kho na nyid ston pa'i phyir yang ma nges par gsungs pa sogs dgos pa'i dbang du mas 'thad par grub pa'i phyir 'gal 'dur mi bzung ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Moreover, the incalculable ages’ starting point is designated on the basis of various underlying intentions and is said to be calculated from [the Buddha’s] initial aspiration to awaken. Further, A Compendium of the Great Way clearly states that the three incalculable ages begin with the great path of accumulation:
A bodhisattva imbued with the strength of goodness and aspiration
And whose mind is becoming markedly stable
Is one who has fully begun
The three incalculable ages.
The Rare and Sublime Cloud Discourse states that calculation of [the three incalculable ages] begins with attainment of awakening’s first stage—the first, manifest clear sight of the ultimate awakened mind as it is.
In some cases, the period spent [on the path to awakening] is said to be long; vast accumulations of merit and wisdom are taught to show how difficult it is for a buddha to appear. There are some who become indolent and do not enter [the path of] supreme awakening [when considering] such [a long period]; thus, to make them enter it, the period is said to be short. Further, the time can be unspecified, to demonstrate that ultimately, numbers and enumeration lack an intrinsic nature, and to present the inconceivable ultimate nature, such as that time’s multiplicity does not contradict its unity and that time’s multiplicity converges into one. [These presentations] are suitable due to many purposes; do not consider them contradictory.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
gnyis pa [2. spyad pa spyod tshul dngos] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
The Actual Way the Buddha Engaged in a Bodhisattva’s Conduct [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
yongs grags tshogs kyi lam nas
dang po'i bar/ /grangs med gcig dang gnyis pas sa drug bgrod/ /
gsum pas mi g.yo ba nas bcu gcig bar/ /so skye slob lam gyis bsdus tshogs gnyis bsgrubs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The most prevalent [view is that the period] from the path
of accumulation to awakening’s first stage required one
incalculable age.
During the second incalculable age, he traversed six stages;
During the third incalculable age, he traversed from
Unwavering to the eleventh.
Collectively, these represent the stages of ordinary individuals
and [exalted beings’] path of training; he thereby completed
the twofold accumulation.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de ltar grangs med dang byang chub spyod pa'i tshul rgya che chung ci rigs 'byung ba las/ yongs su grags pa'i dbang du byas na rgyal po'i bu gzhon nu brtson 'grus spyod du gyur cing sangs rgyas phung po chen po bsnyen bkur ba nas bzung ste bskal pa grangs med gcig tshogs bsags pas tshogs kyi lam nas sa dang po'i bar dang*/ de nas tshong dpon shes rab bzang du gyur cing sangs rgyas dkon mchog yan lag bsnyen bkur ba nas bzung ste grangs med gnyis pas sa gnyis pa nas bdun pa'i bar gyi sa drug bgrod/ de nas bram ze'i khye'uchos kyi sprin du gyur cing sangs rgyas mar me mdzad bsnyen bkur ba nas bzung ste grangs med gsum pas sa brgyad pa mi g.yo ba nas bcu gcig kun tu 'od kyi bar bgrod cing*/ de dag las tshogs sbyor ni so so'i skye bo'i sa dang sa dang po yan chad 'phags pa slob lam pa'i rgyud kyis bsdus shing bsod nams dang ye shes kyi tshogs gnyis bsgrubs par mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Among these many kinds of accounts, both extensive and brief, of incalculable ages and how [our teacher] engaged in a bodhisattva’s conduct, the most prevalent is as follows:
From the time our teacher venerated Buddha Great Embodiment during his lifetime as Prince Youthful Diligent Action, he cultivated the accumulations for one incalculable age, traversing the path of accumulation to awakening’s first stage. Then, from the time he venerated Buddha Precious Qualities during his lifetime as the merchant Excellent Wisdom, he traversed six stages, from the second to the seventh, during a second incalculable age. Then, from the time he venerated Buddha Lamp Radiance during his lifetime as a brahmin’s child Dharma Cloud, he traversed from the eighth stage, Unwavering, to the eleventh, Pervasive Luminosity, during a third incalculable age.
Collectively, these spiritual paths represent the stages of ordinary individuals (accumulation and preparation); and the stages of exalted beings on the path of training (awakening’s first stage and above). In traversing these paths, he accomplished the twofold accumulation of merit and wisdom.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
'ga' zhig dbang rtul dad can bcu drug ste/ /brtson 'grus 'bring po 'bum lhag grangs med brgyad/ /
dbang rnon shes rab can ni grangs med bzhis/ /bgrod cing ston pa nyid ni phyi ma dang*/ /
de yang brtson 'grus drag pos myur bar bshad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Some explain that an individual of lesser acumen imbued with faith treads the path for sixteen [incalculable ages];
One of average [acumen endowed with] diligence, for eight incalculable ages plus a hundred thousand [ages];
One of a high degree of acumen having sublime insight, for four
incalculable ages.
Our teacher himself belongs to this last group;
Moreover, due to his intense diligence, he was swifter.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
spyir byang sems rnams kyis lam bgrod pa'i yun la mkhas pa 'ga' zhig gang zag gi dbang gis dbang rtul dad pa can grangs med bcu drug_/'bring brtson 'grus can 'bum lhag pa'i grangs med brgyad/ dbang rnon shes rab can grangs med bzhi rnams kyis bgrod cing*/ bdag cag gi ston pa ni phyi ma dang*/ de la'ang brtson 'grus drag po'i khyad par gyis grangs med gsum lhag tsam zhig gis lam rdzogs par 'chad pa'ang yod do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Some scholars explain the general duration of a bodhisattva’s journey on the path as dependent on the individual’s acumen. An individual of lesser acumen also imbued with faith treads the path for sixteen incalculable ages. An individual of average acumen also endowed with diligence treads the path for eight incalculable ages, plus one hundred thousand ages. An individual of a high degree of acumen also imbued with sublime insight treads the path for four incalculable ages. Our teacher belongs to this last category. Moreover, due to his particularly intense diligence, he completed the spiritual path in a little more than three incalculable ages.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="3">
gsum pa [3. spyad bya'i chos bshad pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="3">
The Teachings in Which the Buddha Engaged [3]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
'gro smin zhing sbyong phar phyin drug gis bgrod/ /yang na theg pa mchog dman gnyis ka la/ /
mos rnams 'dun dang 'dul phyir spyod pa bzhi/ /mi zad brgyad cu la sogs mthar phyin mdzad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
[The Bodhisattva] traversed the path by maturing beings, purifying realms, and [completing] the six transcendent perfections.
Alternatively, he engaged in four forms of conduct — to foster interest in those devoted to the supreme way,
To the lesser way, or to both; and the conduct of guiding [beings].
He reached the end of the path through the eighty inexhaustible qualities and other attributes.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'o na bskal pa bgrang ba las 'das par byang chub sems dpas spyad par bya ba'i chos de gang zhe na/ sdus pa las/ bdag nyid chen po sems can yongs su smin bya dang*/ /zhing sbyong pha rol phyin rdzogs don byed kho nar zad/ /ces gsungs pa ltar/ sems can yongs su smin par mdzad pa dang*/ sangs rgyas kyi zhing sbyong ba dang*/ pha rol tu phyin pa drug rdzogs par mdzad pa ste rnam pa gsum mam/ yang na/ mdo sde rgyan las/ lus can theg pa chen po dang*/ /theg pa dman la mos pa dang*/ /gnyis po 'dun par bya ba dang*/ /gdul ba'i zhing na brtan rnams kyi/ /spyod pa bzhi po/ zhes bshad pa ltar/ theg chen la mos pa rnams kyi phyir pha rol tu phyin pa bcu'i spyod pa/ theg dman la mos pa rnams kyi phyir byang phyogs so bdun gyi spyod pa/ gnyi ga la mos pa rnams mthus 'dun par bya ba'i phyir mngon par shes pa'i spyod pa/ thams cad gdul ba'i phyir sems can smin pa'i spyod pa ste rnam pa bzhi'am/ blo gros mi zad pas zhus pa'i mdo las byang chub sems dpa' rnams kyi mi zad pa brgyad cu gsungs pa rnams te/ sems bskyed pa mi zad pa dang*/ bsam pa dang*/ sbyor ba dang*/ lhag pa'i bsam pa dang*/ pha rol tu phyin pa drug dang*/ tshad med bzhi dang*/ mngon shes lnga dang*/ bsdu ba bzhi dang*/ so so yang dag pa rig pa bzhi dang*/ rton pa bzhi dang*/ tshogs gnyis dang*/ byang phyogs so bdun dang*/ zhi lhag gnyis dang*/ gzungs spobs gnyis dang*/ chos kyi mdo bzhi dang*/ bgrod pa gcig dang*/ thabs la mkhas pa mi zad pa rnams dang*/ gzhan yang bzang po spyod pa tshad med pas sangs rgyas kyi yon tan bsam brjod kyi yul las 'das pa thob cing mthar phyin par mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
What teachings did the Bodhisattva engage in during those incalculable ages? The Concise Discourse on the Perfection of Sublime Insight states:
The great being accomplished only what was meaningful: He brought sentient beings to full maturity, purified realms, and completed the transcendent perfections.
[Thus, the Bodhisattva] brought sentient beings to full maturity, purified buddha realms, and completed the six transcendent perfections. Alternatively, The Ornament of the Discourses states:
Four forms of conduct Foster interest in embodied beings devoted to the great way, Those devoted to the lesser way, Or to both; And stabilize the domains of those to be guided.
As stated, he engaged in four forms of conduct: for those devoted to the great way, the conduct of the ten transcendent perfections; for those devoted to the lesser way, the conduct of the thirty-seven aspects of awakening; for those devoted to both, the conduct of clairvoyance to inspire them through his powers; and to guide all, the conduct of bringing sentient beings to spiritual maturity.
Alternatively, The Discourse Requested by Bodhisattva Infinite Wisdom lists eighty inexhaustible qualities of bodhisattvas—inexhaustible development of the mind of awakening, intention, application, superior intention, six transcendent perfections, four immeasurable wishes, five kinds of clairvoyance, four means to attract disciples, four perfect understandings, four kinds of reliance, two accumulations, thirty-seven aspects of awakening, tranquility and insight, retention and eloquence, four principles of the teachings, the unique path, and skillful means. As well as these, the Buddha engaged in immeasurable excellent conduct to attain enlightenment’s indescribable, inconceivable qualities, and reached the end of the path.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="V">
lnga pa [V. zhar byung dbang po'i rim pa bstan pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="V">
Bodhisattvas’ Levels of Capability [V]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
sems mchog thog mar bskyed dang sa dang po/ /brgyad pa'i skabs nas phyir mi ldog pa gsum/ /
dbang po'i khyad yin thub mchog dang po'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The three points at which bodhisattvas no longer regress — [From] the first instance of the supreme mind of awakening, at awakening’s first stage, or at the eighth stage —
Indicate distinctions of capability; the sublime Sage belongs to the first.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
byang chub sems dpa' dbang rnon sems mchog dang por bskyed pa tsam gyis phyir mi ldog pa dang*/ dbang 'bring sa dang po'i skabs dang*/ dbang rtul sa brgyad pa'i skabs nas phyir mi ldog pa gsum/ shin tu rtul po sa dgu pa'i skabs su'ang bshad de de dag kyang gong smos ltar dbang po'i khyad par yin cing*/ bdag cag gi ston pa thub mchog don kun grub pa 'di ni dang po yin te bram zergya mtsho rdul gyi tshe thugs dang po bskyed pa nyid nas phyir mi ldog pa'am/ byang chub sems dpa' skyon med pa la zhugs par dbu ma pa chos bshes kyi sher TIka tu gsal lo/ /ston pa nyid sngon byang chub kyi lam du ji ltar gshegs pa skabs dang po'i 'grel pa'o// //
</d>
<d e="2">
A bodhisattva of a high degree of acumen does not regress after the first time he or she develops the supreme mind of awakening; a bodhisattva of average acumen does not regress after attainment of awakening’s first stage; one of lesser acumen, at the eighth stage. These are the three points [after which bodhisattvas] no longer regress. One teaching even states that those of very low acumen [no longer regress after the attainment of] awakening’s ninth stage. These categories are based upon distinctions in capability. Our teacher, sublime Sage Siddharta, belongs to the first. From his very first development of the mind of awakening, when he was Brahmin Ocean Particles, he did not regress. In other words, he entered the flawless state of a bodhisattva. Dharmamitra of the middle way school elucidates this in A Commentary on the Perfection of Sublime Insight.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="skabs gnyis pa">
[de bzhin gshegs pa 'tshang rgya ba'i tshul bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Chapter 2">
2. The Buddha’s Enlightenment
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
!_skabs gnyis pa de bzhin gshegs pa 'tshang rgya ba'i tshul bshad pa la gnyis/ mdor bstan/ rgyas bshad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This chapter has two parts: (1) a brief presentation and (2) a full explanation of the Buddha’s enlightenment.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
dang po [I. mdor bstan] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
A Brief Presentation of the Buddha’s Enlightenment [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
bder gshegs 'tshang rgya'i tshul la lugs gsum ste/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
On the subject of how the Joyful Buddha attained enlightenment, three traditions exist:
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bdag cag gi ston mchog bde bar gshegs pa nyid mngon par rdzogs par 'tshang rgya ba'i tshul la'ang theg dman dang theg chen gsang sngags kyi sde snod las 'byung ba'i lugs srol gsum yod do/ /ste zhes pa lhag bcas kyi sgras mtshan dpe'i sbyar ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
On the subject of how our supreme teacher, the Joyful Buddha, attained
perfect, manifest enlightenment, three traditions exist, derived from collections of the lesser way, great way, and secret mantra teachings.
The colon at the end of the line of the root text above [ste in Tibetan] indicates a grammatical connection to the next sentence of the root text.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="II">
[II. rgyas bshad]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="II">
A Full Explanation of the Buddha’s Enlightenment [II]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la gsum/ theg dman nyan thos kyi 'dod pa/ theg pa chen po pa rnams kyi bzhed pa/ gsang sngags rdo rje theg pa'i tshul las 'byung ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: the Buddha’s enlightenment according to (1) the beliefs of the lesser way’s pious attendants, (2) the perspective of the great way’s followers, and (3) the approaches of the secret mantra vajra way.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
dang po [A. theg dman nyan thos kyi 'dod pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
The Buddha’s Enlightenment According to the Beliefs of the Lesser Way’s Pious Attendants [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
nyan thos pa rnams grangs med gsum gyi mthar/ /bskal pa brgya yis mtshan dpe'i rgyu bsgrubs te/ /
dga' ldan gnas 'khrungs mdzad pa bcu gnyis bstan/ /tshogs lam chen po'i rten la rdor gdan du/ /
bzhugs pa tshun chad so skye 'ching ldan te/ /stan thog gcig la lam bzhi mthar phyin mdzad/ /
zad dang mi skye shes pas sangs rgyas 'dod/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Pious attendants believe that at the end of three incalculable ages,
[The Buddha] completed the karmic causes of the marks and
signs of physical perfection during one hundred ages,
Was born in Joyful, and demonstrated the twelve deeds.
Until he sat at Vajra Seat, his physical support was at the highest [stage of the] path of accumulation
With the limitations of an ordinary being.
At that very time and place, he reached the end of the four
paths;
With knowledge of extinguishing and non-arising, he attained
enlightenment.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de la nyan thos pa rnams kyis gong du smos pa ltar grangs med gsum du tshogs bsags pa'i mthar sangs rgyas skar rgyal la tshigs bcad gcig gis zhag bdun bar ma chad du bstod pas bskal pa dgu'i tshogs 'dums/ de nas bskal pa 'di'i sangs rgyas 'od srungs bsnyen bkur ba yan chad la bskal pa dgu bcu go gcig ste bskal chen brgyar mtshan dpe'i rgyu bsgrubs nas dga' ldan gyi gnas su lha'i bu dam pa tog dkar por sku 'khrungs shing*/ de nas dga' ldan gyi gnas nas 'pho ba sogs mdzad pa bcu gnyis bstan pa ste/ de'ang srid pa tha ma pa rgyal bu don grub kyi dus grangs med gsum gyis tshogs rdzogs kyang tshogs lam chen po'i rten tsam yin cing*/ de nas rdo rje'i gdan la bzhugs pa tshun chad so so'i skye bo 'ching ba kun ldan yin la/ byang chub kyi shing drung du srod la bdud dpung bye ba phrag so bdun btul/ stan thog gcig de kho nar bden bzhi mi rtag sogs bcu drug rtogs pa'i lam gyis sbyor mthong sgom pa mi slob pa'i bar lam bzhi mthar phyin par mdzad cing*/ zad pa dang mi skye ba shes pas sangs rgyas pa dang*/ de'i sngon du ring 'phur skyes dang lhag spyod las 'jig rten pa'i bsam gtan gyi man ngag blangs te srid rtse'i snyoms 'jug man chad la 'dod chags dang bral zin pa'i chags bral sngon song gi sangs rgyas yin par 'dod do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
As stated in the last chapter, pious attendants believe that the Buddha gathered the accumulations during three incalculable ages. At the end of that time, he repeated a verse of praise to Buddha Star Monarch unceasingly for seven days, an act which equaled nine ages of accumulation. From that point, until his veneration of Guardian of the Light, the [third] buddha of this age, ninety-one ages elapsed. During those one hundred great ages, he completed the accumulation of the karmic causes of the marks and signs of a buddha’s physical perfection, after which he was born as the god Sacred White Crown in Joyful Heaven. Following that, he demonstrated twelve deeds [detailed in the next chapter], including departure from Joyful.
During his final lifetime, as Prince Siddharta, although he had perfected the accumulations during three incalculable ages, his physical support was merely at the highest [stage of the] path of accumulation, with all the limitations of an ordinary being, until he sat at Vajra Seat. There, under the tree of awakening at midnight, he subdued three hundred and seventy million armies of demons. Only at that very place and time did the path of realization of the four noble truths’ sixteen aspects, such as impermanence, bring him to the end of the four [remaining] paths— preparation, seeing, meditation, and beyond training. With knowledge of extinguishing and non-arising, he attained enlightenment.
Prior to this, he received pith instructions for worldly meditative concentration from Adrada and Udrada, and thereby gained freedom from desire up to the level of the meditative absorption of the pinnacle of existence. Thus, it is believed he was already an enlightened being freed from attachment.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
gnyis pa [B. theg pa chen po pa rnams kyi bzhed pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
The Buddha’s Enlightenment according to the Perspective of the Great Way’s Followers [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
theg chen kha cig phal cher mthun par smra/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Some great way [perspectives] are in general agreement [with the pious attendant tradition].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
theg chen thun mong ba kha cig gis kyang sa lam gyi khyad par cung zad ma gtogs gong smos nyan thos kyi lugs de dang phal cher mthun par smra ba yod de yon tan yongs su bkod pa'i mdo las/ ngas bla na med pa'i byang chub tu sems
dang po bskyed pa nas bzung ste/ bskal pa chen po grangs med pa gsum du brtson pa chen pos tshogs bsags shing*/ tshe lo brgya pa'i tshe sems can long ba 'dren pa med pa rnams la gzigs te/ dzam+bu'i gling 'di nyid du sangs rgyas te chos kyi 'khor lo bsam gyis mi khyab pa yongs su bskor ro/ /zhes pas so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Some common great way perspectives are in general agreement with the pious attendant tradition’s beliefs expressed above, with the exception of slight differences in the delineation of the paths and stages. The Discourse That Presents All Qualities states:
From the moment I first engendered the mind of unsurpassable awakening, I cultivated the accumulations with great diligence for three incalculable great ages. At the time when the human life span was one hundred years, I saw beings were blind and had no guide. Therefore, I attained enlightenment here in the Land of Jambu and turned the inconceivable wheel of the teachings.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
gzhan du bskal pa dpag med sngon rol nas/ /dbang po'i tog sogs rgyal bar gyur bar gsungs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Alternatively, it is said that countless ages ago,
He became a victor, such as Crown of the Powerful One.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gzhan du nges pa'i don kho na'i dbang du byas na bskal pa dpag tu med pa'i gong du mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas zin pa yin te/ yab sras mjal ba'i mdor/ sngon 'das pa'i dus bskal padpag tu med pa'i gong rol du 'jig rten khams gang+gA'i klung gi bye ma snyed kyi zhing gcig tu gyur pa der/ de bzhin gshegs pa dbang po'i tog ces bya bar sangs rgyas nas sems can gyi don mdzad de mya ngan las 'das nas/ slar yang de 'og tu sangs rgyas pa'i tshul bsam gyis mi khyab pa bskal pa 'di'i bar du bstan cing*/ da dung yang so so skye bo sems dang po bskyed pa nas bzung ste/ sangs rgyas pa'i tshul 'khor ba ma stongs bar du mdzad do zhes pa nas/ dpa' bo chen po thabs mkhas te/ /sems can yongs su smin mdzad phyir/ /bye ba phrag brgyar rgyal ba nyid/ /sangs rgyas nyid du bstan gyur kyang*/ /da dung yang ni 'dren pa khyod/ /sangs rgyas mang po ston par mdzad/ /ces dang*/ pad+ma dkar po las/ rigs kyi bu nga ni bskal pa bye ba khrag khrig brgya stong mang po'i gong rol tu mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas so zhes dang*/ rgyud de nyid bsdus pa las/ bcom ldan 'das bskal pa bsam gyis mi khyab par mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas nas shAkya'i rigs su skye ba ston par mdzad do/ /zhes sogs 'byung ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Alternatively, the perspective based only on the definitive meaning is that he achieved perfect, manifest enlightenment countless ages ago. The Reunion of Father and Son Discourse states:
In the past, countless ages ago, in a world-system that united as many realms as there are grains of sand in the Ganges, I attained enlightenment as Transcendent Buddha Crown of the Powerful One, aided beings, and transcended sorrow. Then once again, from that point until the present age, I have repeatedly demonstrated the inconceivable process of enlightenment.
I will continue, until cyclic existence is empty, to demonstrate [this process of] enlightenment, beginning with the initial development of the mind of awakening as an ordinary being.
Further,
Great hero, skillful in means, Even though you, the Victor, Have demonstrated the attainment of enlightenment A billion times To bring sentient beings to full maturity, You, the guide, will continue To demonstrate enlightenment many more times.
The White Lotus of the Sacred Doctrine states:
Sons and daughters of my spiritual family, I attained perfect, manifest enlightenment many hundred thousand million ages ago.
A Compilation on Thatness states:
An inconceivable number of ages ago, the Transcendent Conqueror attained perfect, manifest enlightenment, then demonstrated taking birth in the Shakya clan.
There are many accounts similar to these.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
dang por tshogs sbyor gnyis par gcig nas bdun/ /gsum par dag pa gsum bgrod srid mtha' la/ /
'og min 'od zer dbang nod rdor ting skyes/ /longs skur 'tshang rgya sprul pas don mdzad mthun/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
[The great way’s traditions] concur that during the first [incalculable age], he traversed the paths of accumulation and preparation;
During the second, [awakening’s] first seven [stages]; during the third, the three pure stages.
In his final lifetime, he received the empowerment of great radiance in Unsurpassed Realm; a vajra-like meditative state arose within him.
He attained enlightenment as the body of perfect rapture; his emanations performed beneficial deeds.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de la theg chen pa rnams kyi lugs su grangs med dang po tshogs lam dang sbyor lam nges 'byed cha bzhi bgrod/ gnyis par sa dang po nas bdun pa'i bar dang*/ gsum pa'i skabs su dag pa sa gsum bgrod nas srid pa tha ma pa'i skabs su 'og min du phyogs bcu'i rgyal ba rnams las 'od zer chen po'i dbang bskur nod cing rdo rje lta bu'i ting nge 'dzin skyes te longs spyod rdzogs pa'i skur sangs rgyas nas ring por ma lon par sprul pa'i gzugs kyis rdo rje'i gdan du 'tshang rgya ba'i tshul bstan te 'gro ba'i don mdzad par bzhed pa mthun par 'byung ngo*/ /'og min du 'tshang rgya ba'i tshul la bzhed pa gnyis te/ kha cig 'og min stug po bkod pa'i zhing du sangs rgyas pa'i rjes la gtsang gnas kyi 'og min du 'tshang rgya ba'i tshul bstan par bzhed de/ lang kar gshegs pa las/ gtsang ma'i ris dag spangs pa yi/ /'og min gnas mchog nyams dga' bar/ /yang dag sangs rgyas der sangs rgyas/ /sprul pa po gcig 'dir sangs rgyas/ /zhes dang*/ 'dod pa'i khams dang gzugs med du/ /sangs rgyas mngon par sangs mi rgya/ /gzugs kyi khams kyi 'og min du/ /'dod chags bral khyed der sangs rgya/ /zhes pa'i lung snga phyi'i dgongs pa gung sbrel bar 'dzad do/ /slob dpon ngag dbang grags pas/ dpal ldan stug po bkod pa nyid du don dam thugs chud cing*/ /dga' ldan skye bo'i don mdzad phyir ni dam pa tog dkar gyur/ /de nas 'dir ni 'gro ba'i don du shAkya'i tog gyur gang*/ /'chi bdag las rgyal sgyu ma kun ston de ni rgyal gyur cig_/ces stug po bkod par sangs rgyas nas dga' ldan du skye ba bzhes par gsungs pa'ang mi 'gal te longs sku brnyes zin nas gcig dang du ma'i cho 'phrul mtha' yas pa la mnga' mdzad pa'i phyir ro/ /'ga' zhig lung gong ma'i ngos 'dzin gtsang ris las gong du spags pa'i 'og min la ngos 'dzin cing thog mar de nyid kho nar sangs rgyas par bzhed pa'ang snang ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The traditions of the great way’s followers concur that during the first incalculable age, the Bodhisattva traversed the path of accumulation and the path of preparation’s four stages of ascertainment; during the second, awakening’s first seven stages; and during the third, the three pure stages [the eighth, ninth, and tenth]. In his final lifetime in Unsurpassed Realm, he received the empowerment of great radiance from the ten directions’ victors, a vajra-like meditative state arose within him, and he attained enlightenment as the body of perfect rapture. Not long thereafter, his emanated form demonstrated the process of enlightenment at Vajra Seat and performed deeds beneficial to beings.
Regarding the process of his enlightenment in Unsurpassed Realm, two perspectives concerning this realm exist: Some assert that after he attained enlightenment in Unsurpassed Richly Adorned Realm, he demonstrated the process of enlightenment in the Unsurpassed of the pure domains [in the gods’ heavens]. The Journey to Lanka Discourse states:
In the joyous supreme Unsurpassed Realm, Not part of the pure [heavenly] realms, [You,] the true Buddha, achieved enlightenment there. One of your emanations achieved enlightenment here.
Further,
The Buddha did not attain manifest enlightenment In the desire or formless realms; You, who are free from attachment, attained enlightenment In Unsurpassed Heaven of the form realm.
The underlying intent of the former and latter excerpts is [that the two enlightenments] were sequential. Master Vakishvarakirti states:
In the glorious Richly Adorned Realm, he comprehended the ultimate. To aid individuals in Joyful Heaven, he became Sacred White Crown. Then, to benefit this world’s beings, he became Crown of the Shakyas. Victorious over Lord of Death, displaying magical illusions, may he be victorious!
There is no contradiction in saying that he achieved enlightenment in Richly Adorned Realm and then was born [as a bodhisattva] in Joyful Heaven. Once he attained the body of perfect rapture, he had mastery of limitless miracles of single and multiple emanations. Some evidently identify “Unsurpassed Realm” referred to in the above quote [from The Journey to Lanka Discourse] as an Unsurpassed Realm that is higher than another located among the pure gods’ realms, and that it was only there that he first attained enlightenment.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="C">
[C. gsang sngags rdo rje theg pa'i tshul las 'byung ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="C">
The Buddha’s Enlightenment according to the Approaches of the Secret Mantra Vajra Way [C]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gsum pa la gzhi/ bya spyod kyi lugs/ rnal 'byor rgyud kyi lugs/ rnal 'byor bla med kyi lugs/ zhar byung 'og min gyi rnam grangs bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has four parts: the Buddha’s enlightenment according to (1) action and conduct tantras’ traditions, (2) yoga tantras’ traditions, and (3) the highest yoga tantras’ traditions; and (4) a supplementary presentation of various definitions of Unsurpassed Realm.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
dang po [1. bya spyod kyi lugs] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
The Buddha’s Enlightenment according to Action and Conduct Tantras’ Traditions [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
rdo rje theg pa bya ba'i rgyud las ni/ /me tog kun tu ston las sngags thos nas/ /
spyod pa spyad mthar dga' ldan nas sprul sogs/ /theg chen spyi dang spyod rgyud khyad par mthun/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The vajra way’s action tantras
State that he studied tantra with Buddha Showing Flowers to All.
He engaged in its conduct, then emanated from Joyful Heaven, and so on.
This accords with the general great way; conduct tantras concur with the specific details.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rgyal ba 'tshang rgya ba'i tshul rdo rje theg pa'i bka' srol gsar rnying rnams las mi 'dra ba mang du gsungs pa'i gtso bor/ bya ba'i rgyud las/ dang por thugs bskyed nas de bzhin gshegs pa me tog kun tu ston pa'i spyan sngar sngags thos te sngags kyi spyod pa spyad pa'i sgo nas grangs med gsum du tshogs bsags shing*/ dam pa tog dkar po nas 'phos pa zas gtsang gi sras su gyur nas sangs rgyas pa sogs theg chen spyi dang khyad par bshad srol rags par mthun zhing*/ spyod rgyud las/ sems bskyed de sngags kyi spyod pa spyad nas sa bcu mngon du byas shing 'og min du longs skur sangs rgyas pa'i tshul bstan par bshad pa sogs theg chen spyi dang khyad par du mthun no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The vajra way’s early and later translation schools present many different [accounts of the] process of the Victor’s enlightenment. The principal ones are the following:
Action tantras state that he first developed the mind of awakening, then studied tantra in the presence of Transcendent Buddha Showing Flowers to All. He then engaged in tantric conduct and thereby cultivated the accumulations for three incalculable ages. He departed from his life as Sacred White Crown, took birth as King Shuddhodana’s son, and attained enlightenment, etc. This concurs, for the most part, with the great way perspective and its general teaching system.
The conduct tantras state that he developed the mind of awakening, engaged in tantric conduct, manifestly achieved awakening’s tenth stage, then demonstrated the process of enlightenment as the body of perfect rapture in Unsurpassed Realm. This account concurs with the general great way perspective and its specific details.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
[2. rnal 'byor rgyud kyi lugs]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
The Buddha’s Enlightenment according to the Yoga Tantras’ Traditions [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la gsum gyi dang po/
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts. First:
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
de nyid bsdus par don grub snying po la/ /bzhugs tshe sangs rgyas mthus skul ting 'dzin las/ /
bzhengs te dbang bskur brnyes nas mngon byang chub/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
According to A Synthesis of the Absolute, when Siddharta sat at Heart of Awakening,
The buddhas inspired him, and he rose from his meditative state.
He received empowerment and achieved manifest awakening.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rnal 'byor rgyud de nyid bsdus pa nas/ byang chub sems dpa' don grub byang chub kyi snying por bzhugs pa la sangs rgyas rnams kyis bskul nas/ mi g.yo ba'i ting nge 'dzin las bzhengs te sems bskyed cing de bzhin gshegs pa thams cad kyis dbang bskur nas mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas par bshad do/ /
gnyis pa/
</d>
<d e="2">
The yoga tantras’ A Synthesis of the Absolute teaches that when Bodhisattva Siddharta sat at Heart of Awakening, the buddhas inspired him: He rose from his unwavering meditative state and engendered the mind of awakening. All transcendent buddhas gave him empowerment, and he achieved perfect, manifest enlightenment.
Second:
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
shAkya bshes gnyen dka' thub mdzad pa'i tshe/ /ye shes sku lus 'og min gshegs pa la/ /
rgyal bas dbang bskur mngon sangs rgyas pa dang*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Shakyamitra teaches that when the Bodhisattva practiced
hardships,
His wisdom body went to Unsurpassed;
The victors gave him empowerment and he attained manifest
enlightenment.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
slob dpon shAkya bshes gnyen sogs kyis zas gtsang gi sras chu bo nai rany+dza na'i 'gram du dka' thub mdzad pa'i tshe sangs rgyas rnams kyis bskul bas/ ye shes kyi lus 'og min du byon pa la sangs rgyas rnams kyis dbang bskur te sangs rgyas nas/ slar rnam smin gyi lus la zhugs nas sprul skur 'tshang rgya tshul bstan par bshad pa dang mthun par/ bod du'ang lo chen rin bzang dang*/ dgyes rdor gyi 'grel byed kha cig bzhed la/ de ltar yang sangs rgyas ye shes zhabs kyi grol ba'i thig le las/ ci phyir shAkya thub pa yis/ /grangs med gsum du tshogs bsags kyang*/ /'di don ma rtogs ne rany+dzar/ /ci yang ma yin ting 'dzin gnas/ /de tshe phyogs bcu'i bde gshegs kyis/ /thal byung blo can de bzlog ste/ /nam mkha'i dbyings ltar rnam dag pa'i/ /zab gsal gnyis med rab bstan pas/ /nam phyed dus na rgyal ba ltar/ /de nyid bsgoms pas tho rangs dus/ /skad cig gis ni yang dag rtogs/ /'gro ba 'dul bar bya ba'i phyir/ /byang chub snying por bzhugs nas kyang*/ /dpung chen bdud rnams rab bcom ste/ /sems can gzung bar bya don du/ /chos kyi 'khor lo bskor ba'o/ /zhes dang*/ snga 'gyur gyi rgyud sgyu 'phrul bla ma las kyang*/ don grub dka' thub lus can la/ /phyogs bcu'i rgyal ba sprin bzhin du/ /'dus pas longs spyod don gyi phyir/ /srod dang tho rengs dus nyid du/ /nyi zla za ba'i dbang byin nas/ /rol pa'i ka ra bstan pa yis/ /de bzhin de bzhin gshegs pa'o/ /zhes gsungs so/ /
gsum pa/
</d>
<d e="2">
Master Shakyamitra and others teach that when King Shuddhodana’s son practiced hardships on the bank of the Nairanjana River, the buddhas inspired him: his wisdom body went to Unsurpassed, where they gave him empowerment and he attained enlightenment. He re-entered his [human] body of ripened acts, then demonstrated the process of enlightenment as enlightenment’s manifest body.
In Tibet, great Translator Rinchen Zangpo and some commentators on the tantras of Vajra Creator of Delight agree with this explanation. Likewise, Venerable Buddhajnana states inThe Vital Essence of Liberation:
Shakyamuni cultivated accumulations
During three incalculable ages,
Yet had not yet realized his goal.
At Nairanjana River, while he dwelled in the meditative state of
“nothing whatsoever,”
The ten directions’ joyful buddhas
Turned him away from that unimpeded mental state,
And taught him nondual profound clarity,
Pure like the sphere of space.
Thus, at midnight he was like a victor;
By meditating on that state,
He attained genuine realization in an instant at dawn.
To guide beings,
He remained at Heart of Awakening
And there defeated huge hordes of demons.
Caring for beings,
He turned the wheel of the teachings.
Further, a tantra of the early translations, The Highest Miraculous Display, states:
The ten directions’ victors gathered like clouds Around Siddharta, the ascetic. During the evening and at dawn, In order that he gain perfect rapture, They granted him the empowerment of the eclipse of sun and moon, And revealed the sweet savor of enjoyment: He became a transcendent buddha, gone to suchness.
Third:
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
kun snying srid pa tha mar rgyal rnams las/ /dbang thob grangs med sngon rol sangs rgyas te/ /
slar yang shAkya'i rigs su ston par bzhed/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Anandagarbha believes that incalculable ages ago, in [the Bodhisattva’s] final existence,
The victors gave him empowerment and he attained enlightenment.
Then he once again demonstrated taking birth in the Shakya clan.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
yo ga'i shing rta chen po slob dpon kun dga'i snying pos/ rgyal bas sems bskyed nas grangs med gsum du tshogs bsags te bsam gtan dang gzugs med sogs kyi ting nge 'dzin thams cad bskyed cing srid pa tha ma par mdzad/ sangs rgyas rnams las dbang bskur ba thob cing bskal pa mang po'i sngon rol tu sangs rgyas nas slar shAkya'i rigs su skye ba bstan par bshad pa legs te/ rtse mor/ bskal pa grangs med sngon du ni/ /bcom ldan byang chub mdzad pa gang*/ /zhes dang*/ rdo rje snying po rgyan gyi rgyud las/ de nas bcom ldan 'das shAkya thub pas de dag gis gsol ba btab pa'i tshig nye bar gsan nas/ 'og min gyi gnas nas byon te dga' ldan gyi gnas su bzhugs nas dga' ldan gyi ris kyi lha'i bu rnams la chos bstan nas zas gtsang gi rigs la mngon par gzigs te/ zhes so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Master Anandagarbha, an important founder of yoga [tantra commentary], gives this excellent explanation: The Victor engendered the mind of awakening, then gathered the accumulations for three incalculable ages. He cultivated all meditative states, such as those related to [the heavens of] meditative concentration and the formless [realms], and reached his final lifetime. The buddhas gave him empowerment and he attained enlightenment many ages ago. Then he again demonstrated taking birth in the Shakya clan. The Vajra Pinnacle Instruction Tantra states:
Incalculable ages in the past, The Transcendent Conqueror attained awakening.
The Vajra Heart Ornament Tantra states:
Having listened attentively to the words of their supplications, Transcendent Conqueror Shakyamuni departed from Unsurpassed Realm, resided in Joyful Heaven, presented the teachings to Joyful Heaven’s gods, and then manifestly saw King Shuddhodana’s family.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="3">
gsum pa [3] bla med kyi lugs ltar na/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="3">
The Buddha’s Enlightenment according to the Highest Yoga Tantras’ Traditions [3]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
bla med nges don srid mtha'i byang sems zhig_/'og min chen por thun min zab lam gyi/ /
nye rgyus rdo rje 'chang gyur sprul pa'i sku/ /sangs rgyas tshe na'ang nye rgyus bgrod par gsungs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
According to the highest yoga tantras’ definitive meaning,
A bodhisattva in his final lifetime in Great Unsurpassed Realm
Practiced the exceptional profound path’s immediate cause and
became Buddha Vajra Bearer.
Even when his emanation [demonstrated] enlightenment, he traveled the path by means of the immediate cause.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rnal 'byor bla med chen po pha ma gnyis med kyi rgyud rnams kyi dgongs pa dang bstun slob dpon so so'i bshad tshul mang yang spyi tsam du snang tshul dang bstun pa shAkya bshes gnyen ltar 'chad pa'ang yod kyang*/ nges don du srid pa tha ma'i byang sems su gyur pa zhig gnas 'og min chen por lam thun mong ma yin pa'i zab lam gyi nye rgyu la brten nas mngon par byang chub pa lnga la sogs pas rdo rje 'chang nyid du sangs rgyas par gyur cing*/ slar sprul pa'i sku 'dzam gling ma ga d+hAr sangs rgyas pa'i tshul bstan pa'i tshe na'ang btsun mo'i 'khor la longs spyod pa sogs nye rgyus lam bgrod cing spangs rtogs mthar phyin par gsungs te/ dus 'khor bsdus rgyud las/ mi rnams dgrol ba'i don nu sras dang bcas pa rgyal ba'i bdag po las kyi sar ni rab bzhugs te/ /mngal ni rab tu bzung bar mdzad cing mchog gi thugs rje dag gis byang chub bskyed par mdzad nas ni/ /nyon mongs dang ni bdud rnams bcom nas sa yi steng gi gnas su chos kyi 'khor lo rab bskor te/ /sprul pa sgyu ma mdzad nas slar yang bcom ldan 'das ni dag pa'i sku can de nyid kho na'o/ /zhes dang*/ 'grel chen las/ sangs rgyas bcom ldan 'das sngar sa bcu gnyis kyi dbang phyug tu gyur pa/ mkhas pa sgyu 'phrul chen po 'chang ba sgyu 'phrul chen po'i mig 'phrul dang ldan pa/ 'phags pa'i yul du lum bi nIr shAkya'i rigs mi'i dbang po zas gtsang ma'i lha mo sgyu 'phrul chen mo'i lhums nas bltams pa ni gzhon nu don kun grub pa yin la/ zhes dang*/ rgyud gzhan las kyang gsal bar 'byung ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Various masters have each taught many explanations [of the Buddha’s enlightenment] based on the great highest yoga tantras’ father, mother, or nondual tantras. Their general outline is similar to Shakyamitra’s [mentioned above].
Nevertheless, the definitive meaning is that a bodhisattva in his final lifetime in the supreme Unsurpassed Realm engaged in the exceptional profound path’s immediate cause and used such means as the five branches of manifest awakening to attain enlightenment as Buddha Vajra Bearer. Even when his emanation demonstrated the process of enlightenment in Magadha, in the Land of Jambu, he traveled the path of the immediate cause, such as enjoyment of his circle of queens, and reached the limits of renunciation and realization. The Concise Tantra of the Wheel of Time states:
The chief victor and his heirs came to this land of karmic action to liberate human beings. He entered a human womb and with pure supreme compassion, he resolved to awaken. He conquered demons and afflictive emotions, then turned the wheel of the teachings on this earth.
He emanated a body of magical illusion and again [demonstrated becoming] a transcendent conqueror. [These appearances] are only of his pure wisdom body.
The Great Commentary to “The Tantra of the Wheel of Time” states:
Buddha, the Transcendent Conqueror, had already attained the state of a lord of awakening’s twelfth stage. Wise, he wielded impressive miraculous powers and was endowed with those powers’ optical illusions. In Lumbini, in the land of exalted beings, he was born from the womb of Mahamayadévi, who was the goddess of King Shuddhodana, lord of the Shakya clan. The Buddha was the youth Siddharta.
This is also clearly stated in other tantras.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="4">
bzhi pa [4. zhar byung 'og min gyi rnam grangs bshad pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="4">
Various Definitions of the Unsurpassed Realm [4]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
'og min la yang don rtags rig gsar rtog_/'jig rten drug tu sangs rgyas gsang bas bshad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Buddhaguhya defined the Unsurpassed Realm in six ways: Ultimate, symbolic, of awareness, secret, conceptual, and worldly.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'tshang rgya ba'i gnas 'og min ces pa la'ang mtha' dpyad na mdo rgyud rnams las rgya che chung 'ga' zhig tu bshad cing*/ grub pa'i slob dpon sangs rgyas gsang bas mdzad pa'i spyan 'grel las/ don gyi 'og min chos kyi dbyings te sangs rgyas bzhugs gnas yin zhing de'i gong na gzhan med pa'i phyir ro/ /rtags kyi 'og min dbyings dang ye shes dbyer med kyi rtags su gzhal yas khang gi dbyibs dang kha dog tu snang ba ste longs spyod rdzogs sku'i bzhugs gnas yin zhing chos kyi dbyings mtshon byed kyi rtags de'i gong na gzhan med pa'i phyir ro/ /rig pa'i 'og min dngos po'i gnas lugs ji lta ba bzhin rtogs pa rig pa'i ye shes te/ dag pa gnyis ldan gyi chos sku'i bzhugs gnas yin zhing de'i gong na rig pa gzhan med pa'i phyir ro/ /gsang ba'i 'og min yum gyi mkha' ste/ gsang ba sku'i bzhugs gnas yin zhing*/ gnas kyi yon tan gong na gzhan med pa'i phyir ro/ /rtog pa'i 'og min las dang po pas 'og min gyi gzhal yas khang bsgom pa ste/ lhag pa'i ting nge 'dzin gyi dkyil 'khor gyi bzhugs gnas yin zhing*/ don spyi 'dzin byed kyi rtog pa de'i gong na gzhan med pa'i phyir ro/ /'jig rten gnas kyi 'og min gtsang ma ris kyi lha lnga'i yang steng ste/ 'phags pa rnams kyi bzhugs gnas yin zhing gzugs khams kyi gnas de'i gong na gzhan med pa'i phyir ro/ /zhes bshad do/ /gzhan yang*/
</d>
<d e="2">
If we investigate what is meant by “the place of enlightenment, the Unsurpassed Realm,” the discourses and tantras present a number of both simple and complex explanations. The accomplished master Buddhaguhya’s Annotated Commentary[3][3. No catalog I have seen attributes this work, an annotated commentary to The Secret Essence Tantra, to Buddhaguhya, nor is the work itself signed or credited to a translator.] states:
The ultimate Unsurpassed Realm is the basic space of phenomena; this is the buddhas’ abode, no realm lies above it.
The symbolic Unsurpassed Realm is the symbol of indivisible basic space and wisdom—the appearances of a celestial palace’s colors and shapes. This is the body of perfect rapture’s abode—no symbol that represents the basic space of phenomena lies above it.
The Unsurpassed Realm of awareness is the wisdom of awareness, the realization of the abiding nature of reality as it is. This is the abode of the body of ultimate enlightenment endowed with two purities; no other awareness lies above it.
The secret Unsurpassed Realm is the female consort’s space; this is the wisdom body’s secret abode, no other place’s qualities surpass it.
The conceptual Unsurpassed Realm is a beginner’s meditation on Unsurpassed Realm’s celestial palace. This is the abode of the sacred circle’s exceptional meditative state; no other conceptual generic image to hold the mind lies above it.
The worldly Unsurpassed Realm is situated above even the pure domains’ five heavens; the abode of exalted beings, no other place in the form realm lies above it.
Further,
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
yang dag don dang rang snang stug po bkod/ /rang bzhin sprul gnas gtsang ris 'og min rnams/ /
sku gsum zhing du klong chen rab 'byams bzhed/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Longchen Rabjam considers that the three bodies of enlightenment’s realms
Are true ultimate [Unsurpassed Realm], self-manifest Richly Adorned [Unsurpassed Realm],
And the manifest body’s natural abode and the pure domains’ Unsurpassed Realm.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sngar bshad pa de'ang bsdu na 'og min rigs gsum du 'du ste/ mtha' dbus phyogs cha gang du'ang bzhag tu med cing spros pa thams cad dang bral ba'i ngo bo sangs rgyas kyi sa mthar thug gam bgrod bya dam pa ste yang dag don gyi 'og min zhes bya'o/ /chos sku'i dbyings las ye shes chen po'i snang bar rang byung ba 'od kyi gzhal yas khang dang gtso 'khor du snang ba ye shes lnga'i rigs su lhun gyis grub cing dus thams cad du 'pho 'gyur med pa rigs lnga so so'i dkyil 'khor gyi tshom bu nam mkha'i dbyings kyi mtha' klas par rang snang ba ni 'og min chen po stug po bkod pa zhes bya'o/ /gdul bya sa la gnas pa rnams kyi don du dbus na 'og min khang bu brtsegs pa sogs rigs lnga'i zhing du snang ba ni rang bzhin sprul sku'i zhing gi 'og min dang*/ 'dres ma'i don du mi mjed la sogs pa 'gro ba sems can gyi snang ba dang mthun pa'i gnas kyi mchog rang rang gi 'jig rten de'i gzugs kyi khams bsam gtan bzhi pa'i gtsang ma ris kyi lha lnga'i gnas kyi 'og min rags pa'i dngos po ma yin pa/ dang ba 'od kyi rang bzhin las grub pa'i gnas/ gzhal yas khang la sogs pa bkod pa'i bye brag sna tshogs pas brgyan pa ni gtsang gnas kyi 'og min yongs su grags pa ste/ snga ma gnyis chos sku dang longs sku'i zhing*/ phyi ma gnyis ni sprul sku'i gnas te sku gsum gyi zhing du kun mkhyen klong chen rab 'byams bzang pos bzhed do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
All-knowing Longchen Rabjam Zangpo considers that the previous explanations can be subsumed into three categories of Unsurpassed Realm: [First,] “true ultimate Unsurpassed Realm,” indefinable in terms of center, limit, or direction, the essence free from all formulations, is enlightenment’s final stage, the sacred goal.
[Second,] “Richly Adorned Supreme Unsurpassed Realm” naturally arises as supreme wisdom’s appearances from ultimate enlightenment’s basic space. They arise as celestial palaces of light, and principal deities and retinues, spontaneously present as the five wisdoms’ aspects, deathless and changeless throughout all time. Each assembly of the five wisdom families’ sacred circles self-manifests throughout the infinity of the expanse of space.
[Third,] “Unsurpassed Realm, the natural realm of enlightenment’s manifest body” appears as the five wisdom families’ realms (Unsurpassed Realm’s multi-storied palace in the center, etc.), for the benefit of disciples who have attained stages of awakening. What is widely known as “Unsurpassed Realm of the pure domains,” the supreme place perceivable by beings of world-systems such as Endurance, appears for the benefit of both [exalted and ordinary beings]. In each world, Unsurpassed Realm lies within the form realm, the pure domains of the five levels of gods immersed in the fourth degree of concentration. This Unsurpassed Realm has no coarse substance: it is a place made of pure light; various specific features, such as a celestial palace, adorn it.
These three are the three bodies of enlightenment’s realms: the former two (true ultimate Unsurpassed and Richly Adorned Supreme Unsurpassed Realm) are realms of the body of ultimate enlightenment and the body of enlightenment’s perfect rapture, while the latter two (the natural realm of enlightenment’s manifest body, and the pure domains’ Unsurpassed Realm) are the manifest body’s realms.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
gzhan yang dngos btags khyad sogs bshad tshul mang*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
In addition, many explanations exist, based on distinctions of Unsurpassed Realm being actual or nominal, etc.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag las gzhan yang 'og min gyi gnas la bod kyi mkhas pa rnams kyis dngos dang btags pa'i khyad par sogs bshad tshul dang dgag sgrub mang du spros par snang yang 'dir ma smos la/ snying po lta bu thams cad mkhyen pa sgrol ba'i mgon pos/ 'og min stug po bkod pa'i zhing la'ang rjes mthun pa sa brgyad dgu la snang ba dang*/ cung zad bsgribs pa'i zhing khams sa bcu pa la snang ba dang*/ shin tu dag pa'i zhing khams sangs rgyas kho na la snang ba ste dngos btags la phye na gsum yod la/ de gsum la rim par btags pa ba/ tsam po dang*/ khyad par can gsum du brda sbyar na rung ngo*/ /de la longs sku'i zhing khams zhes bya zhing*/ lang gshegs las gzugs khams yin pa dang gnas gtsang ma'i 'og min ma yin par yang bshad pa ni lha'i bu dbang phyug chen po'i gnas de yin la/ der 'tshang rgya tshul bshad pa 'di'ang longs sku 'tshang rgya tshul ma yin te/ mchog gi sprul sku ston tshul zhig yin la/ sprul sku de ni byang sems rnams la snang bas rtsa ba dang stong gsum du mdzad pa bcu gnyis ston pa ni des sprul pa'i yan lag nyid do/ /de lta bu'i 'og min de'ang byang sems mos spyod shas che ba rnams dang*/ ma dag pa'i sa la gnas pa'i 'phags pa rnams kyi thun mong gi dge ba'i las kyis bsgrubs pa yin pas rgya tshad nges pa dang*/ rnam par snang mdzad kyis gsar du bsgrubs par bshad pas stug po bkod pa ni ma yin te bde ba can bzhin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In addition to these, Tibetan scholars have produced a proliferation of explanations, refutations, and assertions concerning Unsurpassed Realm, such as distinctions between the actual and the nominal [Unsurpassed Realm]. I will not present these explanations here, yet all-knowing Taranata captures their essence in his threefold categorization of Richly Adorned Unsurpassed Realm based on a distinction between the actual and nominal [realms]: the Unsurpassed Realm similar [to the actual realm], which appears to bodhisattvas at awakening’s eighth and ninth stages; the slightly obscured realm, which appears to bodhisattvas at the tenth stage; and the very pure realm, which appears only to buddhas. It is also appropriate to affix the terms nominal, ordinary, and special to these three. These constitute Unsurpassed Realm as a realm of enlightenment’s perfect rapture.
The realm referred to in The Journey to Lanka Discourse as situated in the form realm is the great powerful gods’ heaven but is not the Unsurpassed Realm of the pure domains. The description of the process of enlightenment in that place [above, under the heading “Perspectives of the Great Way’s Followers”] does not refer to the process of the body of perfect rapture’s enlightenment, but to the supreme manifest body’s demonstration of that process. Such a manifest body appears to bodhisattvas and it thus serves as the basic source [of further emanations], whereas demonstrations of the twelve deeds throughout the threefold thousand world-system constitute its secondary emanations. Moreover, such an Unsurpassed Realm [where the source manifest body demonstrates enlightenment] created by the collective virtuous actions of bodhisattvas who are mainly engaged in intentional conduct and exalted bodhisattvas on awakening’s impure stages has a definite size. It is taught that Buddha Illuminator newly created it; thus, it is not the realm Richly Adorned, which is like the pure realm Blissful.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dus 'khor las/ gtsang ma ris gnas la sogs par bcom ldan gang zhig rnam par bzhugs pa nyan thos rnams kyi slad du ste/ /zhes gsungs pa'i gtsang gnas kyang de dang don gcig pa yin la/ mdo las de gtsang gnas min par gsungs pa ni nyan thos kyi sde snod las gsungs pa'i gtsang ma'i gnas lnga po de rnams min pa la dgongs pa'i phyir/ spyir gtsang gnas yin pa mi 'gal lo/ /'di byang sems 'phags pa kho na'i spyod yul yin pa dang nyan thos kyi don ces pa'ang mi 'gal te/ 'di ninyan thos la sogs pa thun mong gi gdul bya rnams la chos 'khor skor ba'i mchog gi sprul sku rnams sprul pa'i gzhi yin pas de ltar gsungs pa'i phyir ro/ /spyir theg chen kho na'i khyad chos dag pa'i zhing sprul sku'i zhing khams su gyur pa la'ang mchog dman gnyis yod de/ byang sems 'phags pa gtso che ba'i dge rtsa las grub pa bde ba can la sogs pa ni khams gsum du mi gtogs pa'i dag zhing rang dbang can yin la/ 'di ni gzugs khams su gtogs par bshad pas ma dag pa'i zhing la brten pa dang*/ lang gshegs las/ lha yi pho brang 'og min pa'o/ /zhes kyang gsungs pas dbye ba phyed dgos par bzhed do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Wheel of Time Tantra states:
A transcendent conqueror who resides in the pure domains
and other heavens does so for the pious attendants’ sake.
The “pure domains” mentioned here are identical with that [Unsurpassed Realm] just described. When discourses state that [Unsurpassed Realm as the place of enlightenment] is not situated among the pure domains, their underlying intent is to identify that realm as not among the five pure domains taught in the pious attendants’ collected teachings. In general however, it is not wrong to regard [Unsurpassed Realm as the place of enlightenment] as part of the pure domains. It is not contradictory to refer to it both as exalted bodhisattvas’ exclusive experiential domain and as existing for the pious attendants’ sake, since [Unsurpassed Realm] provides the basis for the emanation of the supreme manifest bodies who turn the teachings’ wheel for ordinary disciples, including the pious attendants.
In general, pure realms that are realms of enlightenment’s manifest body (a special feature of the great way) have two kinds—sublime pure realms and lesser pure realms. Realms such as Blissful which are created mainly by exalted bodhisattvas’ roots of virtue constitute independent pure realms and do not belong to the wheel of life’s three realms. In this case, [Unsurpassed Realm] is explained as part of the form realm; thus, it is based upon an impure realm. The Journey to Lanka Discourse states:
The palace of the gods is the Unsurpassed Realm.
This statement implies that it must be classified [as a lesser pure realm].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
ston pa mngon par rdzogs par 'tshang rgya ba'i bzhed pa tha dad kyi skabs gnyis pa'i 'grel pa'o// //
</d>
<d e="2">
*
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="skabs gsum pa">
[sprul pa'i sku'i mdzad pa bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Chapter 3">
3. The Buddha’s Twelve Deeds
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
!_skabs gsum pa sprul pa'i sku'i mdzad pa bshad pa la gsum/ mdzad pa'i tshul spyir bshad pa/ mdzad pa bcu gnyis bye brag tu bstan pa/ theg pa che chung gi rnam dbye 'phros don du smos pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This chapter has three parts: (1) a general explanation of the Buddha’s deeds, (2) a presentation of each of the twelve deeds, and (3) a supplementary explanation to distinguish between the great way and lesser way views of the Buddha’s deeds.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
dang po [I. mdzad pa'i tshul spyir bshad pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
A General Explanation of the Buddha’s Deeds [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
mchog gi sprul sku'i mdzad pa brgya la sogs/ /thun min don thob dbang gis tshad med kyang*/ /
thun mong la grags mdzad pa bcu gnyis te/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
[Various accounts relate] one hundred or other numbers of deeds enacted by the sublime manifest body.
There are countless perspectives, including that of the extraordinary [way] and conclusions [based on inference].
However, an account of twelve deeds is prevalent.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sangs rgyas kyi rnam thar dang phrin las ni nam mkha' ltar rgya che bas 'phags pa rnams kyi spyod yul du'ang ma gyur na so skye'i blo yis phyogs tsam yang dpog pa lta ci smos/ 'on kyang sangs rgyas kyi zhing 'dir mchog gi sprul pa'i sku'i rnam par rol pa gdul bya thun mong du snang ba las brtsams te mdzad pa'i tshul 'di lta bu'o zhes gtam du gleng ba'i gzhir gyur pa yin pas/ mdo sde rin po che rnams las 'phags bod kyi mkhas pa rnams kyis gtso che ba dag bsdus te mdzad pa'i rnam grangs brgya rtsar bshad pa la sogs pa dang*/ thun mong ma yin pa theg pa chen po dang sngags kyi tshul las 'byung ba dang*/ rjes dpag gi rigs pas don thob tu 'jog par 'os pa sogs tshad med pas mtha' gcig tu sangs rgyas kyi mdzad pa 'di kho na'o zhes kha tshon gcod par mi nus kyang*/ theg pa che chung gi gdul bya thun mong la yongs su grags pa ni mchog gi mdzad pa bcu gnyis zhes bya ste/ de'ang rgyud bla ma las/ thugs rje chen pos 'jig rten mkhyen/ /'jig rten kun la gzigs nas ni/ /skye ba mngon par skye ba dang*/ /dga' ldan gnas nas 'pho ba dang*/ /lhums su 'jug dang bltams pa dang*/ /bzo yi gnas la mkhas pa dang*/ /btsun mo'i 'khor 'gyes rol pa dang*/ /nges 'byung dka' ba spyod pa dang*/ /byang chub snying por gshegs pa dang*/ /bdud sde bcom dang rdzogs par ni/ /byang chub chos kyi 'khor lo dang*/ /mya ngan 'das par gshegs mdzad rnams/ /yongs su ma dag zhing rnams su/ /srid pa ji srid gnas par ston/ /ces gsungs pa ltar ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Buddha’s liberation and enlightened activity are as vast as the sky, and transcend the experiential domain of even exalted bodhisattvas. There-fore, it goes without saying that ordinary beings’ minds can fathom only a fraction of them. Nevertheless, the sublime manifest body’s display in this buddha realm appeared in common to his disciples; their oral reports based on their experience—“He acted in this way”—provided the basis for [later] accounts. Scholars of India and Tibet gathered the main [stories of the Buddha’s] deeds from the precious discourses and recounted them in an enumeration of one hundred, or other number of deeds. In addition, countless other versions exist, such as those appearing in the extraordinary great way system or in systems of secret mantra, and those based upon valid deductions of logical inference. Therefore, to come to an unequivocal conclusion—“These alone are the Buddha’s deeds!”— is impossible. Nevertheless, the account prevalent among the great and lesser ways’ disciples in common is called “the twelve sublime deeds.” The Highest Continuity states:
With supreme compassion, he knew the world
And looked upon all worlds.
Without having stirred from the body of ultimate enlightenment,
[He demonstrated] myriad [forms] that had the nature of emanations:
He took manifest birth,
Moved from Joyful Heaven,
Entered the womb, and was born.
He became skilled in arts,
Enjoyed the pleasures of his circle of queens,
Then became disillusioned and practiced austerities.
Having traveled to Heart of Awakening, He subdued hordes of demons and attained perfect awakening.
He turned the wheel of Dharma,
And passed beyond sorrow.
In very impure realms,
He will display these deeds for as long as existence endures.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="II">
[II. mdzad pa bcu gnyis bye brag tu bstan pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="II">
A Presentation of Each of the Twelve Deeds [II]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la dga' ldan gyi gnas nas 'pho ba sogs bcu gnyis rim par 'chad pa'i
</d>
<d e="2">
This section presents each of the Buddha’s twelve deeds in order, starting with his movement from Joyful Heaven:
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
dang po [A] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
The First Deed [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
dga' ldan gnas su dam pa tog dkar pos/ /chos sgo brgya bstan gzigs pa rnam lngas 'phos/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Sacred White Crown taught the hundred approaches to the teachings in Joyful Heaven.
Seeing the five visions, he departed.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bdag cag gi ston pa 'di sangs rgyas 'od srung gi spyan sngar bram ze'i khye'u bla mar gyur nas tshangs par spyod pa spyad de dga' ldan gyi gnas su lha'i bu dam pa tog dkar po zhes bya ba skye ba gcig gis thogs pa'i byang chub sems dpar sku 'khrungs pa yan chad skye ba mngon par skye ba'i sprul pa'i skus byang chub kyi spyod pa rdzogs nas/ mchod pa'i rol mo las gzhan don du bskul ba'i sgra gsan pa na chos kyis mtho ba zhes bya ba'i khang bzang du byang chub sems dpa' rang dang skal ba mnyam pa rnams dang bka'i bgro ba mdzad cing chos ston pa'i gnas su/ dad pa ni chos snang ba'i sgo ste bsam pa mi phyed par 'gyur ro zhes pa la sogs pa chos snang ba'i sgo rgya rtsa brgyad bstan nas thod dang cod pan byams pa'i dbu la bzhag nas khyod ni nga'i 'og tu mngon par rdzogs par 'tshang rgya bar 'gyur ro zhes lung bstan cing dga' ldan du chos ston pa po'i rgyal tshab tu dbang bskur nas gzigs pa rnam pa bzhi'am lnga yis 'jig rten la gzigs nas dpyid zla tha chung skar ma sogs nya ba'i tshes bco lnga rgyu skar rgyal dang ldan pa'i dus sbyor la dga' ldan gyi gnas nas 'pho bar mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In Buddha Guardian of the Light’s presence, our teacher became the spiritual master of brahmin children and engaged in the discipline of pure conduct. He was born in Joyful Heaven as a god named Sacred White Crown, a bodhisattva with only one lifetime remaining [before full enlightenment]. Until that rebirth [in Joyful], his manifest births in emanated forms brought to completion his conduct as a bodhisattva. [In Joyful Heaven,] when he heard sounds from offered music encouraging him to work for others’ benefit, he conferred with bodhisattvas equal to himself in fortune, in the mansion called Enhanced by the Teaching. In that site for the teachings, he presented one hundred and eight approaches to illuminate the Dharma, including “faith, the illuminating approach to the teachings that produces unwavering resolve.”
He then placed a turban and crown on the head of Bodhisattva Loving-Kindness (Maitreya), and foretold: “After me, you shall gain manifest and complete enlightenment,” thereby empowering Loving-Kindness as his regent, presenter of the teachings in Joyful. Having seen the world with the four or the five visions [listed below in “The Second Deed”], he departed from Joyful Heaven on the full moon of the third lunar month [literally: the last spring month, on the fifteenth day], at the conjunction of the constellation Pushya.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
gnyis pa [B] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
The Second Deed [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
'dzam gling tshe lo brgya par yul dbus su/ /rgyal rigs yab dang sgyu 'phrul lhums su zhugs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
In a central country, when the life span [of humans] in the Land of Jambu was one hundred years,
He entered Mahamayadévi’s womb. His father was of the royal caste.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang mi'i gling gzhan gsum las khyad par du 'phags pa dzam+bu'i gling*/ tshe lo brgyad khri pa yan chad longs spyod kyi 'byor pa che bas yid 'byung bar dka' zhing*/ lo brgya pa man chad kyang snyigs ma lnga ha cang bdo bas mi khom par snang bas de dag gi skyon med pas skye dgu gdul sla bar gyur pa'i dus tshe lo brgya pa/ rtsod dus la ltos te yul gyi skyon gyi cha nas smad du med pa dbus 'gyur 'chang gi yul/ 'jig rten 'dir res 'ga' rgyal rigs dang res 'ga' bram ze'i rigs gtso bor bkur ba las da lta rgyal rigs bkur bas mang bkur gyi rgyal brgyud rigs phun sum tshogs pa'i yon tan drug cu rtsa gzhis brgyan pa yab rgyal po zas gtsang ma dang*/ yum yang bud med kyi yon tan sum cu rtsa gnyis kyis brgyan pa lha mo sgyu 'phrul chen mo la gzigs nas/ glang po che'i phru gu thal kar mche ba drug pa'i tshul gyis yum gso sbyong blangs pa'i glo g.yas par zhugs nas lhums su tsan+dan gyi khang bu brtsegs par byis pa zla drug lon pa'i tshad tsam pa na bza' dang bcas pa skyil mo krung gis bzhugs te stong gsum gyi zil dngar ro bcud tshangs pa chen pos phul ba bzhes nas sku lus brtas par mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
[The future Buddha saw] the Land of Jambu, an especially exalted land compared to the other three continents [of this world-system] inhabited by human beings.
He saw that during the period human life span increases to eighty thousand years, the wealth of enjoyments is so abundant that disillusionment with life is difficult. When [the maximum possible] life span decreases under a hundred years, the five degenerations’ extreme spread makes human life one without leisure. A period free from those drawbacks, during which it would be easy to guide many beings, is the time that the human life span is one hundred years.
He saw that the region holding a central position [India] would not become as debased [as others] with faults that arise in other countries due to the era of conflict.
He saw that in this world the royal caste is sometimes the most honored [among castes]; at other times, it is the brahmin caste. At the time, the royalty [enjoyed the greater] respect.
Thus, [the future Buddha] saw his father, King Shuddhodana, who descended from the royal line of [the wheel-monarch] King Honored by Multitudes and whose clan was adorned with sixty-four magnificent qualities; and he saw his mother, the great Mahamayadévi, adorned with the thirty-two qualities of a woman [who will give birth to a buddha].
Having seen these circumstances, [the future Buddha] took the form of a white elephant calf with six tusks and entered his mother’s right side while she observed [the eight precepts] of purification and restoration. In her womb, within a tiered palace of sandalwood, he sat cross-legged and clothed, the size of a six-month-old infant. The god Great Pure One offered him delicious and nutritious nectar dew from the three-thousandfold cosmos; he ate it and his body grew strong.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de la gzigs pa bzhi ni/ gling dang dus dang yul dang rigs te gong du smos pa ltar la/ gzigs pa lnga ni/ rgyal rigs dang*/ yul dbus dang*/ tshe lo brgya pa'i dus/ shAkya'i rigs brgyud/ byang chub sems dpa' zla ba bcur lhums su 'dzin par nus pa'i yum ste lnga la gzigs pa lung dang mngon 'byung nas gsungs shing*/ snyigs ma lnga ni/ tshe dang*/ dus dang*/ lta ba dang*/ sems can dang*/ nyon mongs pa'o/ /de yang tshe'i snyigs ma dang dus kyi snyigs mas srog dang yo byad rgud par byed/ nyon mongs pa dang lta ba'i snyigs mas dge ba'i phyogs rgud par byed/ sems can gyi snyigs mas gzugs rgud par byed cing*/ gzhan yang nad med pa dang*/ stobs dang*/ blo dang*/ brtson 'grus dang*/ bsam gtan nyams par byed pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The four visions, as mentioned above, are those of continent, time, region, and clan. The five visions as they are found in scripture and in histories are those of the caste of royalty, a central region, a period when the life span is one hundred years, the lineage of the Shakya clan, and a mother who can carry the Bodhisattva in her womb for ten months.
The five degenerations are those of life span, time, views, sentient beings, and afflictive emotions. Degeneration of life span and time causes vitality and property to deteriorate. Degeneration of afflictive emotions and views causes virtuous tendencies to decline. Degeneration of sentient beings causes their physical form to deteriorate; moreover, their health, strength, intelligence, diligence, and concentration decline.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="C">
gsum pa [C] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="C">
The Third Deed [C]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
ngo mtshar mtshan ma bye ba snyed dang bcas/ /lum+bi nI yi tshal du don grub bltams/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Accompanied by ten million marvelous signs,
Siddharta was born in Lumbini Grove.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
lhums su zla ba bcu tshang bar bzhugs pa'i tshe lha mi khrag khrig sum cu rtsa drug theg pa gsum la smin par mdzad de bltams pa'i snga ltas sum cu rtsa gnyis dang*/ gling chen po bye ba phrag bzhi'i dbus su ashwat+tha'i ljon pa skye ba dang*/ gling phran rnams su tsan+dan gyi tshal skye ba dang*/ ser skya'i grong gi khor yug tu bde ba'i 'byor pa tshad med pa rang bzhin gyis 'byung ba sogs ngo mtshar ba'i mtshan ma bye ba khrag khrig 'bum phrag snyed kyis zhing thams cad yongs su gtams pa dang bcas/ lum+bi nI'i skyed mos tshal du dbo zla'i tshes brgyad rgyu skar rgyal dang ldan pa'i dus su yum la gnod pa med par dku g.yas brtol te mtshan dpe'i dkyil 'khor gsal ma thag tshangs pa dang brgya byin la sogs pa lha klu rnams kyis mchod cing bsnyen bkur/ phyogs bzhir zhabs kyis goms pa bdun bdun bor te stong chen po'i sems can thams cad dbugs dbyung ba'i gsung dbyangs phyung*/ yab rgyal pos bltams pa'i ngo mtshar las brtsams te gzhon nu don thams cad grub pa zhes bya ba'i mtshan phul/ ser skya'i gzhir ma ma sum cu rtsa gnyis kyis bskyed bsrings/ shAkya gtum po gzu lum can rnams kyi nang du thub pa bzhin gnas pas mtshan gnyis pa shAkya thub pa zhes btags/ shAkya rnams kyi lha gnod sbyin shAkya 'phel sogs 'jig rten skyong ba thams cad kyis zhabs la phyag byas pas yab kyis mtshan gsum pa lha'i yang lha zhes pa btags/ drang srong nag po nyon mongs med kyis sangs rgyas su 'gyur ba lung bstan to/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
During the time [the future Buddha] stayed a full ten months in the womb, he brought thirty-six hundred billion gods and humans to spiritual maturity within the three Buddhist ways.
Thirty-two portents of his birth appeared. In the middle of [each of] forty million large continents, a holy fig tree sprouted, and on all lesser continents, a sandalwood grove grew. Around the town of Kapilavastu, immeasurable riches of happiness naturally arose; in these and other ways, ten million trillion marvelous signs completely filled all realms.
In Lumbini Grove at the time of the constellation Pushya, on the eighth day of the second lunar month, he emerged from his mother’s right side without harming her. As soon as the sacred circle of his body’s marks and signs of physical perfection were apparent, gods and nagas, including Brahma and Shakra, made offerings and paid homage to him. Taking seven steps in each of the four directions, he uttered melodious words of encouragement to all sentient beings in the thousandfold universe. Since his birth began with marvels, his father the king offered him the name Youth who Accomplishes All Wishes.
He was raised in Kapilavastu, nourished by thirty-two wet nurses. Since he dwelt as the most capable amidst the fierce and impetuous Shakyas, he was given a second name, Shakyamuni (mighty one of the Shakyas). All worldly protectors, including the Shakya patron-god, the noxious spirit Increase of the Shakyas, bowed at his feet. Thus, the king conferred a third name to his son, God of Gods. Seer Krishna Asita foretold that [the child] would become a buddha.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="D">
bzhi pa [D] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="D">
The Fourth Deed [D]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
yig rtsis ri mo 'phong stobs brtag dpyad gtam/ /lugs mang sgyu rtsal bzo yi gnas la mkhas/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
He excelled in many aspects of culture and athletics: Composition, mathematics, art, archery, tests of strength, analysis, and rhetoric.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
byang chub sems dpa' shes bya'i gnas thams cad kyi mthar son kyang gdul bya grangs med pa smin pa'i slad du yi ge slob pa'i grwar byon te yig mkhan kun gyi bshes gnyen las slob pa ltar mdzad cing des ming tsam yang ma thos pa mang po bstan pa dang*/ dgung lo bcu drug rdzogs pa na shAkya lag na be con gyi bu mo lha mo dpal chen mo'i sprul pa sa 'tsho ma rgyal ba'i ru mtshon du bzhag nas shAkya bzhon nu lnga brgya dang rtsal 'gran pa'i thog mar rtsis pa chen po shAkya srid sgrub dbang du btsugs te grangs kyi gnas 'gran pa la dpang po dang bcas pa kun gyis byang chub sems dpa' cha tsam la'ang 'gran par ma nus shing*/ de bzhin du ri mo'i du byed dang*/ 'phong dang stobs dang brtag dpyad dang gtam dang rkyal dang bong dang 'degs mchongs la sogs pa lugs srol shin tu mang po'i sgyu rtsal dang bzo'i gnas yod do cog la shin tu mkhas pas sus kyang 'gran zla med par 'gyur te/ lhas byin la sogs pa rigs dang stobs kyi nga rgyal can rnams kyang 'dul bar mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Although the Bodhisattva had previously perfected all fields of knowledge, he went to school in order to bring innumerable disciples to full spiritual maturity. Appearing to train under the grammarian Vishvamitra, he revealed many subjects the names of which his teacher had never heard.
When [the Bodhisattva] reached sixteen years of age, he entered a contest of skills with five hundred Shakya youths. The prize to the winner was to be [the hand in marriage of] Gopa, an emanation of Great Glorious Goddess, and daughter of Shakya Dandapani. For the initial contest, the esteemed mathematician Shakya Arjuna was appointed as judge. No one competing in mathematics, including the judge, could equal even a fraction of the Bodhisattva’s expertise. Similarly, he showed exceptional talent in all subjects in very many aspects of culture and athletics—including art, archery, tests of strength, analysis, rhetoric, swimming, racing, and jumping. In all of these, no one could rival him. He also subdued those proud of their caste and strength, such as Dévadatta.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="E">
lnga pa [E] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="E">
The Fifth Deed [E]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
yon tan kun tshang sa 'tsho grags 'dzin sogs/ /btsun mo drug khri'i 'khor rol smin par mdzad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
His enjoyment with Gopa, Yasodhara, and other women endowed with all qualities
Brought his circle of sixty thousand queens to spiritual maturity.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gzugs bzang dar bab dregs pa dang bral zhing gtong la dga' ba sogs bud med rin po che'i yon tan kun tshang ba sa 'tsho grags 'dzin/ ri dwags skyes te so so 'khor nyi khri dang bcas pa btsun mo drug khri'am brgyad khri bzhi stong gi tshogs kyis 'chi med kyi bdun sa lta bu'i glu dbyangs rol mo'i sgra la sogs pa bkod pa phul du byung bas mchod cing*/ de dag gi nang du rtse zhing rol pa sogs thabs la mkhas pa'i mdzad pas btsun mo'i 'khor de dag thams cad kyang byang chub tu yongs su smin par mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Gopa, Yasodhara, and Mrigaja were endowed with all the precious qualities of womanhood, such as an excellent body, youthfulness, freedom from arrogance, and delight in giving. Each had an entourage of twenty thousand, making a coterie of sixty thousand queens (or eighty-four thousand, according to some). They offered [the Bodhisattva] magnificent arrays of melodious songs, music, and so on, resembling those in the [divine realm’s] Assembly Place of Immortality. His acts of skillful means among these women, such as in play and enjoyment, brought his circle of queens to full spiritual maturity within awakening.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="F">
drug pa [F] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="F">
The Sixth Deed [F]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
rga na 'chi dang tshangs spyod gzigs sogs kyis/ /nges 'byung rab tu byung nas ngur smrig bzhes/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Seeing such things as aging, sickness, death, and a pure mendicant,
He felt renunciation, renounced home life, and accepted saffron [robes].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dgung lo nyer dgu pa la grong khyer gyi sgo bzhir rgas pa dang*/ na ba dang*/ 'chi ba dang*/ tshangs spyod rab tu byung ba rnams gzigs shing phyogs bcu'i rgyal ba rnams kyis glu dbyangs sil snyan gyi sgras bskul zhing byin gyis rlabs pa dang*/ rang nyid kyi smon lam gyi mthus rgyal srid btsun mo'i 'khor rnams la skyo ba'i tshul bstan te nges par 'byung ba'i thugs skyes pa na/ da ni zhag bdun la rab tu ma byung na 'khor los sgyur ba'i rgyal por 'gyur ro zhes mtshan mkhan rnams kyis lung bstan pa thos nas/ shAkya rnams kyis stobs ci yod pas mel tshe byas te bsrungs pa na/ tha skar zla ba'i nya'i mtshan mor grags 'dzin ma'i mngal du rdo rje sems dpa'i sprul pa sras sgra gcan 'dzin bzang po byin gyis brlabs te/ nam phyed na chibs bsngags ldan la chibs/ zhabs 'bring ba 'dun pa dang brgya byin la sogs lha bye ba phrag stong mang pos mchod cing nam mkha'i lam nas dpag tshad bcu gnyis kyi shar phyogs 'das pa yangs pa can du gshegs nas gtsug phud rang nyid kyis bcad de rab tu byung*/ lha yis phul ba'i na bza' ngur smrig bzhes/ 'dun pa chibs bcas slar log nas yab dang btsun mo rnams kyi mya ngan bsang*/ gtsug phud dang kA shi kA'i na bza' lha rnams kyis khyer te mchod pa chen pos mchod do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
At the age of twenty-nine, he saw at his city’s four gates an old man, a sick person, a corpse, and a pure mendicant who had renounced home life. The ten directions’ victorious buddhas encouraged him with the sounds of melodious songs and cymbals. The power of their blessings and his own aspirations made him show signs of disillusionment with the royal dominion and his circle of queens. When renunciation had risen in his mind, interpreters of portents foretold, “Now, if within seven days he does not become an ascetic, he will become a wheel-monarch.” Hearing this, the Shakyas did their utmost to watch over and guard him [within the palace].
On the night of the ninth lunar month’s full moon, he blessed Yasodhara’s womb with a son, Rahulabhadra, an emanation of Buddha Vajrasattva. At midnight, he mounted his horse Necklace. With his servant Chandaka and many tens of billions of gods, including Shakra, who made offerings, he traveled twelve leagues (about 120 miles) to the east, fl ying through the sky. Arriving at Vaishali, he cut off the hair crowning his head, and thus became a mendicant. He accepted saffron robes off ered by the gods.
Chandaka returned with the horse and relieved the anguish of his father and the queens. The gods carried away his hair and garments of the finest silk, and honored them with prodigious offerings.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="G">
bdun pa [G] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="G">
The Seventh Deed [G]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
srid rtse'i snyoms 'jug mngon mdzad chu klung ngogs/ /lo drug skyil krung gcig gis dka' ba spyad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
He actualized the meditative absorption of the pinnacle of existence.
On a river bank, he sat in the same cross-legged posture for six years and engaged in austerities.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
byang chub sems dpa' khyim nas khyim med par rab tu byung ba'i rjes su yangs pa can du gshegs te sgyu rtsal shes kyi bu ring 'phur dang*/ rgyal po'i khab tu rangs byed kyi bu lhag spyod gnyis las bsam gtan gyi gdams ngag nod cing de dag gi rtogs pa'i mthar thug ci'ang med pa dang yod min med min gyi skye mched de srid rtse'i snyoms 'jug mthar thug pa tshegs chung ngus mngon par mdzad kyang zag bcas nyer len dang bcas pa'i bsam gtan snyoms 'jug ting nge 'dzin rnams sun dbyung zhing des mi grol bar bstan pa dang*/ las kyi rgyu ba lung bstan cing log pa'i brtul zhugs can rnams kyang 'dun cing des mi grol bar bstan pa la sogs pa dgos pa mang po nye bar gzigs nas/ chu klung nai rany+dza na'i ngogs su lo drug tu skyil mo krung gcig gis 'das te/ rgya shug gi 'bru/ nas 'bru gcig_/til 'bru gcig rnams nyin rer gsol ba dang chu thigs gcig kyang mi gsol ba la sogs pa'i dka' ba spyad cing*/ lus ngag gi dka' thub la snying po med pas spyod pa des kyang byang chub rdzogs par mi nus par bstan pa'i phyir/ slar kha zas rags par gsol bas sku stobs dang ldan cing mdzes par gyur pas dge sbyong mdzes par mtshan du grags so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
After the Bodhisattva renounced home life and became a homeless mendicant, he met Arada, son of Kalama, at Vaishali; and Rudraka, son of Rama, at Rajgir. From these two, he received instructions on meditative concentration. With little difficulty, he actualized their greatest realization—the basis of perception of nothing whatsoever and the basis of perception neither having nor not having discernment, the final meditative absorption at the pinnacle of existence. However, he repudiated all states of meditative concentration or absorption accompanied by contaminated grasping, showing that they did not lead to liberation.
The Bodhisattva sought out those who affirmed that there are karmic causes [for liberation] and who aspired to follow misleading [austere] disciplines. Seeing that [he could fulfill] many purposes, such as showing that [such beliefs and practices] did not lead to liberation, he passed six years on the bank of the Nairanjana River in the same crossed-legged posture. He engaged in such austerities as eating daily only a single juniper berry, or a grain of barley, or a sesame seed, or not drinking even one drop of water. Since physical and verbal austerities are pointless, he showed that even such conduct could not lead to perfect awakening; thus, he again ate solid food. His body became imbued with strength and beauty: he was known by the name Handsome Ascetic.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="H">
brgyad pa [H] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="H">
The Eighth Deed [H]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
'o thug gsol nas mtshan dpe 'od du 'bar/ /rtswa yi stan bsnams byang chub snying por gshegs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
When he drank milk soup, the marks and signs of physical perfection appeared and he blazed with light.
Carrying a seat of grass, he proceeded to Heart of Awakening.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de nas phyag dar khrod kyi gos las chos gos sbyar mar mdzad pa bzhes shing grong mi dga' byed ma'i bu mo legs skyes ma la lhas lung bstan pa bzhin ba stong gi 'o ma lan bdun du nying khur byas pa'i 'o thug sbrang rtsi can gsol ma thag tu gser gyi mdog dang*/ 'od 'dom gang la sogs mtshan dpe rnams rab tu gsal zhing 'od du 'bar bar gyur cing*/ rtsa 'tshong bkra shis las rtsa bslangs te stan gyi phyir bsnams nas/ mi bskyod stabs dang dbang po'i mchod sdong 'dra/ /zhes pa la sogs pa'i stabs lnga bcu rtsa gcig gis byang chub snying por gshegs pa na/ sa gzhi thams cad 'khar ba'i snod bzhin du sgra 'byin/ stong gsum gyi bdag po tshangs pa dbang sgyur gyis 'jig rten 'di bkod pa chen pos kun nas brgyad pa la sogs pa lha rnams dang phyogs bcu'i byang chub sems dpa' rnams kyis phyogs bcu'i sangs rgyas kyi zhing mang por rang rang gi tshogs gnyis kyi stobs tshad med bkod pas brgyan/ sangs rgyas kyi zhing thams cad skyod pa'i 'od zer dpag tu med pas dmyal ba la sogs pa'i 'gro ba rnams dbugs dbyung zhing klu nag po bya ba tshe bskal par gnas shing dmus long du gyur pa/ sangs rgyas 'jig rten du byon pa'i tshe mig thob pa de'ang mig bye zhing snang ba mthong*/ tsA sha'i khyu rnams snyan par sgrogs shing mkha' la g.yas su bskor/ thub mchog nyid kyis kyang dus gsum gyi sangs rgyas kyi zhing yod do cog byang chub snying po'i rgyan bkod pa ji snyed pa rnams de nyid du snang bar mdzad/ rtsa'i rtse mo rnams nang du bstan nas bting ba'i steng du skyil mo krung bcas nas zhal shar du gzigs/ sku drang por bsrang*/ dran pa mngon du bzhag nas bzhugs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Bodhisattva put on religious robes he sewed together from discarded rags. Following the gods’ directive, Sujata, daughter of the townsman Nandika, prepared an extract of one thousand cows’ milk, seven times refined and sweetened with honey. As soon as the Bodhisattva drank this, all the marks and signs of physical perfection (a golden complexion, a full aureole of light, etc.) became vividly apparent, and he blazed with light.
He begged for grass from the grass-seller Svastika, and carried it for his seat. As he proceeded to Heart of Awakening showing fifty-one ways of movement (including “a steadfast gait” and “resembling Powerful God’s offering pillar”), the earth resounded like a bronze vessel. The gods, such as powerful Brahma, lord of the three-thousandfold cosmos, fully decorated this world with a supreme array, and the ten directions’ bodhisattvas each adorned the ten directions’ many buddha realms with infinite displays according to their strength of cultivation of merit and wisdom. Immeasurable shimmering light from all buddha realms relieved the sufferings of beings in the hells and other realms.
The blind naga Kalika, who lives for an eon and acquires sight when a buddha appears in this world, opened his eyes and saw. A flock of Indian jays, singing sweetly, circled clockwise in the sky. The supreme sage himself had a vision of all the beautiful displays of Heart of Awakening within every buddha realm of the three times. Having arranged the grass straws with the points turned inward, he sat in a cross-legged posture and gazed eastward. He straightened his body and settled into manifest mindful composure.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
dgu pa [I] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
The Ninth Deed [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
shin du mi bzad g.yon can bdud kyi sde/ /nyon mongs dang bcas byams pa'i mthu yis bcom/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
With the power of loving-kindness, he subdued the utterly enraged one And hordes of deceptive demons, along with the gods’ afflictive emotions.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de nas bdud las rgyal ba dang bdud ris kyi lha'i bu dge rtsa can rnams smin par mdzad pa'i slad du smin mtshams nas 'od zer spros te bdud kyi gnas g.yos shing bskul bas/ sdig can rang nyid kyis rmis ltas mi bzad pa mthong ba sogs 'jigs skrag sngangs shing shin tu mi zad pa'i sems skyes te/ dpag tshad brgyad cu'i khor yug gang ba'i dpung gi tshogs dran pa tsam gyis snying 'gas par nus pa'i bkod pa'jigs su rung ba dang*/ stong gsum kun nas g.yon can de 'dra bye ba phrag brgya rnams kyang lhan cig tu lhags te mtshon cha'i char phab cing gdug pa'i dbugs spros pas/ de dag thams cad byang chub snying po mdzes pa'i mchod sprin gyi bkod pa sha stag tu gyur nas mthu rdugs te/ bsod nams de tsam gyis thar pa mi thob pas bzhengs su gsol ba na/ bskal pa dpag tu med par tshogs gnyis bsgrubs shing mthar son pa'i dpang po sa'i lha mo 'khor dang bcas pas zhus/ slar sred ma dang dga' ma sogs bdud kyi bu mo rnams kyis kyang 'dod pa'i g.yo sgyus bslu bar brtsams kyang thugs g.yo bar ma nus te g.yon can bdud kyi sde 'khor dang bcas pa rnams tshar bcad cing*/ de dag las dge rtsa smin pa'i lha'i bu tshad med pa dag gi nyon mongs pa rnam par bcom ste byang chub tu smin par mdzad pa sogs mdor na byams pa'i ting nge 'dzin kho nas bdud kyi dmag mi 'khrugs phrag gcig byang chub kyi snying por bzhugs pa'i nam srod 'khor de nyid du btul bar mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Then, to defeat demons and to bring to spiritual maturity those demonic gods with propensities for virtue, the Bodhisattva cast light from the space between his eyebrows. This shook the demons’ realms and incited them. The evil one himself experienced ominous signs, such as terrifying omens in his dreams; his mind became filled with fear, panic, and utter rage. [An area of] eighty leagues around the Bodhisattva filled with hordes of armies so terrifying that the mere thought of them would cause one’s heart to burst. At the same time, one billion similar deceptive demons arrived en masse from all world systems. They hurled rains of weapons and exhaled noxious fumes. All of this, however, became only arrays of offering clouds, which beautified Heart of Awakening; [the demons] lost their power.
[The demons’ king taunted him saying,] “That much merit is not sufficient for you to attain liberation. Rise [from your meditation]!” [In response,] Earth Goddess and her retinue attested to witnessing [the Bodhisattva’s] practice and perfection of the two accumulations during countless eons.
The demons’ daughters—Craving, Pleasure, and others—tried to entice him with seductive illusions, but they were unable to disturb his mind. Thus, he vanquished hordes of deceptive demons with their retinues. Apart from them, he subdued the afflictive emotions of innumerable gods whose virtuous propensities had ripened, bringing them to the full maturity of awakening and other [positive states].
In summary, during the first watch of the night at Heart of Awakening he subjugated an army of one hundred thousand trillion demons with the meditative state of loving-kindness alone.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="J">
bcu pa [J] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="J">
The Tenth Deed [J]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
bsam gtan bden bzhi rten 'brel rim gzigs nas/ /rdo rje lta bus mngon par rdzogs byang chub/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
He successively saw [levels of] concentration, the four truths, and the links of interdependent causation.
With a vajra-like meditative state, he gained manifest, complete awakening.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
nam gyi gung la bsam gtan bzhi por rim gyis snyoms par zhugs/ lha'i spyan sogs mngon par shes pas bden pa bzhi dang*/ rten 'brel lugs 'byung lugs ldog gi rim pa legs par gzigs nas/ nam gyi cha smad skya rengs 'char ka rnga rdung ba'i dus su skyes bu'i khyu mchog kha lo sgyur ba bla na med pa des 'phags pa'i ye shes kyi stobs bskyed pas shes par bya ba dang mngon du bya ba gang ci'ang rung*/ de thams cad sems kyi skad cig gcig dang ldan pa'i shes rab kyis rig pa gsum thob cing*/ spang bya phra zhing phra ba'ang rdo rje lta bu'i ting nge 'dzin gyis bcom nas chos kun gyi dbyings su bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs pa'i byang chub tu mngon par rdzogs par sangs rgyas so/ /de'i nub mo kho nar grags 'dzin ma la sras sgra gcan zin dang*/ bdud rtsi zas kyi bu kun dga' bo'ang btsas shing zla ba sgra gcan gyis zin to/ /de nas de bzhin gshegs pa shing tA la bdun srid kyi nam mkha' la 'phags te/ lam gyi rgyun ni chad do zhes bya ba la sogs pa ched du brjod par mdzad/ stong gsum 'di'ang rnam pa drug tu g.yos shing phyogs bcu'i 'dren pa rnams kyis legs so gsungs nas chos kyi dgab pa bskur/ stong gsum gyi lha rnams kyis mchod cing bstod de
</d>
<d e="2">
At midnight, he successively entered absorption within the four levels of concentration. With clairvoyant sight (divine eyes, etc.), he saw clearly the four truths and the links of interdependent causation in their order of sequential unfolding as well as in their reverse order.
During the last watch of the night, at daybreak when drums are sounded, the sublime one among humanity, our unsurpassed guide, developed the strength of exalted beings’ wisdom. Thus, he gained the three forms of awareness through the sublime insight that encompasses in a single instant of mind all that is to be known and all that is to be achieved. His vajra-like meditative state subdued even the most subtle trace of what is to be relinquished. Within the basic space of all phenomena, he gained unsurpassable, full, and complete awakening, manifest and perfect enlightenment.
On that very night, during a lunar eclipse, Rahula was born to Yasodhara, and Ananda was born the son of Amritodana.
The Transcendent Buddha rose seven palm trees’ height into the sky and declared, “The continuous path [of the wheel of life] has been cut!” The three-thousandfold cosmos trembled in six ways and [enlightened] guides in the ten directions proclaimed, “Excellent!,” delivering the joy of the Dharma. The gods of the three-thousandfold cosmos showered homage and praise upon him.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
zhag bdun du skyil krung ma bshigs par byang chub kyi shing la gzigs nas bsam gtan gyi bde bas dgyes par mdzad/ bdun phrag gnyis par stong gsum rgyang ring du 'chag_/bdun phrag gsum par byang chub kyi snying po la spyan mi 'dzum par gzigs/ bdun phrag bzhi par shar nub kyi rgya mtsho'i bar du mi ring bar 'chag_/bdun phrag lnga par klu btang bzung gi gnas su bzhugs/ bdun phrag drug pa la de nas shing n+ya gro d+ha'i drung du bzhud/ bdun pa'i tshe shing sgrol rgyu'i drung du bzhugs pa na lhas bskul te tshong pa ga gon dang bzang po gnyis kyis bsod snyoms kyi thog mar phul ba la rgyal chen bzhis rdo'i lhung bzed bzhi phul ba gcig tu byin gyis brlabs par blangs nas gsol te/ lha yi bkra shis don grub cing*/ /sogs kyi bkra shis mdzad nas sangs rgyas su lung bstan to/ /theg pa chen po'i lugs su 'di dag gi skabs su bkod pa bsam gyis mi khyab pa dang*/ zhag bdun phrag bdun gyi skabs su sangs rgyas phal po che'i chos kyi sgo 'byed pa sogs thun mong ma yin pa'i tshul ches mang ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Buddha remained facing the tree of awakening, not breaking his cross-legged posture for a period of seven days, jubilant in the exaltation of meditative concentration. During the second week, he journeyed far within the three-thousandfold cosmos. During the third week, he gazed unblinking at Heart of Awakening. During the fourth week, he traveled to the nearby eastern and western oceans. During the fifth week, he dwelt at the residence of the naga Mucilinda. During the sixth week, he moved from there to the foot of a banyan tree. During the seventh week, the Buddha sat at the foot of the tree of liberation.
At this time, Trapusha and Bhallika, two merchants encouraged by the gods, offered him the first alms. The Four Great Kings offered four begging bowls made of stone which [the Buddha] blessed [so that they merged] to become a single bowl. The Buddha accepted [the offered food], ate it, then recited a prayer of auspicious fortune which begins with the words, “[You have] fulfilled the auspicious wishes of the gods.” He then foretold that [the two merchants] would become buddhas.
The great way system has very many extraordinary interpretations [of this period], including accounts of inconceivable [miraculous] displays at the time of these events, and during these seven weeks, his opening of the doctrine of The Flower Ornament Discourse.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="K">
bcu gcig pa [K] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="K">
The Eleventh Deed [K]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
tshangs sogs gsol btab nges dang ma nges gnas/ /drang nges chos kyi 'khor lo rim gsum bskor/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
At the request of Brahma and others, he taught in known and unknown places
Expedient and definitive meanings in three successive turnings of the wheel of Dharma.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
rdzogs pa'i sangs rgyas shing sgrol rgyu'i drung du bzhugs pa'i tshe rang gis brnyes pa'i chos zab mo de 'jig rten pa kun gyis mi rtogs par dgongs te/ zab zhi spros bral 'od gsal 'dus ma byas/ /bdud rtsi lta bu'i chos shig bdag gis rnyed/ /su la bstan kyang go bar mi nus pas/ /mi smra nags 'dab nyid du gnas par bya/ /zhes gsungs te thugs las chung ngur bzhugs pa na/ sangs rgyas kyi mthus tshangs pa gtsug phud can 'khor 'bum phrag drug cu rtsa brgyad kyi 'khor dang lhan cig tu 'ongs nas chos ston par gsol ba btab kyang ma gnang ba na/ brgya byin grogs su sbran te lan gsum du gsol ba btab pas/ gdul bya rnams kyi dbang po'i rim pa legs par gzigs te ma nges pa'i sems can rnams las brtsams te bdud rtsi'i sgo dbye bar zhal gyis bzhes pa na/ de bzhin gshegs pas chos kyi 'khor lo bskor ro zhes pa'i sgra tshangs ris kyi bar du grags so/ /de nas wa ra NA sir bsod snyoms mdzad cing drang srong lhung ba ri dwags kyi nags su gshegs pa'i tshe lnga sde bzang pos mdun bsus te de dag tshur shog gis dge slong gi dngos por gyur nas/ sa phyogs der seng ge'i khri chen po stong byung ba dang khri
dang po gsum la bskor ba mdzad cing khri bzhi pa la skyil mo krung gis bzhugs pa'i tshe phyogs bcu'i 'jig rten du snang ba chen pos khyab pa dang chos nyan par skul ba'i sgra'ang byung ba na/ lha'i bu byang chub sems dpa' sems bskyed ma thag tu chos kyi 'khor lo bskor ba zhes bya bas dzam+bu chu gser las grub pa'i 'khor lo rtsibs stong pa phul ba sogs byang chub sems dpa' dang lha dpag tu med pa dag kyang 'dus pa la chu stod zla ba'i tshes bzhir bden pa gzhi'i ngo bo dang*/ bya ba dang 'bras bu'i tshul gyis lan gsum du bzlas te rnam pa bcu gnyis su bskor ba'i chos bstan pas lnga sde bzang pos dgra bcom thob/ 'jig rten na dkon mchog gsum gyi thog ma byung*/
</d>
<d e="2">
During the time the perfect Buddha sat beneath the tree of liberation, he thought that no worldly being could realize the profound understanding he had attained. Thus, he said,
Deep, tranquil, unformulated, non-composite clear light:
This ambrosia-like reality I have gained
Is unfathomable by anyone I might teach.
Thus, I will dwell at the forest’s edge in silence.
He sat alone with little activity in mind.
Through the Buddha’s power, Brahma with a tufted crown arrived with his retinue of sixty-eight hundred thousand, and beseeched him to teach the Dharma, but the Buddha did not do so. Brahma then called on Shakra for assistance. After their third request, the Buddha, clearly seeing his disciples’ different capabilities, promised to open the door of ambrosia-like teachings, beginning with teachings to any kind of sentient being. The tidings, “The Transcendent Buddha will turn the wheel of Dharma!” resounded as far as Brahma’s realm.
The Buddha then went to seek alms in Varanasi. When he arrived at Deer Park, Descent of the Sages, the five excellent ones came to greet him. The Buddha called them forth, and they thereby became true fully ordained monks.
At that place, one thousand magnificent lion-supported thrones appeared. The Buddha circumambulated the first three; when he sat in cross-legged posture on the fourth, a great light spread throughout worlds in the ten directions, and a sound arose calling beings to listen to his teachings. A god called Bodhisattva Who Turned the Wheel of the Teachings upon Developing the Intention to Attain Awakening presented him with a one thousand-spoked wheel made of gold from the Jambu River. He and countless other bodhisattvas and gods assembled.
On the fourth day of the sixth lunar month, the Buddha taught the four truths in three enunciations: [he first explained] their essence, then their function, and finally their result. In this way, he presented that cycle of teaching in twelve aspects. As a result, the five excellent ones attained [the state of] arhat (foe-subduer), and for the first time the three jewels (Buddha, Teaching, and Spiritual Community) appeared in this world.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de nas rim par ri bo ga ya dang*/ spos ngad ldang*/ rgyal po'i khab/ bya rgod phung po'i ri/ mnyan yod rgyal byed kyi tshal/ ko sa la/ ser skya'i gzhi/ yangs pa can gyi grong khyer la sogs pa nges pa dang*/ lha dang klu'i gnas/ rdo rje rin po che'i khang pa sogs ma nges pa'i gnas ci rigs pa rnams su drang ba dang nges pa'i don las brtsams te thog mtha' bar du dge ba'i chos kyi 'khor lo chen po rim pa gsum du bskor/ mchog zung la sogs pa 'khor rnam pa bzhi bgrang ba las 'das pa 'bras bu rnam pa bzhi la bkod/ theg pa chen po'i rigs can gyi lha dang mi grangs med pa byang chub tu lung bstan/ mnyan du yod par 'jig rten dang 'jig rten las 'das pa'i cho 'phrul chen po bstan/ sum cu rtsa gsum du yum sgyu 'phrul chen mo'i ched du dbyar gnas par mdzad cing grong khyer gsal ldan du lha las babs/ dpal ldan 'bras spungs kyi mchod rten la sogs par gdul bya thun mong ma yin pa rnams la sngags kyi theg pa bstan pa sogs 'dul bzhi'i cho 'phrul bsam brjod kyi yul las 'das shing*/ mdor na dgung lo nyer dgur khab tu bzhugs/ lo drug tu dka' ba spyad/ dgung lo so lnga par sangs rgyas nas dgung lo brgyad cu tham pa'i bar dbyar gnas pa bzhi bcu rtsa lnga mdzad nas chos kyi 'khor lo bla na med pa bskor to/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Beginning with instruction in the expedient and definitive meanings [of Dharma], the Buddha turned the great wheel of Dharma—virtuous in the beginning, middle, and end—in three stages. He taught in known locations—Gaya Peak, Gandhamadana Mountain, Rajgir, Vulture Peak, Shravasti, Jetavana, Kosala, Kapilavastu, and the city of Vaishali—as well as in many places unknown [to humans], such as realms of gods and nagas, and the precious vajra palace.
The Buddha led innumerable disciples of the four kinds, including the sublime pair, to the attainment of four results. He foretold the awakening of countless humans and gods who had affinity with the great way. In Shravasti, he displayed supreme miracles, both mundane and supra-mundane. For his mother Mayadévi’s sake, he spent one summer retreat period in Heaven of the Thirty-three, then descended from the gods’ realm [back to earth] at Sankashya. At glorious Treasure Mound Stupa and other places, the Buddha taught the secret mantra way to exceptional disciples. In these ways, his display of the four taming miracles was inconceivable and indescribable.
In summary, the Buddha stayed in his father’s royal residence until the age of twenty-nine. He practiced austerities during six years, and at the age of thirty-five he attained enlightenment. From then until his eightieth year, he conducted forty-five summer retreats and set in motion the highest wheel of the teachings.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="L">
bcu gnyis pa [L] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="L">
The Twelfth Deed [L]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
mi gnas mya ngan 'das pa'i tshul bstan cing*/ /sku gdung 'jig rten kun tu rgyas par mdzad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
He demonstrated unlimited transcendence of sorrow.
His relics spread throughout the world.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de ltar mdzad pa mthar phyin pa'i skabs sku tshe'i 'du byed ni btang*/ 'tsho ba'i 'du byed ni byin gyis brlabs nas ltas chen po snang bar gyur pa dang lhan cig grong khyer yangs pa can la sogs par rim gyis gshegs te slad ma'i dus chos dang chos ma yin pa rnam par dbye ba na/ mdo sde dang mthun/ 'dul ba la snang*/ chos nyid dang mi 'gal na ston pa'i bstan par zung zhig pa sogs gdams nas mgar ba'i bu tsun+da_ las bshos kyitha ma gsol te grong khyer rtsa can du shing sA la zung gi bar tha ma'i gzims khri la seng ge'i nyal stabs kyis bzhugs te snang ba'i 'du shes dang*/ dran pa dang shes bzhin gyi 'du shes dang*/ mya ngan las 'da' ba'i 'du shes thugs la mdzad/ kun dga' bo la ngo mtshar rmad du byung ba'i chos bzhi tshan gsum bstan cing zhal gyi gdams pa stsal/ dri za'i rgyal po rab dga' dang kun tu rgyu rab bzang sogs btul/ zla ba phyed phyed du so sor thar pa'i mdo 'don pas ston pa'i mdzad pa mdzad pa sogs gdams nas
</d>
<d e="2">
When the Buddha had completed these deeds, the composite factors [that sustained] his life span were spent. [At the request of some disciples,] he blessed the composite factors [that sustained] his life-force [and thereby extended his life]. Significant portents appeared, and he proceeded to such places as the city of Vaishali together with his followers. There, he counseled them to distinguish in the future between what is Dharma and what is not: what concurs with the [collection of] discourses, appears in the collection on discipline, and does not contradict the nature of reality should be accepted as the teacher’s doctrine.
[The Buddha] ate his last meal, offered by the blacksmith’s son, Chunda. Then, in Kushinagara, he reclined in the lion’s sleeping posture on his last bed, between a pair of sal trees. He then gave his attention to the perception of illumination, to the perception of recollection and mindfulness, and to the perception of transcending sorrow. He gave instructions to Ananda concerning the three groups of four marvelous teachings, and oral counsel. He converted the king of the celestial musicians [called] Gaiety, a wandering mendicant Subhadra, and others. Furthermore, he gave specific instructions on how to continue the teacher’s acts, such as [for the community of ordained persons] to recite The Individual Liberation Discourse every fortnight.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
lugs 'byung dang lugs ldog gi bsam gtan la snyoms par zhugs nas/ slar bsam gtan bzhi pa'i rab mtha' la brten nas/ zhi ba mi g.yo ba'i spyan dang ldan pa brnyes te mi gnas pa'i dbyings su mya ngan las 'das pa'i tshul bstan/ zhag bdun du lha dang mi'i mchod pa rgya chen pos mchod cing sku gdung gyad kyis dbu rgyan btags pa'i mchod rten gyi drung du spyan drangs te sa'i steng du zla med pa'i nyan thos chen po bzhi la sogs pas mchod cing me rang 'bar du gyur pas gdung rnams yungs 'bru lta bu'i ring bsrel gyi phung por gyur pa ma ga d+hA'i rgyal po ma skyes dgra dang*/ yangs pa can gyi li ts+tsha bI la sogs pa rnams kyis cha brgyad du bgos te so so'i yul du mchod rten btsigs shing dus ston chen por btsugs nas mchod pa rgya chen pos mchod/ tshems mche ba bzhi po sum cu rtsa gsum pa dang*/ grong khyer sgra sgrogs klu'i rgyal po sogs kyis so sor thob nas mchod/ ma skyes dgra'i gdung skal rnams phyis chos rgyal mya ngan med kyis blangs te dzam+bu'i gling du mchod rten bye ba nub gcig la bzhengs pa dang*/ ma 'ongs pa na de dag nor bu tog gi blo gros su gyur nas don mdzad pa sogs mdor na sku gdung yang 'jig rten kun tu rgyas shing 'phel bas sangs rgyas kyi mdzad pa mtha' yas pa mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Buddha then entered absorption within of each level of meditative concentration in ascending and reverse order, and [ascended] again to the farthest limit of the fourth level of concentration. Resting there, he attained unmoving tranquil vision, and within the unlimited basic space of phenomena, he demonstrated transcendence of sorrow.
For seven days, amidst vast offerings of gods and humans, his physical remains were carried to [a stupa known as] Stupa Adorned with a Crown Offered by the Mallas. The four great pious attendants, unequaled on earth, and others made offerings, and the pyre burst into flame spontaneously. His remains became a mass of relics resembling mustard seeds, which King Ajatashatru of Magadha, the members of the Licchavi clan of Vaishali, and others divided into eight parts. Each took a part to his respective region and built stupas to enshrine these relics. They consecrated the occasion with a great holy festival during which immense offerings were made.
The Buddha’s four canine teeth were distributed to Heaven of the Thirty-three, the naga king of the city of Ravana, and others, and they became objects of offering. The relics belonging to King Ajatashatru were later recovered by the Buddhist king Ashoka, who built ten million stupas throughout the Land of Jambu in one night. In the future, these [relics] became such [wonders] as the “Crown Jewel of Intelligence,” which aided beings. In brief, in these and other ways, the relics of the Buddha’s body were distributed throughout the entire world and they continue to increase. Thus, his deeds are endless.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="III">
gsum pa [III. theg pa che chung gi rnam dbye 'phros don du smos pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="III">
Supplementary Explanation to Distinguish between Great Way and Lesser Way Views of the Buddha’s Deeds [III]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
nyan thos lugs la cho 'phrul nyin gcig pa/ /theg chen lugs su nyin zhag bco lngas mtshon/ /
chos 'khor sku tshe'i tshad sogs 'dra min rlabs/ /che chung khyad par che yang thun mong gi_/
gdul byar snang rnams nyan thos dbang btsan pas/ /'chad dus rnam dbye ma 'dres phyed dgos la/ /
'dir ni sa bcu'i dbang phyug lung ltar bshad/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
According to the pious attendant system, the miracles occurred on the same day;
According to the great way system, in fifteen days.
This illustrates dissimilarities in explanations of cycles of
teaching, length of life, etc.
There is also a major difference in scope.
However, the pious attendant system presents the account
as witnessed in common by disciples, and it has become
prevalent.
Therefore, when recounting the Buddha’s deeds, [the two
systems] must be differentiated and unmixed.
Here, I have recounted the deeds according to a scripture by the sovereign bodhisattva of awakening’s tenth stage.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sangs rgyas kyi mdzad pa 'dul mdo las 'byung ba rnams theg pa che chung so so'i dbang gis mi mthun pa mang ste/ dper na nyan thos lugs la cho 'phrul chen po nyin gcig pa lung phran tshegs las bshad pa dang*/ theg chen pa rnams kyi lugs su nyin zhag bco lnga pa mdo sde mdzangs blun las 'byung bas mtshon te/ chos kyi 'khor lo bskor ba'i tshul dang*/ sku tshe'i tshad kyang thun mong du brgyad cu tham par bzhugs shing*/ nges don gyi gsung rab rnams las/ sangs rgyas mya ngan yongs mi 'da'/ /chos kyang nub par mi 'gyur te/ /zhes pa'i tshul rgya cher bshad pa sogs 'dra min dang*/ rlabs che chung gi khyad par shin tu che yang thun mong gi gdul bya yongs kyi ngor snang ba rnams ni nyan thos kyi lugs 'di yin pa'i phyir de nyid dbang btsan pas sor bzhag ste/ 'chad pa'i dus su'ang de gnyis rnam dbye ma 'dres par phyed par dgos kyi bsre 'dres su 'chad par bya ba ma yin la/ mdzad pa bcu gnyis kyi rnam grangs bgrang tshul yang 'phags pa klu sgrub kyis rin chen phreng bar gsungs pa dang*/ des mdzad par grags pa'i bstod rnying dang*/ bod 'dir mkhas pa dag gis sbyar ba ci rigs par snang ba las 'dir ni sa bcu'i dbang phyug rgyal tshab byams pa'i lung gong du drangs pa de'i rjes su 'brangs te dpal ldan dpa' bo gtsug lag phreng bas bstod pa'i tshigs su bcad pa sbyar ba dang mthun par bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Accounts of Buddha’s deeds as they appear in the collections on discipline and in the discourses diverge due to differences between the great
and lesser ways. To illustrate this, in the pious attendant system, the major miracles are said to have occurred [on the same day], as explained in Various Scriptures on Monastic Discipline. However, according to proponents of the great way system, the Buddha performed miracles over fifteen days, as related in The Discourse of the Wise and the Foolish. Different explanations exist regarding how the Buddha turned the wheel of the teachings, on the length of the Buddha’s life, and other points. According to the common view, he lived eighty years, but scriptures of definitive meaning teach another perspective in detail:
The Buddha does not transcend sorrow, Nor will the teachings disappear.
Major differences in scope exist between the great and lesser ways. However, since the pious attendant system records what all the Buddha’s common disciples witnessed, it has become prevalent and accepted. When [the Buddha’s deeds] are presented, the two perspectives must be differentiated and unmixed; composite, blended versions should not be taught.
How the twelve deeds are enumerated is stated by the noble Nagarjuna in The Precious Garland and in Ancient Praise (a text said to be by the same author), and in many books by Tibetan scholars. I have recounted here the deeds according to the praise in verse composed by the illustrious Pawo Tsuklak Trengwa, who derived his work from the text quoted above [The Highest Continuity] by the sovereign bodhisattva of awakening’s tenth stage, the regent Maitreya.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'dir rje btsun thams cad mkhyen pa tA ra nA tha'i gsung rab mdzad pa mthong ba don ldan las/ de bzhin gshegs pa'i rnam par thar pa sde snod gsum las byung mnyam yin yang*/ theg pa che chung gi dbye ba phyed dgos par snang ste/ 'phags pa rgya che rol pa las/ ston pa dga' ldan du bzhugs pa nas/ chos 'khor thog mar bskor ba'i bar rgyas par 'byung ba lta bu theg chen gyi lugs yin pas de'i rjes 'thud par 'dod na/ 'dus pa rin po che tog las 'byung ba'i mchog zung gi lo rgyus dang*/ dkon mchog brtsegs pa'i nang gi yab sras mjal ba'i mdo las 'byung ba'i lo rgyus dang*/ mdzangs blun nas bshad pa'i cho 'phrul chen po dang*/ mya ngan las 'das pa'i skor rnams myang 'das chen po las 'byung ba sogs/ mdor na theg chen gyi mdo kho na las kha bskang na shin tu legs par 'gyur la/ yang mngon par 'byung ba'i mdo dang*/ 'dul ba nas 'byung ba ni/ theg pa thun mong ba nyan thos kyi sde snod kyi lugs yin pas/ de la 'thud par spro na mdo sde las brgya pa dang*/ rtogs brjod brgya pa sogs theg dman gyi mdo sde thor bu ba rnams las 'byung ba rnams kho nas kha bskang na legs par 'gyur gyi/ gnyis po phan tshun gcig la gcig bsres na mi 'grig cing gnyis ka ma yin par 'gyur bas mi legs so/ /mdzangs blun dang dran pa nyer gzhag la sogs pa nyan thos kyi sde snod yin par phyogs 'di na grags 'dug kyang*/ yin pa ni nges par theg pa chen po'i sde snod nyid yin pas/ mdzangs blun las 'byung ba'i cho 'phrul chen po'i rnam gzhag ni/ theg chen nyid kyi lugs yin te/ de yang nyan thos lugs la cho 'phrul nyin gcig pa dang*/ theg chen lugs la zhag bco lnga yin no/ /des mtshon pa gzhan kun la yang mi 'dra ba'i khyad par shin tu mang ngo*/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The noble master all-knowing Taranata, in his work Meaningful to Behold, states:
Although the stories of the Transcendent Buddha’s liberation as they appear throughout the three collections are all equally [valid], we must distinguish between the great way and lesser way versions. The Vast Enjoyment Discourse, for instance, gives a detailed account of the events from the Buddha’s residence in Joyful Heaven until his first turning of the wheel of the teachings. Since this is a great way discourse, if one wishes to continue an account of the Buddha’s deeds, it would be best, in brief, to use as supplements sources that are exclusively great way discourses. These include the account of the outstanding pair of the Buddha’s disciples from The Concise Long Mantra of Precious Top Ornament; the accounts that appear in The
Reunion of Father and Son Discourse, from the collection The Noble Cluster of Jewels Discourse; the great miracles explained in The Discourse of the Wise and the Foolish; and the circumstances of his transcendence of sorrow in The Great Discourse of Transcendence of Sorrow.
The discourses from the collection on observed phenomena and in the collection on monastic discipline belong to the systems of the common Buddhist way—the collections of the pious attendants. Therefore, if one is interested in furthering their accounts, it is best to supplement them only with sources found in diverse lesser way discourses. These include The Discourse of One Hundred Actions and The Hundred Histories. It is unacceptable to mix the two, making them neither one nor the other, which is incorrect.
Here in Tibet, The Discourse of the Wise and the Foolish, The Great Discourse on Mindfulness, and others are considered to be part of the pious attendants’ collection, but in fact, they definitely belong to the great way collection. The presentation of the major miracles in The Discourse of the Wise and the Foolish is of the great way system: the pious attendant system states that there was [only] one day of miracles; the great way, fifteen days. This illustrates many marked differences among all other points [that prove the provenance of these books].
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de yang sangs rgyas 'jig rten du byon pa'i skabs kyi log lta can dang mu stegs byed dang tha na dud 'gro tshun chad yul nye ba na gnas shing rung ba rnams kun gyi thun mong du snang ba'i mdzad phrin ni/ theg pa thun mong lugs sam nyan thos lugs 'di yin la/ theg chen thun mong ma yin pa'i ched du bya ba'i gdul bya rnams kyi snang ngor la ji ltar shar ba'i tshul ni/ theg chen gyi mdo las 'byung ba rnams yin pas de dag la spyir yang rnam grangs mi 'dra ba dang*/ sgos su rlabs che chung gi khyad par cher yod pas/ tshul gnyis don la mi 'gal yang 'chad tshul ma 'dres par byed dgos la/ de'i phyir bod kyi phyogs 'dir thams cad mkhyen pa gnyis par grags pas kyang*/ mdzad pa bcu gnyis kyi dang po bcu gcig rgya rol dang bstun/ tha ma lung phran tshegs nas 'byung bas kha 'gengs mdzad de/ de ni shin tu 'grig par ma mthong la/ des mtshon pa'i gzhan yang mang ngo*/ /lugs de gnyis las spyir theg chen gyi lugs nyid rgya che ba dang*/ bsam gyis mi khyab pa'i ye shes kyi spyod yul dang*/ gdul bya mchog gi snang ngor yin pa dang*/ gsang ba chen po'i rnam par thar pa yin pa dang*/ theg chen pa rang nyid kyi mtho dma'i khyad par sogs rgyu mtshan du mas mchog yin mod/ 'on kyang skye bo kun gyi mthun snang du grub pa dang*/ sku tshe'i tshad dang*/ snga phyi'i dus dang*/ yul phyogs de dang der zhabs kyis gcags so ma gcags so zhes sogs dpyad pa sna tshogs pa 'jug pa'i gzhi ni lugs thun mong ba 'di kho na yin gyi/ theg chen lugs ni min te bsam gyis mi khyab pa'i spyod yul yin pas na/ yul dang*/ dus dang*/ mdzad pa rnams la 'di kho na'o zhes tshad bzung dka' ba'i phyir ro/ /de'i phyir gtam rgyud kyi sbyor ba 'chad pa'i tshul la theg pa thun mong gi lugs 'di nges par gnad che bar shes so/ /zhes gsungs so/ /sprul pa'i skus zhing 'dir mdzad pa bcu gnyis bstan par bshad pa skabs gsum pa'i 'grel pa'o// //
</d>
<d e="2">
The system of the common Buddhist way (or pious attendant system) gives the account of the Buddha’s activity and deeds in the world as they appeared in common to all who were in the vicinity of the Buddha’s presence and were apt [witnesses]—including those holding wrong views, non-Buddhists, or even animals. The great way discourses relate how the deeds appeared in the experience of disciples for whom the extraordinary great way was taught. As a result, [the two systems] have different enumerations of the deeds in general, and in particular, very marked differences in scope.
Therefore, although these two systems are not fundamentally contradictory, their styles of teaching must not be mixed. For this reason, I do not see as very acceptable [the account of the Buddha’s twelve deeds by] a master known in Tibet as the second omniscient one, since he explained the first eleven deeds according to The Vast Enjoyment Discourse and supplemented that record with the last deed according to The Minor Scripture on Discipline. This illustrates [a mixing of sources] that is prevalent.
Comparing the two systems’ [accounts of the Buddha’s twelve deeds], the great way’s account is superior to the pious attendant system for various reasons: it is vaster; it relates the domain of experience of inconceivable wisdom; it reflects the perceptions of sublime disciples; it relates the esoteric story of his liberation; the great way itself has different levels [of accounts], and so forth. Nevertheless, only the common system [of the lesser way] provides a basis for various points of enquiry, such as what existed in the common perception of all individuals [at that time], the Buddha’s life span, the chronology [of the events of his life], and assertions that the Buddha traveled to one place and did not travel to another.
The great way system cannot serve in that way. It is the domain of the inconceivable: it is difficult for it to provide set limits, such as, “These alone were the Buddha’s places of residence, historical period, and deeds.” Therefore, the system of the common Buddhist way is definitely of primary significance when writing history.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="skabs bzhi pa">
['od gsal rdo rje rtse mo'i lugs kyi sku dang zhing khams khyad par du dbye ba]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="Chapter 4">
4. Enlightenment’s Bodies and Pure Realms
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
!_skabs bzhi pa 'od gsal rdo rje rtse mo'i lugs kyi sku dang zhing khams khyad par du dbye ba la gnyis/ mtshams sbyar ba/ don rgyas par bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Chapter Four, a specific categorization of enlightenment’s bodies and pure lands, according to the clear light vajra pinnacle’s tradition, has two parts: (1) an introduction and (2) a full explanation of enlightenment’s bodies and pure lands.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="I">
dang po [I. mtshams sbyar ba] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="I">
An Introduction [I]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
theg mchog 'od gsal rdo rje rtse mo las/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
According to the highest way, clear light vajra pinnacle,
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
snga 'gyur gsang sngags rnying ma'i lugs su theg pa rim pa dgur grags pa thams cad kyi mchog gam mthar thug 'od gsal rdzogs pa chen po a ti yo ga rdo rje rtse mo'i rgyud dang gzhung lugs rnams las thun mong ma yin pa'i sku dang zhing khams kyi bkod pa 'di ltar du bshad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In the secret mantra Ancient tradition of the early translations, the highest point or culmination of what are known as the nine Buddhist ways is clear light great perfection, atiyoga, the vajra pinnacle. Great perfection’s tantras and textual traditions describe the extraordinary array of enlightenment’s bodies and pure realms as follows.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="II">
[II. don rgyas par bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="II">
A Full Explanation of Enlightenment’s Bodies and Pure Lands [II]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa la bzhi/ gdod ma'i mgon po mngon par byang chub nas zhing khams bkod pa'i tshul/ de'i rnam 'phrul rdo rje 'chang gis zhing 'dir zhi ba brnyes pa'i tshul/ de las gzugs sku gnyis kyi rnam par 'phrul pa snang tshul/ zhar byung bshad srol gzhan gyi gleng bslang ba'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has four parts: (1) how the original lord [Buddha Ever Excellent] attained manifest awakening, then created the pure realms; (2) how his emanation, Buddha Vajra Bearer, attained peace in this pure realm; (3) how Buddha Vajra Bearer’s two form bodies’ emanations appear; and (4) a supplement introducing other systems’ explanations of this subject.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="A">
[A. gdod ma'i mgon po mngon par byang chub nas zhing khams bkod pa'i tshul]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="A">
How the Original Lord Buddha Ever Excellent Created the Pure Realms [A]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la gnyis/ chos sku mngon par byang chub pa'i tshul/ de las rang snang gi zhing khams rgya mtsho bkod pa'i tshul lo/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) how the original lord [Buddha Ever Excellent] attained the body of ultimate enlightenment’s manifest awakening and (2) how Buddha Ever Excellent then created oceans of self-manifest pure realms.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
dang po [1. chos sku mngon par byang chub pa'i tshul] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
How the Original Lord Buddha Ever Excellent Attained the Body of Ultimate Enlightenment’s Manifest Awakening [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
'khor 'das gang yang ma phyes sngon rol tu/ /rang byung ye shes bde gshegs snying po ni/ /
gzhi las gzhi snang shar ba'i skad cig la/ /rang ngo shes pas gzhi thog rang grol te/ /
chen po gsum ldan kun bdag kun tu bzang*/ /gzhon nu bum sku'i zhing du nang gsal gyi/ /
phra ba'i ye shes thim la ma rmugs bzhugs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Prior to any division between the wheel of life and transcendent states,
There existed self-arisen wisdom, buddha-nature, the basis
of being.
At the moment the basis of being dawned as manifest
appearances,
[Ever Excellent] recognized them as his own and gained natural
liberation on the basis of being.
Endowed with threefold greatness, master of all,
Buddha Ever Excellent abides in the youthful vase body’s pure
realm—
Inwardly luminous subtle wisdom, indwelling but not obscured.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'khor ba dang mya ngan las 'das pa gang du'ang ma phyes pa'i sngon rol du/ srid zhi yongs la mnga' dbang sgyur ba'i ston pa kun tu bzang po nyid dbyings rang byung gi ye shes bde bar gshegs pa'i snying po gdod ma'i gzhi las gzhi snang du shar te gzhi las 'phags pa'i skad cig de nyid la rang snang du ngo shes pas rang byung rig pa'i ye shes nyid gzhi thob tu rang sar grol te/ spangs pa dang rtogs pa dang sems chen po gsum lhun grub tu ldan cing 'khor 'das kun bdag kun tu bzang po zhes bya ba rgyu'i theg pa bdag gis 'jug pa thams cad kyi dbyings su nye bar zhi ba'i 'gog pa la gnas par bshad pa'i stong rkyang tsam las ring du 'das pa'i tshul gyis/ lhun grub rin po che'i sbubs/ gdod ma'i zad sa ka dag chen po/ gzhon nu bum pa sku'i btsan sa zin te phyir snang gi yon tan thams cad mched pa'i gzhi'am rgyur gyur pa nang gsal phra ba'i ye shes thim la ma rmugs pa shel 'od nang du bsdus pa'i tshul can chos kyi sku'i rang bzhin du bzhugs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Prior to any division between the wheel of life and transcendent states, there existed the teacher who mastered all existence and quiescence, Buddha Ever Excellent. The basis of being dawned as manifest appearances from basic space, self-arisen wisdom, buddha nature, the original ground. At the very moment those appearances arose from the basis of being, [Ever Excellent] recognized them as his own manifestations; thus, his self-arisen wisdom of awareness was liberated on the basis of being, in its own ground. He was thereby spontaneously endowed with threefold greatness —renunciation, realization, and mind. Known as Ever Excellent, master of all the wheel of life and transcendent states, he far transcends mere emptiness alone, which is taught by adherents to cause-based spiritual ways to be abiding in the complete quiescence of cessation within the sphere of all [forms of meditative] equipoise.
Thus, Buddha Ever Excellent reached the unassailable state of the spontaneously present jeweled enclosure, the original place of resolution, supreme primordial purity, the youthful vase body. He abides in the nature of the body of ultimate enlightenment — the cause or basis for the unfolding of all externally appearing qualities—inwardly luminous subtle wisdom, indwelling but not obscured, like light gathered within a crystal.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
gnyis pa [2. de las rang snang gi zhing khams rgya mtsho bkod pa'i tshul] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
How Buddha Ever Excellent Created Oceans of Self-Manifest Pure Realms [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
de yi byin las rang snang ye shes zhing*/ /stug po bkod par rang snang longs spyod rdzogs/ /
rigs lnga'i tshom bu nges pa lnga ldan snang*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
His blessing [created] self-manifest wisdom’s pure realm, Richly Adorned,
Where the self-manifest body of perfect rapture in the five families’ assemblies appears
Endowed with the five certainties.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
chos sku de'i rtsal lam byin rlabs las rang snang ye shes lngas gdal ba'i zhing khams lhun grub stug po bkod pa'i dkyil 'khor nam mkha'i mtha' klas pa bsam brjod mtshan ma'i yul las 'das shing rgya chad phyogs lhung dang bral bar chos sku'i ye shes kyis bsdus pa'i rang snang longs spyod rdzogs pa sku rigs lnga'i tshom bu nges pa lnga ldan gyi bdag nyid can du snang zhing gdul bya'i spyod yul las 'das pa sku dang ye shes tha mi dad pa'i rol pa chen por bzhugs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The body of ultimate enlightenment’s dynamic expression or its blessings’ self-manifest five wisdoms diffused as a pure realm—spontaneously present Richly Adorned. Its sacred circle exceeds the bounds of space and surpasses domains of thought, expression, or characteristics; it is not limited or localized. There, the body of perfect rapture—the convergence of the natural manifestation of the body of ultimate enlightenment’s wisdoms—appears as the epitome of the five wisdom families’ assemblies endowed with the five certainties. These forms dwell as a supreme display of enlightenment’s indivisible bodies and wisdoms, which surpass disciples’ experiential domains.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
'khrul pa'i 'gro la brtse ba'i thugs rje skyes/ /phyag rgya'i gnas dang ba spu'i khung rer yang*/ /
'byung bzhi'i rdul snyed zhing khams tshad med bkod/ /chos kyi dbyings kun zhing dang sku yis gtams/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Loving compassion for deluded sentient beings arose:
They arrayed in the buddhas’ hand implements’ locations and within each of their pores
Immeasurable pure realms, as numerous as the four elements’ atoms,
Filling the basic space of phenomena with enlightenment’s pure realms and bodies.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de nas dus gzhan du gdod ma'i gzhi las gzhi snang du shar ba'i rtsal rang ngo ma shes pas rmi lam ltar 'khrul pa'i rgyu med bzhin du 'khrul pa ltar snang ba'i 'gro ba'i khams tshad med pa g.yo bar gzigs nas/ brtse ba'i thugs rje chen po skyes te de dag gi don du zhing khams rnam par bkod pa ni/ rang snang longs sku'i snang cha las rigs lnga'i rgyal ba gang chen mtsho'i sku nam mkha'i mtha' klas par bkod pa rnams kyi phyag rgya 'khor lo la sogs pa'i khong gseng gi gnas kyi pad+ma dang*/ ba spu'i khung bu re la yang spos chu'i rgyun gang chen mtsho 'babs pa'i dbyings na sa chu me rlung 'byung bzhi'i rdul phra rab ji snyed pa'i go thams cad na/ sangs rgyas kyi byin rlabs dang 'gro ba'i las kyis rang snang ba'i zhing khams chen po/ zlum po gru bzhi nar mo la sogs pa gzugs dbyibs rgya tshad bkod pa bsam gyis mi khyab cing tshad med pa bkod de/ chos kyi dbyings dang nam mkha' gang du khyab pa de tsam du sku gsung thugs yon tan phrin las dang de dag las shar ba'i zhing khams dang sku yis khyab par gtams shing rtag pa rgyun gyi 'khor lor 'gro ba'i don mdzad pa ni thog ma'i mgon po gcig gi 'dul zhing dang mdzad pa yin te rgya che zhing*/ thog ma'i dus 'di tsam nas byung dang mthar gyis mdzad pa 'di tsam na rdzogs so zhes mu dang mtha' gzhal bar mi nus so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
At another time, [sentient beings] had not recognized as their own the manifest appearances’ dynamic expression that dawned from the original basis. As in a dream, while there was no cause for delusion, they experienced seeming delusion. [Buddha Ever Excellent] saw the movement of beings’ immeasurable realms: great loving compassion arose within him and he created pure realms for their benefit.
The self-manifest body of perfect rapture’s appearing aspect arrayed itself as Victor Great Glacial Lake of the five wisdom families, whose physical dimensions exceed the bounds of space. Streams of scented water flow in brimming lakes from lotuses in the interstices of the [buddhas’] hand implements, such as a wheel, and from the hollow of each of their pores. From this sphere where the streams fell, in the space of the four elements’ every atom of earth, water, fire, and air, the buddhas’ blessings and beings’ acts create self-manifest great pure lands in immeasurable, inconceivable patterns of size, shape, and form, including round, square, and oblong. In them, enlightenment’s body, speech, mind, qualities, and activity, and the bodies and pure realms that arise from them, fill entirely wherever space and the basic space of phenomena reach; acts for beings’ benefit occur in this lasting, constant wheel.
This is one original lord’s deeds and realm of influence. It is vast: none can measure its extent or limits with such statements as, “It originated at just such a beginning; and finally, after this many acts, it will cease.”
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
chos sku 'od gsal rdo rje snying po'i zhing*/ /rang snang longs skur tshangs pa rnga sgra ste/ /
sprul sku'i dus na tshangs chen bskal pa zhes/ /skra tsam khyon la dus gsum tshad snyed kyi/ /
sangs rgyas rgya mtsho la sogs kun bzang gi_/mdzad pa ji snyed 'di yi khongs su 'du/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
In the context of the body of ultimate enlightenment, the realm
is called Luminous Vajra Essence;
In the context of the self-manifest body of perfect rapture,
Sound of Brahma’s Drum;
In the context of the manifest body, Great Brahma Eon.
On the space of a hair’s breadth are oceans of past, present, and future buddhas
In numbers equal [to the realms’ atoms], etc.
The extent of Ever Excellent’s deeds is gathered in this.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
bshad ma thag pa de dag kyang sangs rgyas sku gsum gyi snang ba la zhing khams kyi bye brag gsum du grags pa ste/ chos sku'i dus su 'od gsal rdo rje snying po'i zhing dang*/ rang snang longs sku'i dus su tshangs pa rnga sgra'i zhing dang*/ sprul sku'i dus su tshangs chen gyi bskal pa zhes bya la/ de dag gi rdul phra ba skra rtse tsam gyi khyon la'ang gdod ma'i mgon po nyid kyi sprul pa dus gsum du byon pa rdul phran tshad snyed kyi sangs rgyas rgya mtsho rnams dang*/ sogs khongs nas sems can gyi khams rgya mtsho'ang de snyed yod de 'byung ba bzhi dang nam mkhas khyab tshad thams cad tshangs chen bskal pa 'di'i khongs su 'du la/ der ma dag pa'i sems can rnams 'chi 'pho ba dang*/ skye zhing 'byung ba dang*/ sangs rgyas rnams mya ngan las 'da' ba dang*/ bstan pa gnas pa dang*/ nub pa dang*/ lam sgrub pa la sogs bde sdug gi snang ba sna tshogs la spyod pa'i tshul rmi lam ltar snang ba dang*/ de ltar rdul phran re re'i go na'ang ri gling rgya mtsho sogs zhing tshad med pa snang zhing der ma zad rdul gcig gi steng gi 'jig rten de'i rdul phra ba gcig la'ang sems can gyi khams tshad med pa gnas pa rnams bde bar gshegs pa'i rnam 'phrul dang*/ byang chub sems dpa' rnams kyi zhing sbyong ba'i smon lam gyi mthu chen po dang*/ sems can rnams kyi 'khrul snang gis las kyi tshogs mngon par 'du bgyis pa dang*/ chos nyid kyis rab tu thog pa la sogs pa'i rgyu dang rkyen gyis rab tu tshogs pa ste chos kyi dbyings la kun rdzob pa gdod nas grub ma myong bas don la med pa gsal snang yin pas de ltar snang du rung ba yin no/ /de ltar na gdod ma'i mgon po kun tu bzang po'i mdzad pa ji snyed pa thams cad zhing 'di dag gi khongs su 'du ba yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
These realms just mentioned are known as three specific realms in relation to the manifestations of enlightenment’s three bodies:
In the context of the body of ultimate enlightenment, the realm is called Luminous Vajra Essence; in the context of the self-manifest body of prefect rapture, Sound of Brahma’s Drum; and in the context of the manifest body, Great Brahma Eon. Upon each realm’s every atom, a hair’s breadth in dimension, appear the Original Lord’s own emanations who appear in past, present, and future—oceans of buddhas as numerous as minute atoms.
The word “etc.” [in the root text] alludes to similarly numerous oceans of sentient beings’ realms, and all their four elements and encompassing space: these are included within this Great Brahma Eon Realm. There, the experience of the myriad appearances of happiness and suff ering— including impure sentient beings’ death and transmigration, birth and development; the buddhas’ transcendence of sorrow; the Buddhist doctrine’s duration and disappearance; and practice on the spiritual path — appear as in a dream.
Thus, in the space of each minute atom, immeasurable realms appear, including an axial mountain, surrounding continents, and oceans. Moreover, on each single minute atom of those world systems appearing on each atom, immeasurable realms of sentient beings exist, brought together by causes and conditions, such as the joyful buddhas’ miraculous emanations, the great force of bodhisattvas’ aspirations to purify realms, the deluded perceptions of sentient beings’ manifest collection of karmic accumulations, and the results of the nature of reality.
In the basic space of phenomena, relative appearances have never been originally existent; thus, they are ultimately nonexistent vivid appearances that can thereby appear as they do. The totality of Original Lord Ever Excellent’s deeds is gathered within these realms.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="B">
[B. de'i rnam 'phrul rdo rje 'chang gis zhing 'dir zhi ba brnyes pa'i tshul]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="B">
How Buddha Vajra Bearer Attained Peace [B]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa rdo rje 'chang gis zhi ba brnyes tshul la gnyis/ dngos dang*/ mdzad pa'i khyad par ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) the actual topic [Vajra Bearer’s attainment of peace] and (2) his distinguishing deeds.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
dang po [1. dngos] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
Buddha Vajra Bearer’s Attainment of Peace [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
de las zhing 'di 'dul ched thabs mkhas 'phrul/ /dpag med sngon rol me tog mdzes chen la/ /
gser gyi rdo rje phul nas thugs mchog bskyed/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Among Ever Excellent’s deeds, he sent a skillful emanation to guide this realm:
Innumerable [eons] ago, he offered a golden vajra to Buddha Exquisite Flower
And developed the intention to attain supreme awakening.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de las zhing 'di'i gdul bya 'dul ba'i ched du thog ma'i sangs rgyas kun tu bzang po nyid kyis thabs la mkhas pa'i rnam 'phrul chen pos so skye rang ga mas sems bskyed pa ltar bstan nas sangs rgyas pa'i tshul dang mdzad pa'i rol pa bstan par mdzad de/ 'di nas bskal pa dpag tu med pa'i sngon rol du zhing khams rang bzhin rnam par bkod pa zhes bya bar thog ma'i mgon po'i rnam par 'phrul pas sangs rgyas me tog mdzes pa chen po la gser gyi rdo rje gcig phul nas dang por byang chub mchog tu thugs bskyed do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Among Buddha Ever Excellent’s deeds, he sent a great emanation, skillful in means, to guide disciples in this realm. As an ordinary individual, he demonstrated how to develop the mind of awakening, then exhibited the process of enlightenment and the display of a Buddha’s deeds. Thus, innumerable numbers of eons ago, in a realm known as Natural Array, the Original Lord’s emanation offered a golden vajra to Buddha Great Exquisite Flower and first developed the intention to attain supreme awakening.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
skye ba rim brgyud rgyal las chos gsan cing*/ /mnyam par gzhag mthar rin chen rnam bkod kyi/ /
ri rtser sangs rgyas chos sku'i dgongs par bzhugs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
In a series of incarnations he received the victors’ teachings. At the end of settling in evenness,
He attained enlightenment at the summit of Mount Perfectly Configured Profusion of Jewels
And dwelt in the realization of the body of ultimate enlightenment.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de nas skye ba rim par brgyud pa'i tshul bstan te/ de'ang skye ba gnyis nas khyim bdag legs sbyin gyisras nor bu'i phreng ba zhes par gyur nas sangs rgyas 'khor lo legs par spyod pa'i drung du chos mnyan/ de nas glog gi 'od ces bya ba'i sras bram ze'i khye'u legs byin ces par gyur te sangs rgyas dge ba'i blo gros las chos nyan cing lo bdun du ting nge 'dzin la mnyam par bzhag ste/ bdun cu rtsa lnga'i mthar rin po che'i phung po rnam par bkod pa zhes bya ba'i ri bo'i rtse mor mngon par rdzogs pa sangs rgyas pa'i tshul bstan nas chos sku'i dgongs par bskal chen gcig tu bzhugs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Then that emanation demonstrated a seeming series of incarnations. In the second of these, he was known as Jeweled Rosary, son of the layman Excellent Generosity; he listened to the teachings in the presence of Buddha Wheel of Excellent Conduct.
Then he became the brahmin boy Excellent Splendor, son of Lightning Flash. He listened to Buddha Virtuous Intellect’s teachings and settled in evenness within a meditative state for seven years. Seventy-five [years] later, he displayed the process of complete, manifest enlightenment at the summit of Mount Perfectly Configured Profusion of Jewels and dwelt in the realization of the body of ultimate enlightenment for a single great eon.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
gnyis pa [2. mdzad pa'i khyad par] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
Buddha Vajra Bearer’s Distinguishing Deeds [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
longs spyod sprin bkod snang char rdo rje 'chang*/ /gsang gsum mi zad rgyan gyi 'khor lo yi/ /
mdzad pa gsum cu drug la dbang 'byor ba/ /rigs brgya'i 'khor lo'i mgon po'i sku ru snang*/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
[Buddha] Vajra Bearer arose as the appearing aspect of the body
of perfect rapture’s array of clouds.
Having mastery of the three mysteries’ wheel
Of endless ornaments’ thirty-six deeds,
He appears in the form of lord of the wheel of the hundred
wisdom families.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de las longs spyod thams cad rdzogs pa'i sku rgyan dang kha dog gi 'khor lor rang byon cing de nyid kyi ngang las rang snang gi rgyal ba rigs lnga dkyil 'khor grangs las 'das pa'i sprin rang byung du bkod cing*/ snang cha las mtshan dang dpe byad yongs su rdzogs pa rdo rje 'chang gi skur byung ba ni thugs bskyed pa'i rten rdo rje phul ba las byung ngo*/ /de dag kyang sku gsung thugs mi zad pa rgyan gyi 'khor lo'i mdzad pa sum cu rtsa drug la dbang 'byor ba ste snying thig gi 'chad tshul phyogs gcig yin mdzad pa de dag kyang bya byed kyi mdzad pa ni ma yin te yon tan gyi ngo bo dang rtsal du rang shar ba'o/ /don la gong du smos pa ltar thog ma'i mgon po'i thabs la mkhas pa'i sgyu 'phrul tsam las tha mi dad cing gsang sngags kyi rgyud phal cher ston pa'i rdo rje 'chang dang snying thig yang gsang gi rdo rje'i gnas zab mo ston pa la kun tu bzang po dang*/ gzhan du dam pa dang da ka'i sangs rgyas dang*/ rdo rje sems dpa' sogs mtshan gyi rnam grangs du mas bsnyad pa rigs brgya'i dkyil 'khor rgya mtsho'i 'khor lo'i mgon po'i skur snang ba ste/ rtog bsdus las/ sems dpa' thog ma tha ma med/ /rdo rje sems dpa' dga' ba che/ /kun tu bzang po kun gyi bdag_/rdo rje snying po gtso bo'i gtso/ /gdod ma tha ma med phyir yang*/ /dam pa'i dang po zhes 'dod de/ /'khor lo kun gyi gtso phyir na/ /dam pa dam pa'i dbang phyug yin/ /zhes gsungs pa ltar ro/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Within that [immersion in the body of ultimate enlightenment], the body of perfect rapture naturally arose as a circle of colors and ornaments. Within that same continual state, innumerable clouds of the five wisdom families’ self-manifest victors’ sacred circles took shape, arising naturally. Among these appearances, Buddha Vajra Bearer’s body, with all the marks and signs of physical perfection, arose as a result of his offering of a vajra as the basis for his [initial] development of the mind of awakening. Moreover, all those [victors] had mastery of the thirty-six deeds of the panorama of endless ornaments of enlightenment’s body, speech, and mind.
This account reflects one aspect of the Heart Essence style of teaching on this subject;4 nevertheless, these deeds are not [deliberately] performed acts, but arise naturally as the qualities of enlightenment’s essence and dynamic expression.
4. “Heart Essence” here, and “Innermost Heart Essence” in the next paragraph, refer to the highest teachings of great perfection’s corpus of pith instructions, itself the highest of three approaches within that system.
Ultimately, as stated above, Vajra Bearer is merely the Original Lord’s skillful emanation, and not distinguishable from him. Many varieties of names indicate him, including teacher Vajra Bearer in most secret mantra tantras; Ever Excellent, teacher of the profound vajra subjects in the Innermost Heart Essence; and elsewhere, True First Buddha and Vajrasattva. He appears in the form of lord of the wheel of the hundred wisdom families’ ocean of sacred circles. A Compendium of Wisdom’s Concepts states:
Spiritual warrior, without beginning or end, Vajrasattva, supreme joy; Ever Excellent, master of all; Vajra Essence, chief of chiefs: Without origin or ending point, You are believed to be “the first sacred [buddha].” Chief of all sacred circles, You are the sacred powerful lord of true [buddhas].
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="C">
[C. de las gzugs sku gnyis kyi rnam par 'phrul pa snang tshul]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="C">
How Buddha Vajra Bearer’s Two Form Bodies’ Emanations Appear [C]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gsum pa de la/ gzugs sku gnyis kyi rnam par 'phrul pa snang ba'i tshul la gnyis/ longs sku dang*/ sprul pa'i sku bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: an explanation of how (1) enlightenment’s body of perfect rapture and (2) enlightenment’s manifest body appear.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="1">
dang po [1. longs sku] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="1">
How Enlightenment’s Body of Perfect Rapture Appears [1]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
phyir gsal mched pas phyed snang longs sku che/ /rnam snang gang chen mtsho yi gnas rnams su/ /
zhing dang nges pa lnga ldan rigs lnga'i rgyal/ /sgyu 'phrul rdo rje'i rol mo 'byams su klas/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The unfolding of outwardly appearing luminosity produces the
semi-apparent supreme body of perfect rapture.
In the residences of Buddha Illuminator Great Glacial Lake
Are found realms and the five wisdom families’ victors,
endowed with the five certainties:
The music of their vajra miraculous manifestations unfolds to infinity.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de'ang sangs rgyas gsang ba'i lam rim las/ lhun rdzogs rig pa rang snang ba'i/ /zhing dang gzhal yas gdan khri rgyan/ /'od zer du mar snang ba ste/ /zhes bshad pa ltar chos kyi sku chen po nang gsal chos nyid kyi ngang du bzhugs pa de nyid man shel gyi nang 'od kha dog lnga nyi zer gyi rkyen gyis gsal ba ltar rang snang gi yul la phyir gsal du mched pa'i ye shes kyi snang cha sku dang zhing khams tshad med pa la longs su spyod pa'i gnas su sprul pa'i bkod pa phyed snang longs sku zhes bya ba/ rnam par snang mdzad gang chen mtsho'i phyag gi mthil na pad+ma'i sdong po skyes pa'i 'dab ma dang ze phol rnams la zhing khams nyi shu rtsa lnga re brtsegs mar gnas shing zhabs kyi skyil krung man chad las spos chu'i rgyun dpag tu med pa 'bab pa dag tu'ang zhing khams drug cu re yod pa de rnams su nges pa lnga ldan gyi rigs lnga'i rgyal ba mtshan dang dpe byad rgya mtsho'i bdag nyid rtag pa rgyun gyi 'khor lor longs spyod pa bgrangs kyis mi long bar bkod pa de dag ni ye shes gang chen mtsho'i zhing dang sku'i bkod pa longs sku chen po'i mtshan gzhi ste de dag rdul gcig gi steng na rab 'byams rgya mtsho'i rdul snyed kyi zhing yang mi 'gal zhing sku gcig la rab 'byams rgya mtsho'i sku 'du ba dang*/ sku re res kyang zhing khams rab 'byams rgya mtshor khyab pa sogs sgyu 'phrul rdo rje'i rol mo 'byams klas pa gsang ba bsam gyis mi khyab pa'i gnas su shes par bya ste/ gsang ba snying po las/ stong gsum yungs 'brur 'jug tshul gyis/ /dbyings nas dkyil 'khor spyan drangs mchod/ /ces gsungs pa bzhin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Buddhaguhya’s Stages on the Path states:
Spontaneous, perfect awareness’s Self-manifest realms, celestial palaces, thrones, and ornaments, Appear as many lights.
As stated here, just as the catalyst of sunlight reveals a crystal’s inner five colored light, when the supreme body of ultimate enlightenment’s inner luminosity that abides in the nature of reality’s indwelling state unfolds in its self-manifest domain as outwardly appearing luminosity, its wisdom’s appearing aspects deploy in an emanated array of enlightenment’s immeasurable bodies and realms within a place of rapturous enjoyment. This array is known as the semi-apparent body of perfect rapture.
Buddha Illuminator Great Glacial Lake holds a lotus stem in his palm. On each of the petals and stamens growing from it, twenty-five realms rise in levels. Below his crossed legs, infinite streams of scented water flow; in each of these are sixty realms. In them are the five wisdom families’ victors arrayed in uncountable numbers, endowed with the five certainties, epitomes of an ocean of the marks and signs of a buddha’s physical perfection, enjoying their everlasting, continuous panorama. These are the array of Great Glacial Lake of Wisdom’s realms and bodies, the basis for the appellation, “supreme body of rapture.”
These do not contradict [the great way’s statement that] there are as many realms on each atom as there are atoms in infinite oceans of realms: vast oceans of enlightenment’s bodies converge in a single body; moreover, each such body encompasses oceans of pure realms. These and other forms of the music of their vajra miraculous manifestations unfolding to infinity should be understood to be subjects of inconceivable mystery. The Secret Essence Tantra states:
Just as the three-thousandfold cosmos fits into a mustard seed,
Invite the sacred circle from basic space, and present offerings.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
ston pa khyad par bdun dang phyi nang gsang*/ /mtshan dpe'i rgyan ldan rnam dag dkyil 'khor 'phro/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The teacher, endowed with seven special attributes and decorations of outer, inner, and secret marks and signs, Emanates a pure sacred circle.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
zhing khams de dag la mnga' dbang mdzad pa'i ston pa longs spyod rdzogs pa'i sku de'ang rang bzhin bdun gyi khyad par dang ldan pa yin te/ de bzhin nyid du nar son pa'i rang bzhin/ yon tan ma btsal bar lhun gyis grub pa'i rang bzhin/ ye shes mtha' dbus dang bral ba'i rang bzhin/ 'bras bu la mnga' mdzad kyang rang gi ngo bo bstan du med pa'i rang bzhin/ mnyam pa nyid mngon du mdzad kyang spyod yul dang bral ba'i rang bzhin/ gcig dang du ma las grol ba'i rang bzhin/ dus gsum 'du 'bral med pa'i rang bzhin te bdun gyi bdag nyid chen por lhun gyis grub pa nyid gdul bya'i dbang gis sku gsung thugs kyi mtshan ma sna tshogs par snang ba'i rnam 'gyur gyi cha las mtshan dang dpe byad kyi rnam par 'bar ba ste/ de'ang ston pa'i thugs ye shes bzhis phye ba'i rtsal las phyi'i mtshan dpe/ rtsa 'khor lo rnam par dag pa'i cha las nang gi mtshan dpe/ khams byang chub sems kyi rnam par dag pa'i cha las gsang ba'i mtshan dpe ste mdzes byed phul du gyur pa'i rgyan dang rang bzhin gyis ldan cing*/ zag pa med pa'i phung po lnga gshegs pa yab lnga/ khams lnga gshegs ma yum lnga/ spyan snyan shangs ljags te dbang po bzhi sa snying sogs nang sems bzhi/ gzugs sgra dri ro ste yul bzhi sgeg sogs bzhi/ mthong thos snom myang bzhi byams pa sogs phyi sems bzhi/ dus bzhi me tog ma sogs bzhi/ reg pa reg byed reg bya reg shes bzhi khro bo bzhi/ rtag chad bdag mtshan du lta ba bzhi khro mo bzhir rang bzhin gyis rnam par dag pas mtha' yas pa'i 'khor lo'i bkod pa dkyil dang 'khor gyi tshul du snang ba ste/
</d>
<d e="2">
The body of perfect rapture, the teacher with dominion over these realms, is further endowed with special attributes of the seven natures: (1) the nature of maturation in the way things are; (2) the nature of spontaneously present, unsought qualities; (3) the nature of wisdom free from center or limits; (4) the nature of mastery of the result, the essence of which cannot be demonstrated; (5) the nature of manifest equanimity, yet without an objective domain; (6) the nature free from one and many; and (7) the nature without joining or separation throughout past, present, and future.
Spontaneously present as the supreme epitome of these seven, the characteristics of enlightenment’s body, speech, and mind appear in myriad ways according to disciples’ degrees of acumen. Their changing aspects blaze as the appearances of the marks and signs of a buddha’s perfection. Among them, the teacher’s enlightened mind’s four wisdoms reveal outer marks and signs from [the teachers’] dynamic expression; inner marks and signs from the aspect of purification of their body’s channels and energy centers; and secret marks and signs from the aspect of their pure constituent, the awakened mind’s fluid. They are thus endowed with beautifying, magnificent ornaments and nature.
Inherently pure, infinite arrays of sacred circles, with a center and edge, appear—the uncontaminated five aggregates as the five male transcendent buddhas; the five elements as the five female transcendent buddhas; the four sense organs—eyes, ears, nose and tongue—as the four inner bodhisattvas, including Essence of Earth; the four objects of perception—form, sound, smell, and taste—as four goddesses, including Goddess of Charm; the four [perceptions]—sight, hearing, smelling, and tasting—as the four outer bodhisattvas, including Loving-Kindness; the four times as the four goddesses, including Goddess of Flowers; the four [aspects of perception]—contact, contact’s agent, contact’s object, and contact’s consciousness—as the four male wrathful deities; and the four [extreme] views—eternalism, nihilism, an existent self, and existent characteristics—as the four female wrathful deities.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gsang ba snying po las/ rang rig mtha' dbus med pa'i dkyil/ /ye shes bzhi 'phro 'khor lo'i tshul/ /zhes dang*/ khog gzhung las/ 'bras bu mthar phyin 'og min na/ /bzhugs pa dkyil dang 'khor gyi tshul/ /zhes bshad pa ltar dang*/ de dag kyang sangs rgyas rang snang gi ye shes rnam pa thams cad pa'i bdag nyid sgyu 'phrul drwa ba'i rol pa rnam pa kun tu zhing dang kun tu gdan la sogs par snang zhing*/ dbang po re res kyang dbang po thams cad kyi bya ba byed pa ste ye shes rtsal 'gag pa med pas chos kyi dbyings mtha' klas par khyab gdal ba'i phyir te/ seng ge rtsal rdzogs las/ kun tu bzang po'i zhal ni phyogs bcur gzigs/ /kun gzigs kun bzang sku la mdun rgyab med/ /phyogs bcu gang bar spyan gyis rnam par gzigs/ /zhes so/ /sangs rgyas kyi yul de ni sangs rgyas kho na'i rgyud kyis bsdus pa'i phyir sa bcu'i dbang phyug rnams kyi'ang spyod yul las 'das pa ste rang snang gzhi'i 'od gsal chen po'i snang cha dag pa rab 'byams kyi 'khor lo'i snod bcud du shar ba rmi lam dag pa dang chos mtshungs pa las rdul rdzas rang mtshan du grub pa cung zad kyang med do/ /snga phyir bshad pa'i longs sku chen po 'di gnyis 'char gzhi dang 'char cha'i dbye ba'ang shes par bya'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
The Secret Essence Tantra states:
Intrinsic awareness is the center free of middle or limits;
The four wisdoms emanate [around it] as a wheel.
The Framework Scripture states:
Having reached the final result, Unsurpassed Realm,
He dwells as [the sacred circle’s] center and periphery.
Moreover, these are enlightenment’s self-manifest wisdoms embodied in every circumstance, the net of magical illusion’s display, appearing as
realms everywhere, thrones everywhere, etc. Each sense organ even performs the functions of all sense organs, since wisdom’s dynamic expression is unobstructed and encompasses the infinite basic space of phenomena. The Lion’s Perfect Dynamic Expression states:
Ever Excellent’s face sees the ten directions.
All-seeing Ever Excellent’s body has no front or back.
His seeing eyes fill the ten directions.
Only a buddha’s mind can encompass a buddha’s experiential domain; therefore, what has been described transcends even the experiential domain of lord bodhisattvas of awakening’s tenth stage. Self-manifest supreme clear light of the basis of being’s appearing aspect arises as the worlds and beings of the panorama of infinite purity. Their appearances have the same qualities as those of a pure dream; apart from those qualities, they do not in the least exist in their own right as [things made of] substantial atoms.
Note that the former and latter presentations of the supreme body of perfect rapture refer respectively to the basis for what appears and that which actually appears.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="2">
[2. sprul pa'i sku bshad pa]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="2">
How Enlightenment’s Manifest Body Appears [2]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa sprul pa'i sku bshad pa la gnyis/ spyi dang bye brag go /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has two parts: (1) a general description of the manifest body and (2) a specific description of the manifest body.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="a">
[a. spyi]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="a">
A General Description of the Manifest Body [a]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dang po la gsum/ rang bzhin sprul pa/ 'gro 'dul sprul pa/ sna tshogs sprul pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
This section has three parts: (1) enlightenment’s natural manifestation,
(2) enlightenment’s manifestations to guide beings, and (3) enlightenment’s diverse manifestations.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="i">
dang po [i. rang bzhin sprul pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="i">
Enlightenment’s Natural Manifestation [i]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
de nyid shel la gzugs brnyan 'phos pa ltar/ /sa bcu pa la rang bzhin sprul sku'i zhing*/ /
sku dang ye shes chos sogs lnga lngar ston/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
That very [teacher], like an image transferred into crystal, Appears to tenth-stage [bodhisattvas] as the realms of enlightenment’s natural manifestation
In fivefold bodies, wisdoms, teachings, etc.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
dbyings snang longs sku chen po'i ston pa de nyid ji ltar dwangs shel la gzugs brnyan 'phos pa ltar cung zad dag pa'i gdul bya sa bcu'i dbang phyug rnams la snang ba ni 'di ltar rang bzhin sprul sku'i zhing khams dbus na 'og min dang*/ phyogs bzhir rim pa bzhin mngon par dga' ba/ dpal dang ldan pa/ pad+ma brtsegs pa/ las rab grub pa lngar ston pa de bzhin gshegs pa gzugs kyi rgyal po la sogs pa lnga po mtshan dang dpe byad rgya mtsho'i bdag nyid can zhi ba dang khro bo'i rnam 'gyur dpag tu med pa'i skus chos rnams 'jal zhing ston pa dang*/ gdul bya'i nyon mongs pa lnga'i gnyen por che ba'i zhing khams lnga dang*/ sku lnga dang chos lnga ye shes lnga la sogs pas brjod du med cing bsam mi khyab pa'i chos kyi 'khor lo bskor ba de nyid ston pa longs spyod rdzogs sku dang 'khor rgyud gzhan gyis bsdus pa'i phyir phyed snang rang bzhin sprul pa zhes nyi zla kha sbyor gyi rgyud chen po las gsal bar bstan to/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
That very teacher, the supreme body of perfect rapture, the appearance of basic space, appears to his disciples who are slightly pure, lord bodhisattvas of awakening’s tenth stage, like an image transferred into clear crystal. His appearance constitutes the five realms of enlightenment’s natural manifestation: Unsurpassed in the center; and Truly Joyous, Resplendence, Tiered Lotus, and Fully Accomplished Activity in the four directions. In these realms appear five teachers, such as Transcendent Buddha King of Form, who embody oceans of the marks and signs of a buddha’s physical perfection. In infinite numbers of peaceful and wrathful forms, they appraise and present the teachings. As antidotes to their disciples’ five afflictive emotions, their five great pure realms, five bodies, five teachings, five wisdoms, and other aspects turn the inexpressible and inconceivable wheel of the teachings.
Because [these appearances] are gathered within these teachings’ teachers — the body of perfect rapture — and the retinue — others’ streams of being — it is called the semi-apparent natural manifestation. This subject is clearly presented in The Great Tantra of the Union of Sun and Moon.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="ii">
gnyis pa [ii. 'gro 'dul sprul pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="ii">
Enlightenment’s Manifestations to Guide Beings [ii]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
de yi ngang las 'gro 'dul sprul pa'i sku/ /
mchog dang rig pa'i skyes bu thub pa drug_/
'gro drug gnas su 'dul bzhi'i cho 'phrul ston/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Within the continual [natural manifestation], manifestations to guide beings—
Sublime emanations and the six sages who embody awareness—
Demonstrate the four miraculous displays of training in the six kinds of beings’ abodes.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de nyid kyi ngang las 'gro ba 'dul ba'i sprul pa'i sku ni 'jig rten gyi khams ma lus par gdul bya'i tshogs yongs su smin par mdzad pa'i phyir tshad med pa'i thabs la mkhas pas rnam par rol pa bsam gyis mi khyab pa'i tshul gyis/ dus gcig tu phyogs bcu'i 'jig rten gyi khams rab 'byams thams cad du mdzad pa bcu gnyis kyi tshul ston pa mchog gi sprul pa'i sku ste/ de re re la'ang gdul bya rigs drug so so'i dbang shes la rang rang gi rigs dang mthun pa'i 'dul byed rig pa'i skyes bu thub pa drug tu sprul nas 'gro ba rigs drug so so'i don mdzad pa ste/ sgyu 'phrul bla ma las/ lha yi gnas na brgya byin mgon/ /lha ma yin na thags bzang ris/ /mi la bdud 'dul shAkya'i mgon/ /yi dwags gnas na kha 'bar te/ /byol song seng ge nyid du smra/ /dmyal ba las kyi gshin rje mgon/ /zhes so/ /de ltar gdul bya 'dul byed thabs kyi khyad par yang sku bsod nams chen pos 'dul ba/ thugs mngon sum pas 'dul ba/ rdzu 'phrul bsam gyis mi khyab pas 'dul ba/ gsung rig pas 'dul ba ste 'dul ba rnam pa bzhi'i cho 'phrul chen po mchog gi sprul pa'i sku rnams kyis dngos su ston la/ gzhan dag gis kyang shugs sam rjes mthun par bstan nas 'gro ba rnams 'dul bar mdzad do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Within the continual [natural manifestation], manifestations to guide beings appear in order to bring groups of disciples in every worldly realm to full spiritual maturity. Their skill in immeasurable techniques produces inconceivable displays: sublime emanations simultaneously demonstrate the Buddha’s twelve deeds in all ten directions’ infinite worldly realms. Further, in each of those, they manifest as six sages who embody awareness and guide disciples, the six kinds of beings, in forms corresponding to their species and attuned to their respective sense perceptions. They work for the benefit of each of the six kinds of beings. The Highest Miraculous Display [lists the six sages and their respective realms]:
In the gods’ realm, Lord Shakra, Among demi-gods, Vemachitra,
Among humans, the subduer of demons, Lord of the Shakyas,
In starving spirits’ abodes, Blazing Mouth,
The animals call him Lion,
In hell, Lord of Death, lord of deeds.
Sublime manifestations openly demonstrate the four miraculous displays of training using different techniques to guide disciples: by their body’s tremendous merit; their mind’s clairvoyance; inconceivable miraculous displays; and apt speech. Other manifestations demonstrate [such miracles’] power or similar acts to guide beings.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="iii">
gsum pa [iii. sna tshogs sprul pa] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="iii">
Enlightenment’s Diverse Manifestations [iii]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
sna tshogs sprul pa nor bu ljon shing gter/ /gru zam zas sman bzo skye nges pa med/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Diverse manifestations appear as varied artistic creations, incarnate beings,
Or inanimate substances—gems, trees, treasures, boats, bridges, food, or medicine.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag gi rtsal lam byin rlabs las shar ba'i sna tshogs sprul pa ni/ sems can rnams la gang phan pa chen po'i gzhir gyur to cog rnams te 'di ltar rang bzhin dang 'du byed las byung ba'i gzugs kyi sku dang*/ khang bzang*/ skyed mos tshal/ gan+d+ho la/ mya ngam gyi thang la grong khyer du sprul pa dang*/ dpag bsam gyi shing*/ yid bzhin nor bu/ gru gzings/ zam pa/ shing rta/ zas gos/ sman sogs bem po'i dngos po dang*/ mu ge'i tshe nya bo che/ nad kyis gdungs pa la srog chags des pa/ srin mo'i gling du cang shes b+ha la ha/ 'dam khrod du gser gyi bung ba sogs bzo dang skye ba'i sprul pa nges pa med pa sna tshogs su ston pa ste/ dkon mchog ta la la'i mdo las rgya cher gsungs pa bzhin no/ /phyi ma 'di dag ni rdo rje 'chang gis bkod pa'i tshangs chen gyi bskal pa zhes dbye ba phye ba yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Diverse manifestations arise from those [initial] manifestations’ dynamic expression or blessings; these are things that provide the basis for significant aid to sentient beings. They appear in such varied forms as diverse artistic creations or incarnate beings, and they include inanimate substances, such as sacred images produced naturally or deliberately, fine mansions, gardens, ghandhola spires, cities that manifest in the midst of desolate plains, wish-fulfilling trees, wish-granting gems, boats, bridges, conveyances, food, clothing, or medicine; or [such beings as] great fish in times of famine, noble creatures which cure the intense sufferings of sickness, the foreseeing horse Balaha in the land of female ogres, or golden bees in a swamp. The Lamp of Precious Jewels Discourse presents this subject in an extensive version.
These latter manifestations are classified as belonging to the Great Brahma Eon Realm created by Buddha Vajra Bearer.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="b">
[b. bye brag]
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="b">
The Manifest Body according to Great Perfection [b]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnyis pa bye brag rdzogs chen thun mong ma yin pa'i sprul pa'i sku phyogs gcig gi 'chad tshul la gnyis/ dngos dang*/ bstan pa'i btsas gsum bshad pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
A specific description of the manifest body according to great perfection’s single, extraordinary style of explanation has two parts: (1) the main topic, a description of the manifest body, and (2) an explanation of the three precious representations of the teachings.
</d>
</f>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="i">
dang po [i. dngos] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="i">
A Description of the Manifest Body [i]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
khyad par longs sku'i snang char bskal pa 'dir/ /dga' ldan brtsegs par snang ba dam pa nas/ /
rgyal byed tshal du shAkya thub pa'i bar/ /gnas ris bcu gnyis ston pa bcu gnyis byon/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
In particular, as appearing aspects of the body of perfect rapture
during this eon,
Twelve teachers have appeared in twelve places,
From Sacred Illuminator in Joyful Pinnacle
Until Shakyamuni in Jetavana Grove.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sprul pa'i sku'i bye brag khyad par du dbye ba/ rdzogs chen thun mong ma yin pa'i 'chad tshul phyogs gcig gi dbang du byas na/ longs spyod rdzogs pa'i sku'i snang cha las bskal pa bzang po 'di nyid du tshe lo dpag med nas brgya pa yan gyi bar la sprul pa'i sku bcu gnyis su byon te/ de'ang bskal pa dang por gnas dga' ldan brtsegs pa zhes bya bar ston pa khye'u snang byed dam pa bsam gyis mi khyab pa/ 'khor sangs rgyas stong rtsa gcig_/ston pa kun gyi rtsa ba sgra thal 'gyur/ sdud pa po lha'i bu dga' byed dbang phyug_/grogs lha'i bu nyi ma rab tu snang byed/ sems can rnams tshe lo dpag tu med pa thug pa'i dus na'o/ /pa gnas 'jig rten mi mjed du/ ston pa khye'u 'od mi 'khrugs pa/ 'khor mkha''gro ma 'bum phrag gnyis/ bstan pa sku gsung thugs yon tan phrin las kyi rgyud/ dus tshe lo bye ba'i dus na'o/ /gnas drod sher 'dus pa 'od kyis spungs par/ ston pa dpal 'jigs pa skyob pa'i yid/ 'khor byang chub sems dpa''bum phrag drug_/bstan pa 'khor ba dong sprugs dang*/ rma bya 'jing bsnol/ dpal 'byung bzhi zad pa'i rgyud rnams dang*/ dus tshe lo 'bum pa'i dus su'o/ /gnas chags 'byung mngal du snang bar/ ston pa gzhon nu rol pa rnam par rtse ba/ 'khor gnod sbyin dang srin po stong phrag gcig_/bstan pa sems sde rtsa ba'i rgyud lnga dang*/ yan lag gi rgyud drug_/dus tshe lo brgyad khri'i dus su'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
According to great perfection’s own extraordinary style of explanation, we can distinguish specific manifest bodies as emanations of the body of perfect rapture in the form of twelve manifestations that lived during this fortunate age from the time of a limitless life span until a hundred-year life span.
During the first era, in a place called Joyful Pinnacle, the teacher was the child Inconceivable Holy Illuminator, who taught a circle of one thousand buddhas. His teaching, during a period when sentient beings were capable of a limitless life span, was the basis of all teachings, The Unimpeded Sound Tantra; the compiler, the god Lord Creator of Delight, was assisted by the god Sun Illuminator.
In Endurance world-system, the teacher was the child Unwavering Luminosity, who taught a circle of two hundred thousand dakinis. His teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of a ten million-year life span, comprised the tantras of wisdom body, speech, mind, qualities, and activities.
In Heat and Moisture Gathering Light Mass, the teacher was Illustrious Mind that Protects from Fear, who taught a circle of six hundred thousand bodhisattvas. His teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of a one-hundred-thousand-year life span, was Emptying the Wheel of Life’s Depths, The Peacocks’ Entwined Necks, and The Glorious Tantra of the Four Elements’ Exhaustion.
In Appearance in the Womb of Conception, the teacher was Youthful Playful Frolic, who taught a circle of one thousand noxious spirits and ogres. His teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of an eighty-thousand-year life span, was the mind section’s five root and auxiliary tantras.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnas 'tsho byed gzhon nu'i ldum rar/ ston pa drug pa rdo rje 'chang*/ 'khor sangs rgyas rabs bdun la sogs pa/ bstan pa pha rol tu phyin pa drug sogs dang*/ dus tshe lo bdun khri'i dus su'o/ /gnas gsang chen rol pa dur khrod me ri 'bar bar/ ston pa gzhon nu dpa' bo stobs ldan/ 'khor byang chub sems dpa' sprin gyi shugs can bdun/ chos pha rgyud ma rgyud la sogs pa rgyud sde du ma dang*/ dus tshe lo drug khri'i dus su'o/ /gnas srin phug ru lu'i sgra dang ldan par/ ston pa drang srong khros pa'i rgyal po/ 'khor srin po bye ba gcig la/ chos rags pa 'dul ba'i rgyud bcu la sogs pa/ dus tshe lo khri'i dus na'o/ /gnas bya rgod phung po'i rgyal po'i khab na/ ston pa dgra bcom pa gser 'od dam pa/ 'khor 'phags pa nyan thos rdzu 'phrul dang ldan pa dpag tu med pa la/ dam pa'i chos 'dul ba khri phrag dpag tu med pa/ dus tshe lo lnga stong thub pa'i dus su'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In Medicinal Garden of Youth, the teacher was Vajra Bearer, the sixth [Buddha], who taught a circle that included the seven successive buddhas. His teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of a seventy-thousand-year life span, included the six transcendent perfections.
In Display of Supreme Mysteries, Charnel Ground Blazing Fire Mountain, the teacher was Youthful Powerful Warrior, who taught a circle of seven bodhisattvas, including Strength of Clouds. His teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of a sixty-thousand-year life span, included many classes of tantras, such as father tantras and mother tantras.
In Rulu Resounding Ogre Cave, the teacher was Seer Wrathful Monarch, who taught a circle of ten million ogres. His teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of a ten-thousand-year life span, included the ten tantras for subduing coarse phenomena.
In Vulture Peak of Rajgir, the teacher was the arhat Sacred Golden Light, who taught a circle of countless exalted pious attendants endowed with miraculous powers. His sacred teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of a five-thousand-year life span, was the infinite ten thousand [teachings on] monastic discipline.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gnas sog po g.yu'i smin ma can byang chub kyi shing rnam par rgyas pa'i drung du/ ston pa brtse bas rol pa'i blo gros/ 'khor sa brgyad pa'i byang chub sems dpa' rnams la/ chos phra rgyud bdun pa la sogs pa rnams gsungs/ dus tshe lo stong gi dus su'o/ /gnas bya rgod spungs par/ ston pa 'od srung bgres po/ 'khor tshe dang ldan pa bdun/ dam pa'i chos mdo sde dang kri ya/ lung a nu'i chos khri phrag brgyad la sogs pa gsungs/ dus tshe lo lnga brgya pa'i dus su'o/ /gnas rdo rje gdan byang chub 'byung ba'i shing drung du/ ston pa yab mngon rdzogs rgyal po/ 'khor rigs gsum mgon po la/ chos nges pa'i don 'ba' zhig gsungs/ dus tshe lo sum brgya pa'i dus su'o/ /gnas rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal mgon med zas byin gyi kun dga' ra bar/ ston pa shAkya thub pa/ 'khor rnam pa bzhi la/ chos bden pa bzhi'i 'khor lo/ sdug bsngal ba/ stong pa/ bdag med pa/ kun 'byung*/ rgyu dang*/ rkyen gyi rnam pa/ lam/ rig pa/ sgrub pa/ 'gog pa/ zhi ba/ gya nom pa ste lan bcu gnyis su bskor/ dus tshe lo brgya pa'i dus su ste/ de ltar gnas ris mi 'dra ba bcu gnyis su sprul pa'isku ston pa bcu gnyis su byon pa'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
In Turquoise Eyebrows in Mongolia, at the foot of the flourishing tree of awakening, the teacher was Love’s Display of Intelligence, who taught a circle of eighth-stage bodhisattvas. His teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of a thousand-year life span, included the seven subtle tantras.
In Vulture Peak, the teacher was the elder Guardian of the Light, who taught a circle of seven long-lived [seers]. His sacred teaching, during a period [when human beings were capable] of a five-hundred-year life span, included the discourses, kriya tantra, and eighty thousand teachings of the anuyoga transmission.
In Vajra Seat, at the foot of the source tree of awakening, the teacher was Father Consummate Monarch, who taught a circle of the lords of the three kinds of beings. He taught only the definitive meaning during a period [when human beings were capable] of a three-hundred-year life span.
In Prince Anatapindata’s gardens in Jetavana Grove, the teacher was Shakyamuni, who taught a circle of the four orders. His teaching was of the four truths, turning the wheel in twelve stages: suffering, emptiness, non-self, the origin of suffering, causes, circumstances, the path, awareness, the cultivation of awareness, cessation, peace, and excellence. He taught during a period [when human beings were capable] of a hundred-year life span.
As described, the twelve teachers of manifest enlightenment appeared in twelve different places.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
phun tshogs lnga ldan chos sgo drug cu'i bdag_/mdzad pa'i rnam grangs dgu bcu rtsa drug tshogs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
Endowed with the five magnificent qualities, these teachers epitomize the teachings’ sixty gateways.
Their deeds are enumerated in terms of ninety-six collections.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de dag kyang 'gro ba rnams kyi phung po lnga dag par bya ba'i phun sum tshogs pa lnga ldan gyi rang bzhin can lan bcu gnyis su snang bar mdzad pas bsdams na chos sgo'i rnam grangs drug cu tham pa'i bdag nyid can du gyur pa dang*/ mdzad pa phrin las kyi grangs kyang*/ kun mkhyen klong chen pas/ sku'i mdzad pa bcu gnyis ni gnas mi 'dra ba bcu gnyis su ston pa nyid sku mdog phyag mtshan mi 'dra ba bcu gnyis su sprul nas byon pas gdul bya rigs mi mthun pa bcu gnyis kyi tshogs mi 'dra ba dpag tu med pa'i don mdzad pa mi 'dra ba bcu gnyis mdzad pa'i mdzad pa zhes sku'i gzi mdangs la brten nas sku'i bstan pa 'phel ba'i don du byung ba'o/ /sku de dag gi dus su gsung chos kyi 'khor lo mi 'dra ba bcu gnyis gsungs pas 'gro ba'i ngag gi bcings pa mi 'dra ba bcu gnyis las grol bar mdzad pa'i mdzad pa zhes gsung gi bstan pa 'phel ba'i don du byung ba'o/ /gsung de tsam zhig gi tshe na thugs kyi dgongs pa mi 'dra ba bcu gnyis kyis 'gro ba'i rigs mi 'dra ba rnams kyi rtog pa bcu gnyis las grol bar mdzad pa'i mdzad pa zhes thugs kyi bstan pa 'phel ba'i don du byung ba ste/ de ltar bstan pa nges pa'i sprul pa'i sku gcig la chos kyi rnam grangs dgu bcu rtsa drug tshogs dgos te/ de dag dang ldan pa ni bstan pa'i bdag po zhes bya'o/ /gal te mi ldan na sangs rgyas 'jig rten du byon pa khol bu'i bstan pa zhes bya ste/ de dag kyang sngon gyi sems bskyed pa las byung ba'o/ /zhes khyad par du ma dang bcas te gsungs so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Moreover, these teachers, who are naturally endowed with the five magnificent qualities that act to purify beings’ five aggregates, appear twelve
times and thus epitomize a total of sixty gateways to the teachings. On the subject of the enumeration of their deeds of enlightened activity, omniscient Longchenpa describes their various distinctions:
Concerning the [teachers’] bodies’ twelve deeds: the teacher himself appeared in twelve different places, manifesting with twelve different colors and hand implements. These emanations performed what are known as twelve different acts of infinite benefit for different groups of disciples of twelve dissimilar affinities, acts done to spread the doctrine of wisdom body, based on [the teacher’s] brilliant physical glow.
While these bodies appeared, they taught twelve different wheels of the teachings’ speech. These performed what are known as acts that untie twelve different bonds of beings’ speech, done to spread the doctrine of wisdom speech. While this speech lasted, twelve different intentions of wisdom mind appeared, performing what are known as acts that liberate different kinds of beings from twelve concepts, done to spread the doctrine of wisdom mind.
Thus, the enumeration of the teachings of a single manifest body of the certain doctrine must have ninety-six collections. Teachers who possess them are known as lords of the doctrine; however, those without them all are known as buddhas who appeared in the world with a partial doctrine. Such buddhas, however, arose from their previous development of the mind of awakening.
</d>
</f>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="ii">
gnyis pa [ii. bstan pa'i btsas] ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="ii">
Explanation of the Three Precious Representations of the Teachings [ii]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
de dang dus mtshungs sku gsum bstan pa'i btsas/ /rang byung rdo rje glegs bam sku gzugs ni/ /
'gro ba gang gis mthong thos reg pas kyang*/ /gdos bcas rang sar grol ba'i phrin las can/ /
gang 'dul gnas 'phar da lta zhing 'dir bzhugs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
At the same time, representations of the three bodies’ doctrines appear:
A naturally produced vajra, book, and statue.
They have the enlightened activity of liberating in their own ground
Any being, along with that being’s material body, who sees, hears, or touches them.
They move to disciples’ abodes; at present they reside in this realm.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
sprul pa de dag dang dus mtshungs par sku gsum gyi bstan pa'i btsas chen po sku gsung thugs kyi sprul par rang byung du snang bas 'gro ba'i don mdzad pa ste dzam+bu'i gling 'dir chos sku'i bstan pa dngos rdzogs pa chen pa'i byin rlabs las rang shar ba rin po che brgya rtsa las 'khrungs pa'i rdo rje phyag gang ba dang*/ longs sku yongs su rdzogs par spyod pa'i bstan pa dngos rang byung bstan pa bu gcig pa'i byin rlabs las rang shar ba'i rin po che brgya rtsa gcig las 'khrungs pa'i glegs bam sor bzhi pa chos nyid kyi rang sgra sgrogs pa dang*/ sprul pa'i sku ston pa bcu gnyis kyi byin rlabs las rang shar ba rin po che brgya rtsa gcig las rang byung ba'i sku gzugs 'gro ba'i lus bongs dang mnyam pa ste/ de gsum ni 'dus ma byas pas skye 'jig med cing byin rlabs las rang byung du shar bas rdzu 'phrul dang yon tan dpag tu med pa 'jig rten gyi khams su byon dang 'byon 'gyur gyi sangs rgyas sprul pa'i sku rnams kyi sku gsung thugs kyi bstan pa 'phel bar byed pa'i rten yin la mthong thos reg pas gdos bcas rang dengs su 'gro ba'i phrin las kyi bdag nyid can no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
At the same time as those manifest teachers [appear], supreme representations of the three bodies’ doctrines, manifestations of enlightenment’s body, speech, and mind, naturally appear and work for beings’ benefit.
In this Land of Jambu, a hand-sized vajra born from one hundred precious substances naturally manifests by great perfection’s blessings. That vajra is the material representation of the body of ultimate enlightenment’s doctrine. A four-finger-width text that resounds with the nature of reality’s innate sound, born from one hundred and one precious substances, naturally manifest by the blessings of The Self-Arisen Doctrine Like an Only Child, is the material representation of the body of perfect rapture’s doctrine. A life-sized sacred image, naturally produced from one hundred and one precious substances, self-manifest by the twelve teachers’ blessings, is [the material representation of] the manifest body’s [doctrine].
These three are non-composite, and are thus not subject to creation or destruction. As they are produced naturally from blessings, they have infinite magical powers and qualities. For enlightenment’s manifest bodies that have and will appear in worldly realms, they constitute sacred supports that spread the doctrines of wisdom body, speech, and mind. They epitomize the activity of causing the natural dissolution of [any being], along with that being’s material body, upon seeing, hearing, or touching them.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
de ltar btsas gsum po de 'od gsal rdo rje rtse mos gang la 'dul ba'i gdul bya snang ba'i gnas der 'phar bas da lta zhing 'dir bzhugs shing ma 'ongs par zhing gzhan du 'phar ba na zhing 'dir rdzogs pa chen po'i bstan pa'ang mi 'byung ngo*/ /de'ang zhing 'di thog mar chags pa'i tshe bstan pa'i btsas gsum byang phyogs g.yo ba ldan ces bya ba'i zhing na bzhugs/ zhing 'dir ston pa khye'u snang ba dam pa byon pa'i tshe btsas gsum zhing 'dir 'phar te sku gsung thugs kyi bstan pas 'dul ba'i dus kyi dbang gis gnas so sor bzhugs shing*/ sku'i bstan pa'i dus su rdo rje ni o rgyan gyi yul rgya mtsho'i gling na bzhugs shing 'od dang sgra dang*/ dge slong rdzu 'phrul dang ldan pa'i sprul pa grangs med pa 'byung bar byed/ gsung gis bstan pa'i dus su ri ma la ya lag na rdo rje'i gnas su gnod sbyin gyi rgyal po rnams kyis phyag byed do/ /thugs kyi bstan pa'i dus su rdo rje gdan gyi steng gi nam mkha' la gnas so/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
These three precious representations move to where the clear light vajra pinnacle teachings can guide disciples. Therefore, they now abide in this realm; when they move to another realm in the future, great perfection’s doctrine will no longer appear in this realm.
At the time of this realm’s initial formation, the doctrine’s three representations dwelt in a northern realm called Movement. When the teacher, the child Inconceivable Holy Illuminator [the first of the twelve teachers of great perfection listed above], appeared in this realm, the three representations moved here. They remain in separate locations depending upon whether the doctrines of wisdom’s body, speech, or mind guide beings.
During the duration of the wisdom body’s doctrine, the vajra resides on a sea’s island in the land of Oddiyana and makes appear light, sound, and infinite numbers of emanated fully ordained monks endowed with miraculous powers. During the duration of the doctrine of wisdom speech, the vajra resides on Mount Malaya, Bodhisattva Vajra Holder’s abode, where the rulers of noxious spirits pay homage to it. During the duration of the wisdom mind’s doctrine, it remains in the sky above Vajra Seat.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
glegs bam ni sku'i bstan pa'i dus su rdo rje gdan gyi steng du dpag tshad lnga brgya 'phags pa'i nam mkha' la DA ki ma rnams kyis bzung nas gnas so/ /gsung gi bstan pa'i dus su sku gzugs rdo rje nyid dang lhan cig tu gnas so/ /thugs kyi bstan pa'i dus su rab tu khros pa drang srong gi phug par gnas so/ /sku gzugs ni sku'i bstan pa'i dus su 'di nyid kyi byin rlabs kyis sku dngos dang*/ sprul pa dang*/ yang sprul rnams dang lhan cig tu gnas shing*/ de dag gis zhal gyi dkyil 'khor la dngos su spyod pa'o/ /gsung gi bstan pa'i dus su/ gcig tu ma nges par 'dzam gling kun tu 'khor bar gnas te/ lha dang mi'i 'du ba khyad par can rnams kun gyis mchod pa'i gnas su 'gyur zhing*/ skabs su bstan pa la gnod pa byung ba'i tshe sku las 'od 'byung*/ zhal nas hU~M 'byung*/ spyan nas ye shes kyi me 'byung ngo*/ /thugs kyis 'dul ba'i bstan pa la/ sum cu rtsa gsum pa'i lha rnams kyi gzhal med khang lag na rdo rje'i khang brtsegs kyi yang thog na mnyam pa'i rang bzhin dpal chen po zhes bya bas phyag mdzad cing cho 'phrul rgya mtsho'i bdag nyid can du bzhugs so/ /de'ang tshe lo dpag med nas stong thub pa'i dus phan chad la skus 'dul ba'i bstan pa ste/ lo lnga brgya lnga stong phrag gsum yod do/ /de nas tshe lo bdun cu pa'i bar du gsung gis 'dul ba'i bstan pa ste/ lo lnga brgya lnga stong phrag gcig go_/de nas tshe lo bcu pa'i bar du thugs kyis 'dul ba'i bstan pa ste/ lo lnga brgya lnga stong phrag gcig go_/tshe lo de dag ni bstan pa de dag gis 'dul ba'i lo grangs te dus spyi'i yun tshad ma yin no/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
During the duration of the wisdom body’s doctrine, the book resides in the care of the dakinis five hundred leagues in the sky above Vajra Seat. During the duration of the doctrine of wisdom speech, it remains together with the statue and the vajra. During the duration of the wisdom mind’s doctrine, it dwells in the cave of Extremely Wrathful Seer.
During the duration of the wisdom body’s doctrine, the sacred image, by its own blessings, resides together with the teacher’s actual body, as well as with that teacher’s primary and secondary emanations, and he or she actually sees the sacred circle of its face. During the duration of the doctrine of wisdom speech, the sacred image does not stay in one location, but circles throughout the Land of Jambu and serves as the object of worship of all special gatherings of gods and humans. Occasionally, when the teachings are harmed, light shines from the image, [the sound of] Hung roars from its mouth, and wisdom’s flames pour from its eyes. During the duration of the wisdom mind’s doctrine, it remains on the highest floor of Vajra Holder’s building in the celestial palace of the gods of Heaven of the Thirty-Three. There, the one known as Magnificent One of an Even Nature worships it, and it embodies an ocean of miraculous displays.
Further, the time of limitless life span until that of one thousand years is the period of the wisdom body’s doctrine, which lasts seven million, five hundred thousand years. From that point until the human life span is seventy years is the period of the doctrine of wisdom speech, which lasts two million, five hundred thousand years. From that point until the life span is ten years is the period of the wisdom mind’s doctrine, which lasts two million, five hundred thousand years. These periods refer to the number of years of these doctrines’ influence; it does not represent the general measure of time.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'dir tshe lo bcu pa 'das nas btsas gsum lho phyogs mdzes ldan bkod pa/ byang phyogs langs pa skyob/ nub phyogs gtsug phud dbyangs rnams su rim par 'phar/ de dag thams cad la'ang 'byung ba'i dus bdun/ mi 'byung ba'i dus bdun te bcu bzhi res bstan pa dar nub tu 'gyur ro/ /de la dus bdun ni/ snying po ldan dang rdzogs ldan dang*/ /rdzogs ldan che dang nyis ldan dang*/ /sum ldan rtsod ldan rtsod ldan che/ /zhes so/ /de dag gi bar bar du nub pa ni mi 'byung ba'i dus te mun pa'i bskal par gsungs/ zhing de dag tu mdzad pa rdzogs nas rdo rje 'chang gis bkod pa'i tshangs chen gyis bskal par yod do cog gdod ma'i sar grol te snod bcud stongs nas btsas gsum po'ang chos nyid kyi ngang du rang yal te mi snang ngo*/ /slar gdul bya dbyings nas snang ba dang sprul pas tshangs chen bkod de btsas gsum po'ang rang shar ba sogs rtag pa rgyun gyi 'khor lor 'gro ba'i don mdzad pa nyid do/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
When the life span here becomes less than ten years, the three representations will move in succession to [realms known as] Elegant Configuration to the south, Protected Expanse to the north, and Melodious Top-knot in the west. Moreover, there will occur seven periods during which the representations will be present, and seven periods during which they will not be present—fourteen periods during which the teachings spread and decline, respectively. The seven times are
The eras of the essence, of completeness,
Of supreme completeness, of two-quarters,
Of three-quarters, of conflict, and of intense conflict.
The periods between these times, when the representations have vanished and do not appear, are said to be dark ages. After the completion of buddhas’ deeds in these realms, all that exists in Great Brahma Eon Realm created by Buddha Vajra Bearer is liberated in its original ground. The environment and its inhabitants having become void, the three representations disappear as well, vanishing of themselves into the nature of reality. Then, once again beings to be guided appear from basic space, enlightenment’s manifestation creates a Great Brahma Eon Realm, and the three representations naturally manifest as well, and so on. Thus, they work for beings’ benefit in an everlasting, continuous wheel.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
gzhan yang sku gsum re re zhing sku gsung thugs la phyi nang gsum re/ de re re la bzhi bzhir dbye ba'i mdzad pa sum cu rtsa drug re/ bsdams pas mdzad pa brgya rtsa brgyad du snang ba dang*/ longs sku rnam par snang mdzad kyi phyag mthil pad+ma'i ze'u 'brur zhing khams tshad med pa rnams nyi shu rtsa lnga re'i tshul du brtsegs mar yod pa'i bcu gsum pa thugs ka'i thad du mi mjed 'jig rten 'di yod pas rang bzhin rdzogs pa chen po'i bstan pa 'byung ba'i babs su gyur pa sogs chags gnas 'jig stong gi khyad par du ma dang*/ 'jig rten chags pa'i rjes su rin po che pad+ma'i ljon shing la chu rlung gi lha mo sogs 'jig rten srid pa'i sems can rnams kyi yid zhugs pa las pad+ma gsung sgra phyogs bcur 'phros pas bskul te/ sngon gyi gzugs med yin rung rnam shes gzung ba'i char gnas pa'i sa bon bag la nyal mngon gyur du sad de rnam par shes pa ting nge 'dzin gyis sprul pa'i lus su grub nas yod min med min sogs khams gsum rim par mched pas/ da lta'ang dbyings kyi rig pa lung ma bstan g.yos pas sems can glo bur ba'i 'khrul pa 'byung ba yod pa sogs thun mong ma yin pa'i bshad tshul rgya che ba rnams ni kun mkhyen chos rje'i gsung rab las rtogs par bya ba kho na'o/ /
</d>
<d e="2">
Moreover, each of enlightenment’s three bodies has realms corresponding to wisdom body, speech, and mind; and each of these has outer, inner, and secret realms. Each can be divided into four—thirty-six deeds for each [of enlightenment’s three bodies]. In all, they equal one hundred and eight.
In the palm of Buddha Illuminator of Form, the body of perfect rapture, there lies a lotus stamen. Upon it are immeasurable realms configured in stacks of twenty-five; at the thirteenth, directly at his heart, is located this realm Endurance, an ideal place for the teachings on natural great perfection to effortlessly arise. Such an event depends upon various conditions of [this world-system’s] formation, abiding, destruction, or vacuity. After the period of formation, goddesses of water and wind, etc., place the minds of the world’s possible sentient beings into a jeweled lotus tree. The sound of a lotus voice radiates in the ten directions as an invocation. This wakes into manifestation the latent seeds that dwell in the fixation aspect of consciousness even of [beings of the] formless [heavens]. These consciousnesses’ meditative states create emanated bodies that gradually spread throughout the three realms, [beginning with the highest formless realm, absorption within] neither discernment nor no discernment. Thus even now, the haphazard movement of awareness in basic space produces the arising of sentient beings’ adventitious delusion.
These and many other extraordinary systems of teachings can be learned only in the writings of the omniscient lord of the teachings [Longchenpa].
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</b>
<b>
<f>
<d e="1" crumb="D">
bzhi pa [D] zhar byung 'phros srol gzhan gyi gleng bslang ba ni/
</d>
<d e="2" crumb="D">
A Supplementary Statement Concerning Other Teaching Traditions [D]
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1" root="2">
mdo dang sgyu 'phrul la sogs bshad srol ni/ /mtha' yas phyir na so so'i gzhung du rtogs/ /
</d>
<d e="2" root="2">
The ways in which The Discourse That Gathers Wisdom’s Realization, Vajrasattva’s Net of Illusion Tantra, and other tantras explain these subjects are boundless;
Therefore, learn them from their individual source texts.
</d>
</f>
<f>
<d e="1">
'dir sku dang zhing khams kyi rnam gzhag man ngag rdzogs pa chen po a ti yo ga'i rgyud kyi rtsa ba sgra thal 'gyur/ a ti bkod pa chen po/ dpag bsam ljon shing rgyas pa'i rgyud chen po sogs kyi dgongs don zhang mkhas pa nyi 'bum dang kun bzang dri med 'od zer gyis zhib mor bkral ba'i rjes su snga 'gyur gyi mkhas pa phyi ma thams cad 'brangs te bshad pa ltar smras pa yin gyi/ gzhan du mdo'i lung chen po rnams dang rdo rje sems dpa' sgyu 'phrul drwa ba/ 'jig rten las 'das pa'i sgrub sde lnga la sogs pa'i bshad srol 'dzin pa'i mkhas pa ji snyed cig byon pa thams cad kyi bzhed tshul cung zad mi 'dra ba mtha' yas pa'i phyir na phyogs gcig tu bsdu mi nus pas shes par 'dod na so so'i gzhung 'grel rnams las rtogs par bya'o/ /'od gsal rdo rje rtse mo'i lugs kyi sku dang zhing khams khyad par du dbye ba skabs bzhi pa'i 'grel pa'o/ /
theg pa'i sgo kun las btus pa gsung rab rin po che'i mdzod bslab pa gsum legs par ston pa'i bstan bcos shes bya kun khyab ces bya ba las 'dul byed ston pa byon tshul rim par phye ba ste gnas gnyis pa'i 'grel pa grub bo// //
</d>
<d e="2">
The scholar Zhang Nyibüm and Ever-Excellent Drimé Özer [i.e., Longchenpa] elucidated in detail the intention concerning enlightenment’s bodies and pure realms of such texts as the fundamental tantras of atiyoga great perfection’s pith instructions, The Unimpeded Sound Tantra, The Great Array of Ati, and The Great Tantra of the Flourishing Wish-Granting Tree. All later scholars of the early translation school followed their example in their explanations, which is what I have related here.
Besides this presentation, a boundless number of slightly differing viewpoints exist, from as many scholars as have appeared, who preserve the teaching traditions of such sources as the supreme transmission of The Discourse That Gathers Wisdom’s Realization, Vajrasattva’s Net of Illusion Tantra, and the five classes of supramundane practices, etc. Therefore, I have not been able to gather them all in one place. If you wish to learn them, do so from their individual source texts and commentaries.
</d>
</f>
</b>
</b>
</b>
</book>
